TST3-MUC4-0001

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [INTERVIEW WITH FMLN COMMANDER HANDAL BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [HANDAL] WE ARE NOT DEMANDING THAT THEY STOP THEIR OPERATIONS AS A PRECONDITION FOR NEGOTIATING. HOWEVER, IT SHOULD BE CLEAR THAT WE ARE FACING THE SAME SITUATION AS BEFORE, THEREFORE, WE HAVE THE SAME RIGHTS AND WILL CONTINUE OUR OPERATIONS UNTIL A CEASE-FIRE IS AGREED.

IN CARACAS WE COMMITTED OURSELVES TO NEGOTIATING AND HOLDING TALKS IN ORDER TO OBTAIN A CEASE-FIRE AND THE NECESSARY AGREEMENTS FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE COUNTRY AND THE ENTIRE NATION.

THAT IS THE IMPORTANT ISSUE RIGHT NOW. WE HAVE BEEN FIGHTING WITHOUT THAT GOAL, WITHOUT HAVING ANY COMMITMENT TO NEGOTIATE ANYTHING. HOWEVER, THAT DOES NOT MEAN THAT THE SITUATION SHOULD REMAIN THE SAME. NOW THERE IS A NEW FACTOR, A COMMITMENT TO NEGOTIATE AND REACH AGREEMENTS ON ALL THOSE TOPICS. IT IS VERY IMPORTANT THAT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE KNOW THE CONTENTS OF THE AGENDA, THAT THEY ARE FULLY AWARE OF ALL THE TOPICS TO BE DISCUSSED, AND THAT THEY KNOW THE IMPORTANCE OF THE TIMETABLE AGREEMENT FOR DISCUSSIONS AND NEGOTIATIONS. YOU JOURNALISTS CAN HELP THE PEOPLE UNDERSTAND PROBLEM.

[REPORTER] [WORDS INDISTINCT] COMMANDER, WHEN DO YOU EXPECT THE FMLN TO JOIN THE PROCESS?

[HANDAL] LOOK, DEADLINES ARE NOT THE MOST IMPORTANT THING RIGHT NOW. WHAT IS IMPORTANT NOW IS COMPLYING WITH THE AGREEMENTS TO REACH POLITICAL AGREEMENTS. THAT IS THE MAIN ASPECT OF THE GENEVA AGREEMENT. IT IS POSSIBLE THAT SOME DEADLINES WILL NOT BE MET. IF DEADLINES ARE SET AND THE TIME FOR IMPLEMENTING THEM EXPIRES, THEN THIS IS TANTAMOUNT TO WASTING TIME. THIS THEN LEADS TO STEPS BEING DEMANDED THAT IN REALITY DEPEND ON THE POLITICAL AGREEMENTS THAT ARE REACHED AND NOT THE DEADLINES FOR REACHING THEM.

THEREFORE, ACCORDING TO THE AGENDA AND THE TIMETABLE AGREED TO HERE IN CARACAS, THE ACCENT IS ON THE POLITICAL AGREEMENTS. THOSE AGREEMENTS HAVE TO DO WITH CHANGES WITHIN THE ARMED FORCES. EVERYTHING RELATED TO THE ARMED FORCES MUST BE CHANGED. EVERY FACTOR CONCERNING THE ARMED FORCES MUST BE REVIEWED FROM A CERTAIN POINT OR PERSPECTIVE. CHANGES ARE NECESSARY; CHANGES MUST BE MADE AND THOSE CHANGES MUST BE SIGNIFICANT. THESE CHANGES MUST COMPLETELY TRANSFORM THE ARMED FORCES, BEGINNING WITH ITS ROLE AND INFLUENCE IN DETERMINING THE COUNTRY'S POLICIES AND GUIDELINES.

WE HAVE BEEN PRESENTING PROPOSALS IN THIS REGARD FOR SOME TIME. THE TOPIC OF DEMOCRATIZATION IS CLOSELY LINKED TO THE TOPIC OF THE ARMED FORCES, TO ITS PURGING, ITS REDUCTION, AND IN SUM, ITS END. WE BELIEVE THAT THE COUNTRY WILL NOT ALWAYS NEED THE ARMED FORCES. AS WITH ANY INSTITUTION OR HISTORICAL FACTOR, IT EMERGES, IT IS MAINTAINED FOR A CERTAIN TIME, AND THEN IT TENDS TO DISAPPEAR.

THE COUNTRY MUST HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO DEVELOP. IT CANNOT CONTINUE ALONG THE SAME PATH BECAUSE THIS WOULD ONLY REPRESENT EXPENSES AND A HEAVY BURDEN FOR THE COUNTRY.

FOR SEVERAL DECADES, THE ARMED FORCES HAVE MEANT ABSENCE OF LIBERTY, REAL SECURITY, AND THE IMPOSSIBILITY OF THE CIVILIAN SOCIETY TO DECIDE THE COUNTRY'S PATH. ELECTIONS HAVE BEEN TURNED INTO A MERE FORMALITY, WHERE THOSE WHO WERE NOT ELECTED RUN THE COUNTRY.

THE COUNTRY IS NOW GOING THROUGH A DRAMA THAT HAS ALSO SHOCKED THE INTERNATIONAL PUBLIC, THE MURDER OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS. EVERYONE IS AWAITING THE RESULTS OF THE INVESTIGATIONS AND HOPING THAT THOSE WHO WERE RESPONSIBLE FOR THIS CRIME WILL BE PUNISHED. WE BELIEVE THAT THE CASE OF JESUIT PRIESTS IS REALLY GRAVE; IT IS A DRAMA THAT REFLECTS THE DRAMA OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S HISTORY IN THE CURRENT CENTURY. [CONTINUED]

TST3-MUC4-0002

SAN SALVADOR, 10 JAN 90 -- [TEXT] THOSE ACCUSED OF THE ASSASSINATION OF SIX JESUITS WILL HAVE A "FAIR TRIAL" AND IF FOUND GUILTY, WILL BE PUNISHED WHETHER THEY ARE CIVILIANS, MILITARY, OR INFLUENTIAL PEOPLE, SUPREME COURT PRESIDENT DR MAURICIO GUTIERREZ CASTRO SAID.

THE TECHNICAL INVESTIGATION COMMISSION HAS DETERMINED THAT SOME MILITARY WERE REPORTEDLY INVOLVED IN THE ASSASSINATION OF THE SIX JESUITS AND THEIR TWO MAIDS, WHICH TOOK PLACE AT DAYBREAK ON 16 NOVEMBER, AS REPORTED BY PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI ON 7 JANUARY.

"THE LOCAL AND INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY CAN REST ASSURED THE SALVADORAN JUDICIARY SYSTEM WILL NOT HESITATE TO ENFORCE THE LAW UPON THE AUTHORS OF THIS HORRIBLE CRIME," DR GUTIERREZ POINTED OUT.

GUTIERREZ SAID HE DOES NOT KNOW HOW MANY PEOPLE ARE INVOLVED OR THEIR MILITARY RANKS, BECAUSE THE COMMISSION TO INVESTIGATE CRIMINAL ACTIONS IS STILL CONDUCTING INVESTIGATIONS AND HAS NOT PRESENTED ITS REPORT TO THE TRIBUNAL.

HOWEVER, GENERAL PROSECUTOR DR MAURICIO EDUARDO COLORADO MAINTAINED THAT THE MILITARY SUSPECTS "ARE REGROUPED AND HAVE BEEN PUT IN CUSTODY." HOWEVER, HE DID NOT REVEAL THE NAMES OR THE MILITARY RANKS OF THE SUSPECTS.

THE PROSECUTOR SAID THAT THE SCIENTIFIC TEST CONDUCTED BY THE COMMISSION TO INVESTIGATE CRIMINAL ACTIONS AND THE SPECIALIZED POLICE WORKING ON THIS CASE HAVE DETERMINED THAT THE CRIME COULD HAVE BEEN PERPETRATED BY ARMED FORCES MEMBERS.

"THE ATTORNEY GENERAL OFFICE WILL PROCEED ACCORDING TO THE LAW AND AGAINST WHOEVER TURNS OUT TO BE GUILTY, BECAUSE IT IS THE CONSTITUTIONAL DUTY OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE," COLORADO SAID.

ASKED ABOUT THIS ISSUE, JUSTICE MINISTER DR OSCAR ALFREDO SANTAMARIA, PRESIDENT OF THE COMMISSION TO INVESTIGATE CRIMINAL ACTIONS SAID: "WE UNDERSTAND THAT THE MOST RECENT INFORMATION ON THIS CASE WAS ANNOUNCED BY THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC A FEW DAYS AGO." HE REFUSED TO MAKE ANY FURTHER STATEMENTS.

NEW UCA [CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY] RECTOR JESUIT FRANCISCO ESTRADA ADMITTED PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI HAS TAKEN "A STEP FORWARD" BY UNMASKING THE SUSPECTS IN THIS CRIME, "BECAUSE HIS ETHIC PRINCIPLES DO NOT TOLERATE SUCH ATROCITIES."

ESTRADA SAID HE UNDERSTANDS WHY CRISTIANI, DURING HIS 7 JANUARY SPEECH, DID NOT GIVE ANY NAMES, "BECAUSE THE INVESTIGATIONS ARE STILL BEING CONDUCTED." MOREOVER, THERE MUST NOT ONLY BE ONE SUSPECT, BUT RATHER SEVERAL."

BEFORE MEETING WITH THE REPORTERS, THE UCA RECTOR MET WITH OFFICIALS FROM SCOTLAND YARD. A FEW DAYS AGO, HE ALSO MET SPANISH, CANADIAN, AND U.S. POLICEMEN WHO, AT THE GOVERNMENT'S REQUEST, ARE ASSISTING THE SALVADORAN COMMISSION IN CHARGE OF CLARIFYING THIS CASE.

TST3-MUC4-0003

LIMA, 10 JAN 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE NATIONAL POLICE REPORTED TODAY THAT OVER 15,000 PEOPLE HAVE BEEN ARRESTED IN LIMA OVER THE PAST FEW HOURS IN A DRAGNET AIMED AT UNCOVERING THE ASSASSINS OF FORMER DEFENSE MINISTER ENRIQUE LOPEZ ALBUJAR TRINT, WHO WAS MURDERED IN A TERRORIST ATTACK YESTERDAY. THE POLICE ALSO STOPPED 8,000 CARS IN THE SEARCH FOR ASSASSINS, WHO ARE PRESUMABLY MEMBERS OF THE MAOIST TERRORIST ORGANIZATION SHINING PATH.

LOPEZ ALBUJAR, WHO LEFT HIS POST AT THE MINISTRY IN MAY 1989, WAS RIDDLED WITH BULLETS AS HE WAS GETTING OUT OF HIS CAR IN THE LIMA RESIDENTIAL DISTRICT OF SAN ISIDRO. LOPEZ ALBUJAR, 63, WAS RETIRED. HE WAS DRIVING WITHOUT AN ESCORT.

ACCORDING TO THE SOURCES, THE CAR IN WHICH THE CRIMINALS FLED WAS ABANDONED IN SURQUILLO DISTRICT. THE DIRCOTE [COUNTERTERRORISM DIVISON] HAS IDENTIFIED ONE OF THE TERRORISTS AS GERARDO OLIVOS SILVA THROUGH A COMPOSITE MADE FROM WITNESS' REPORTS. THE POLICE SAY THAT OLIVOS SILVA, A FORESTRY ENGINEER, HAS PARTICIPATED IN OTHER ATTACKS AGAINST ARMED FORCES PERSONNEL IN THE PAST.

LOPEZ ALBUJAR'S MURDER HAS MADE A GREAT IMPRESSION IN PERU. ACCORDING TO POLITICAL OBSERVERS, THE INCIDENT IS BEING REGARDED AS AN INDICATION THAT THE SHINING PATH INTENDS TO CONTINUE ITS TERRORIST ATTACKS TO INTIMIDATE THE PEOPLE BECAUSE OF THE UPCOMING GENERAL ELECTION ON 8 APRIL.

SOME 1600 PERUVIANS WERE MURDERED DURING THE LAST QUARTER OF 1989 DUE TO THE POLITICAL VIOLENCE SURROUNDING THE 12 NOVEMBER MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS.

TST3-MUC4-0004

BOGOTA, 11 JAN 90 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 2) -- [TEXT] THE DIRECTORATE OF JUDICIAL POLICE AND INVESTIGATIONS [DIJIN] HAS DISMANTLED THE BOGOTA CARTEL FOLLOWING AN OPERATION IN WHICH 20 LUXURY HOMES WERE RAIDED IN DIFFERENT AREAS OF THE CITY. ACCORDING TO A DIJIN REPORT, THE POLICE INFILTRATED THE INNER STRUCTURE OF THE CAMILO ZAPATA VASQUEZ FAMILY. THE NOTICIERO DE LAS SIETE NEWSCAST MANAGED TO SHOOT VIDEO FOOTAGE OF THE RAID ON THE LA MARIA FARM ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF BOGOTA. HERE IS EXCLUSIVE FOOTAGE AND A REPORT BY WILLIAM CALDERON:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CALDERON] ANONYMOUS CALLERS INFORMED THE AUTHORITIES ABOUT LA MARIA FARM, A LUXURIOUS RANCH LOCATED NEAR ASUBA, A FEW KILOMETERS FROM BOGOTA. AT 1900, A GOES [SPECIAL OPERATIONS GROUP] TEAM SURROUNDED THE RANCH. AN AGENT MAKES SURE THE MAIN GATE IS NOT ELECTRICALLY WIRED, AND THE DECISION TO FORCIBLY ENTER THE HOUSE IS MADE. THEY ALL COVER ONE ANOTHER AS THEY TAKE THEIR POSITIONS. THESE MEN ARE PERFECTLY TRAINED FOR THIS SORT OF WORK. THESE IS A LIGHT INSIDE THE RANCH HOUSE, SO THEY ASSUME SOMEONE IS INSIDE. TENSION RISES IN VIEW OF THE POSSIBILITY OF AN ARMED CONFRONTATION. AS HE APPROACHES THE RANCH, THE COMMANDER DECIDES TO STORM IT. MOMENTS LATER, SEVERAL MEN OPEN THE DOOR WITHOUT OFFERING RESISTANCE AND SURRENDER TO THE AUTHORITIES.

A PATROL ENTERS QUICKLY AND CONTROLS EVERY CORNER OF THE RANCH. OTHER UNIFORMED MEN SUPPORT THE OPERATION FROM OUTSIDE. THEY UNSUCCESSFULLY LOOK FOR CACHES. THESE THREE WORKERS WHO WERE DOING REPAIRS AT THE RANCH WERE DETAINED AS A PRECAUTION IN THE MAIN HALL. MEANWHILE, THE SEARCH CONTINUES IN OTHER AREAS OF THE HOUSE. THREE SAFES WERE HIDDEN IN DIFFERENT ROOMS OF THE RANCH HOUSE. ONE OF THE SAFES WAS BUILT INTO ONE OF THE EIGHT MARBLE-TILED BATHROOMS. THE HUGE KITCHEN WAS TEMPORARILY AT THE WORKERS' DISPOSAL. NEAR THE MASTER BEDROOM WAS A LARGE SWIMMING POOL WITH A GROUND-LEVEL WINDOW FROM THE SAUNA AND JACUZZI AREA. THERE WERE SEVERAL GAME ROOMS AND TENNIS AND SQUASH COURTS IN THE HOUSE.

THE AUTHORITIES NOW HAVE DOCUMENTS AND PHOTOGRAPHS, ALTHOUGH THE RESIDENTS OF THIS LUXURY RANCH HAD LEFT BEFORE THE RAID.

NINETEEN OTHER OPERATIONS WERE SIMULTANEOULSY CONDUCTED IN BOGOTA. THE AUTHORITIES SAID AFTERWARD THAT THEY FELT THEY HAD DISMANTLED THE BOGOTA CARTEL.

THE DIJIN RELEASED THE FOLLOWING REPORT: 10 PERSONS ARRESTED, INCLUDING JESUS EVELIO ZAPATA LOPEZ, THE ALLEGED HEAD OF THIS DRUG TRAFFICKING BAND THAT HAD INTERNATIONAL CONNECTIONS.

THE FOLLOWING WAS SEIZED: 3 CERTIFICATES OF DEPOSIT WORTH ALMOST 250 MILLION PESOS; 1 1977 PORSCHE SIMILAR TO THE ONE SEIZED FROM JORGE LUIS OCHOA IN 1988; 3 TOYOTAS, ONE OF WHICH WAS SOLD 4 MONTHS AGO BY AN ECUADORAN EMBASSY OFFICIAL IN BOGOTA; 3 REVOLVERS; 3 PISTOLS; 1 CARBINE; AMMUNITION; RADIO COMMUNICATIONS EQUIPMENT; 2 FALSE DIPLOMATIC LICENCE PLATES; AND CASH. [END RECORDING]

TST3-MUC4-0006

SAN SALVADOR, 13 JAN 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE BODIES OF HECTOR OQUELI, UNDERSECRETARY OF THE NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT [MNR] OF EL SALVADOR, AND GILDA FLORES, A MEMBER OF GUATEMALA'S SOCIAL DEMOCRATIC PARTY, WERE FOUND IN CUILAPA, GUATEMALA, NEAR THE BORDER WITH EL SALVADOR, THE RELATIVES OF ONE OF THE VICTIMS HAVE REPORTED. ACCORDING TO THE REPORTS, THE TWO BODIES APPEARED TO HAVE BEEN SHOT IN THEIR TEMPLES.

ONE OF OQUELI'S RELATIVES, WHO ASKED TO REMAIN ANONYMOUS, TOLD ACAN-EFE THAT THE SALVADORAN POLITICIAN STILL HAD HIS PERSONAL PAPERS, INCLUDING HIS PASSPORT, IN ONE OF HIS POCKETS.

THE MNR REPORTED ON 12 JANUARY THAT HEAVILY ARMED MEN IN CIVILIAN CLOTHES HAD INTERCEPTED A VEHICLE WITH OQUELI AND FLORES ENROUTE FOR LA AURORA AIRPORT AND THAT THE TWO POLITICAL LEADERS HAD BEEN KIDNAPPED AND WERE REPORTED MISSING.

OQUELI WAS TO FLY TO NICARAGUA TO JOIN AN INTERNATIONAL SOCIALIST DELEGATION WHICH WILL OBSERVE THE NICARAGUAN ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN.

ACCORDING TO THE RELATIVE, GUATEMALAN CIVILIAN SOURCES REPORTED FINDING THE BODIES TO HIM EARLIER TODAY,

OQUELI DEPARTED EL SALVADOR ON 13 NOVEMBER, 2 DAYS AFTER THE GUERRILLAS LAUNCHED THEIR LARGEST OFFENSIVE IN THE RECENT DECADE. REPORTEDLY, OQUELI HAD BEEN THREATENED WITH DEATH BY SEVERAL PEOPLE WHO, THROUGH A GOVERNMENT RADIO NETWORK, HAD ACCUSED HIM OF BEING AN "ACCOMPLICE" OF THE REBELS.

THE MNR, WHOSE SECRETARY GENERAL IS GUILLERMO UNGO, IS A LEGALLY REGISTERED PARTY WHICH FORMS THE DEMOCRATIC CONVERGENCE TOGETHER WITH THE SOCIAL CHRISTIAN MOVEMENT AND THE SOCIAL DEMOCRATIC PARTY.

TST3-MUC4-0007

TEGUCIGALPA, 7 FEB 89 -- [INTERVIEW WITH JUAN JOSE MEMBRENO, NICARAGUAN EMBASSY COUNSELOR, BY RENATO ALVAREZ] [TEXT] [ALVAREZ] IN THE ABSENCE OF NICARAGUAN AMBASSADOR FRANCISO LACAYO PARAJON, JUAN JOSE MEMBRENO, COUNSELOR TO THE NICARAGUAN EMBASSY IN HONDURAS, CHARACTERIZED AS RIDICULOUS, STATEMENTS MADE YESTERDAY BY LUIS FRANCISCO ORDONEZ REYES, WHO, ACCORDING TO POLICE, IS OF NICARAGUAN ORIGIN. ORDONEZ REYES ACCUSED JOSE JESUS PENA--ALLEGED CHIEF OF SECURITY FOR THE NICARAGUAN EMBASSY IN TEGUCIGALPA--OF MASTERMINDING THE 7 JANUARY ASSASSINATION OF CONTRA COMMANDER MANUEL ANTONIO RUGAMA.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MEMBRENO] WE CATEGORICALLY DENY THAT ALLEGATION. THESE ACCUSATIONS AGAINST THE EMBASSY ARE RIDICULOUS. THE EMBASSY HAS NO OFFICER OR EMPLOYEE WITH THE NAME OF THE MAN IDENTIFIED IN THE NEWS CONFERENCE. THERE HAVE ALREADY BEEN MANY ACCOUNTS OF THIS INCIDENT THAT POINT TO THE COUNTERREVOLUTION. WE CATEGORICALLY DENY THESE ACCUSATIONS AND CHARACTERIZE THEM AS RIDICULOUS. WE HAVE NO SECURITY OFFICERS AT THIS EMBASSY, ONLY DIPLOMATIC AND SUPPORT PERSONNEL. [END RECORDING]

[ALVAREZ] ALL THE PERSONNEL WHO WORK AT THE NICARAGUAN EMBASSY IN TEGUCIGALPA ARE APPOINTED BY THE FOREIGN MINISTRY, ACCORDING TO THE COUNSELOR.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MEMBRENO] ALL OUR PERSONNEL ARE NICARAGUANS. IN REGARD TO WHAT HE [ORDONEZ REYES] HAS INVENTED, WE THINK IT IS RIDICULOUS. WE ONLY HAVE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT PERSONNEL WORKING AT THE EMBASSY. [END RECORDING]

[ALVAREZ] REGARDING THE POSSIBILITY THAT COUNTERREVOLUTIONARY AGENTS INFILTRATED THE NICARAGUAN EMBASSY IN TEGUCIGALPA, COUNSELOR JUAN JOSE MEMBRENO REPLIED:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MEMBRENO] THIS HAPPENED AT THE AMBASSADOR'S RESIDENCE. THE AMBASSADOR LEARNED BY CHANCE THAT ONE OF THE RESIDENCE GUARDS WAS OF NICARAGUAN ORIGIN WITH ALLEDGED COUNTERREVOLUTIONARY LINKS. THIS IS WHAT HAPPENED. THIS CASE DID NOT OCCUR AT THE EMBASSY.

[ALVAREZ] IS MANAGUA INTERESTED IN ELIMINATING ALL THE CONTRA LEADERS LIVING IN HONDURAS OR ALL PEOPLE WHO ARE LINKED TO THE COUNTERREVOLUTION?

[MEMBRENO] ON THE CONTRARY, WE RESPECT PEOPLES' LIVES AND THAT IS WHY WE HAVE ALWAYS BEEN WILLING TO RECEIVE IN NICARAGUA ALL NICARAGUANS WHO WANT TO ACCEPT AMNESTY AND ALL THOSE WHO HAVE IN ONE WAY OR OTHER BEEN INVOLVED IN THE COUNTERREVOLUTIONARY CAMPAIGN.

[ALVAREZ] HAVE THERE BEEN ANY MORE ATTACKS AGAINST THIS EMBASSY OR ANY OTHER TYPE OF THREAT, AS OCCURRED A FEW DAYS AGO?

[MEMBRENO] NO, AFTER THE SHOOTING INCIDENT AT THE AMBASSADOR'S RESIDENCE, WHAT HAPPENED A FEW DAYS LATER--HERE AT THE EMBASSY--WAS THAT A CAR DROVE PAST THE EMBASSY AT NIGHT AND KNOCKED DOWN SOME SECURITY RAILS ON THE SIDEWALK. [END RECORDING]

TST3-MUC4-0010

SAN SALVADOR, 1 NOV 89 -- [COMMUNIQUE] [SALVADORAN NATIONAL COMMUNICATIONS SECRETARIAT] [TEXT] THE GOVERNMENT OF EL SALVADOR STRONGLY CONDEMNS THE TERRORIST ATTACKS CARRIED OUT WITH EXPLOSIVES TODAY AGAINST THE COMMITTEE OF MOTHERS OF POLITICAL PRISONERS AND MISSING IN EL SALVADOR AND AGAINST THE SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION. AS A RESULT OF THESE ATTACKS, SEVERAL PERSONS WERE WOUNDED AND OTHERS DIED. THE GOVERNMENT OFFERS ITS CONDOLENCES.

THE GOVERNMENT REPUDIATES THESE IRRATIONAL AND CRIMINAL ACTIONS AND THE TERRORIST ATTACK CARRIED OUT ON 30 OCTOBER BY THE FMLN AGAINST THE ARMED FORCES STAFF INSTALLATIONS, WHERE 1 CIVILIAN DIED AND 14 OTHERS WERE WOUNDED. IT IS EVIDENT THAT THESE ACTIONS ARE PART OF A PLOT WHOSE OBJECTIVE IS TO BLOCK THE DIALOGUE INITIATED BY PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI.

THE GOVERNMENT HAS ORDERED A CAREFUL INVESTIGATION TO DETERMINE WHAT HAPPENED AND TO FILE CHARGES AGAINST CRIMINAL GROUPS THAT HAVE UNLEASHED THIS INCREASED WAVE OF TERRORIST VIOLENCE TO CREATE A CLIMATE OF UNREST AND TO BLOCK THE ROAD TO PEACE.

FINALLY, THE GOVERNMENT OF EL SALVADOR REAFFIRMS ITS DETERMINATION TO CONTINUE THE SEARCH FOR PEACE THROUGH THE DIALOGUE, AND IT STATES THAT IN SPITE OF THESE BLOODY EVENTS, SALVADORANS MUST REMAIN CALM AND NOT GIVE UP HOPES TO FIND A SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT THROUGH CIVILIZED MEANS.

31 OCTOBER 1989, NATIONAL SECRETARIAT OF COMMUNICATIONS.

TST3-MUC4-0012

SAN SALVADOR, 7 FEB 89 -- [TEXT] THE ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND SAID AT THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY THAT IT DOES NOT AGREE WITH VIOLATING THE CONSTITUTION TO FAVOR THE FMLN PROPOSAL. THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY MET THIS MORNING WITH PRESIDENT DUARTE, AS COMMANDER IN CHIEF OF THE ARMED FORCES; DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL CARLOS EUGENIO VIDES CASANOVA; AND ARMED FORCES CHIEF OF STAFF COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE.

THE ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND TRUSTS THE POLITICAL PARTIES' MATURITY AND WILL SUPPORT ANY RESOLUTION THEY APPROVE CONCERNING THE FMLN PROPOSAL, THE DEFENSE MINISTER SAID FOLLOWING A PRIVATE MEETING WITH THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY'S DIRECTORATE BOARD AND POLITICAL COMMISSION.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GEN VIDES] I TOLD THE POLITICAL PARTIES: IF YOU WANT TO GIVE THEM ADVANTAGES SIMPLY BECAUSE YOU DO NOT WANT YOUR CANDIDATES TO WIN, GO AHEAD AND DO IT. THEY MUST DECIDE WHETHER THEY WANT TO GIVE AWAY THE ADVANTAGES OR NOT; BUT I THINK IT WOULD BE UNJUST. A DEATH SQUAD MIGHT SAY: WE DO NOT WANT PEACE AND WE WILL SET OFF BOMBS UNTIL THE OTHERS CHANGE THEIR MINDS.

THIS IS NOT THE CASE RIGHT NOW. WE WOULD BE SIMPLY ESTABLISHING A PRECEDENT. THAT IS THE MAIN DANGER. IF THE CONSTITUTION IS CHANGED AT WILL TODAY THEN IT CAN BE CHANGED AGAIN TOMORROW, AND AGAIN UNTIL THINGS ARE JUST AS THE REBELS WANT THEM. [END RECORDING]

THE MEETING WAS ALSO ATTENDED BY NAPOLEON DUARTE, IN HIS ROLE AS COMMANDER IN CHIEF OF THE ARMED FORCES.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [DUARTE] I AM HERE AS COMMANDER IN CHIEF OF THE ARMED FORCES. I FULLY SUPPORT THE ARMED FORCES' DECISION CONCERNING ITS UNITY AND THE NEED TO [WORDS INDISTINCT] CONSTITUTION, AND THE WARNING THAT THE ARMED FORCES WILL NOT ADOPT POSITIONS TO HINDER THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS IN THE COUNTRY BECAUSE THERE HAS BEEN TOO MUCH BLOODSHED AND TOO MANY LIVES LOST ALREADY. [END RECORDING]

IT WAS REPORTED THAT THE FMLN PROPOSAL WAS THOROUGHLY ANALYZED DURING THE MEETING, AND IT WAS AGREED THAT THE CONSTITUTION CANNOT BE VIOLATED TO FAVOR MINORITY GROUPS' POSITIONS.

THE DEFENSE MINISTER ADDED: THE ARMED FORCES ARE STRONGER THAN EVER. HE ALSO REFERRED TO THE U.S. VICE PRESIDENT'S VISIT AND SAID THAT HIS VIEWS COINCIDE WITH THE ARMED FORCES' GOALS, PARTICULARLY CONCERNING HUMAN RIGHTS.

THE ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND'S VISIT TO THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY IS CONSIDERED THE SECOND STEP TAKEN IN RESPONSE TO THE FMLN'S PROPOSAL TO THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY. THE FIRST STEP WAS TO CALL A MEETING OF THE THE POLITICAL PARTIES, WHICH WAS NOT ATTENDED BY THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY BUT SERVED AS THE BASIS FOR FUTURE MEETINGS IN A SO-CALLED NEUTRAL PLACE.

THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY'S POLITICAL COMMISSION HAS NOT RULED OUT THE POSSIBILITY OF INVITING ARCHBISHOP ARTURO RIVERA Y DAMAS, WHO IS INVOLVED TO SOME DEGREE IN THE REBEL PROPOSAL.

TST3-MUC4-0013

CLANDESTINE, 2 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] THE FMLN REPORTS TO OUR PEOPLE AND THE PEOPLE OF THE WORLD THE FOLLOWING:

1. THE MASSACRE AGAINST THE SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION [FENASTRAS] WAS PLANNED IN COLD BLOOD. THE SITE AND THE MOMENT WHEN THE FENASTRAS LEADERS WERE MEETING HAD BEEN SELECTED.

2. WE HAVE TRUSTWORTHY INFORMATION FROM OUR INTELLIGENCE ORGANS THAT THIS ACTION WAS ORDERED BY COLONEL PONCE, THAT CRISTIANI KNEW ABOUT IT AND APPROVED IT, AND THAT IT WAS CARRIED OUT BY COLONEL ELENA FUENTE AS THE HEAD OF THE MORBID DEATH SQUAD OF THE ARMY'S 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE IN RESPONSE TO OUR MILITARY ATTACK ON THE ARMY STAFF. THIS BEHAVIOR BY CRISTIANI SHOULD SURPRISE NO ONE. TERRORISM IS AN OLD PRACTICE OF THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE [ARENA].

ONLY A FEW DAYS AGO, ARENA ASSASSINS TRIED TO KILL THE PRESIDENT OF THE MORTGAGE BANK, MR MASON, FOR NOT FOLLOWING THEIR ORDERS.

3. THE PEOPLE DEMAND THE RESIGNATION OF CHIEF OF STAFF COL EMILIO PONCE BECAUSE HIS RESPONSIBILITY IN THIS CRIMINAL ACTION IS REAL.

4. THE FMLN HAS PRUDENTLY TAKEN TIME BEFORE ADOPTING A DEFINITE POSITION. THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES HAVE ADOPTED AN IRRESPONSIBLE ATTITUDE AND HAVE BRAZENLY ACCUSED THE FMLN OF THE CRIMES THEY COMMIT.

IN VIEW OF THIS ATTITUDE AND OF THE PEOPLE'S INDIGNATION, WE HAVE TO PREVENT OUR PRESENCE AT THE DIALOGUE FROM BEING USED TO COVER UP THE GOVERNMENT'S RESPONSIBILITY IN THIS MASSACRE AND TO ENHANCE THE MASK OF MODERATOR AND NEGOTIATOR THAT CRISTIANI HAS BEEN USING TO SECURE POLITICAL SUPPORT AND U.S. FINANCIAL SUPPORT TO EXTEND THE WAR.

IN SAN JOSE, SPEAKING ON ITS VIEW OF THE WAR, THE GOVERNMENT SAID THAT IT CONSIDERS POPULAR MOVEMENTS AS SUPPORT ORGANIZATIONS OF THE FMLN, AND THEREFORE, AS ENEMIES OF THE GOVERNMENT IN THE ARMED CONFLICT.

WE DEMANDED THAT THE GOVERNMENT DELEGATION GIVE US A LIST OF THOSE ORGANIZATIONS, BUT TO NO AVAIL. THE TERRORIST ATTACKS AND MASSACRES ARE NOW YIELDING THE LISTS THAT WERE DENIED TO US AT THE DIALOGUE TABLE.

EVEN BEFORE THE SAN JOSE MEETING, THE GOVERNMENT HAD GREATLY INCREASED ITS REPRESSION. SINCE THE MEETING, IT HAS INCREASED ITS DETENTIONS AND ATTACKED THE RESIDENCES OF LEADERS OF THE SOCIAL CHRISTIAN PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT AND THE UDN [NATIONALIST DEMOCRATIC UNION], UNIVERSITY, FECMASAN [MSGR OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO FEDERATION OF COMMITTEES OF MOTHERS AND RELATIVES], AND FENASTRAS. MEANWHILE, CRISTIANI IS MAINTAINING HIS HYPOCRITICAL POSITION OF MODERATION.

THE MASSACRES, DETENTIONS, AND REPRESSION OF EARTHQUAKE VICTIMS, THE REPATRIATED, UNIVERSITIES, LABOR UNIONS, PEASANT COOPERATIVES, MOTHERS' ORGANIZATIONS, AND OTHER SEGMENTS OF THE POPULATION SHOW THAT THE WAR OF THE ARMED FORCES, GOVERNMENT, AND ARENA IS AIMED AGAINST THE PEOPLE AND, THEREFORE, THESE GROUPS CANNOT AND WILL NOT REMAIN IDLE.

THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE HAVE THE RIGHT TO TAKE UP ARMS AND EXERCISE THEIR LEGITIMATE DEFENSE. THE ARMED PEOPLE'S AND REVOLUTIONARY STRUGGLE HEADED BY THE FMLN IS JUST, LEGITIMATE, AND NECESSARY. [WORDS INDISTINCT] TWO-FACED CRISTIANI ADMINISTRATION, THE FMLN HAS DECIDED TO IMMEDIATELY CONTACT THE DIALOGUE OBSERVERS AND THE CHURCH, WHICH IS THE MEDIATOR, TO DEMAND THROUGH THEM GUARANTEES FOR OPPOSITION CIVIC AND LABOR GROUPS AND A REVIEW OF THE CURRENT CONDITIONS OF THE DIALOGUE, NEGOTIATION PROCESS, AND ITS PROSPECTS. MEANWHILE, WE BELIEVE THAT IT IS NECESSARY TO SUSPEND OUR PARTICIPATION IN THE CARACAS MEETING.

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND: COMMANDERS SALVADOR SANCHEZ CEREN, FRANCISCO JOVEL, SHAFIK JORGE HANDAL, EDUARDO SANCHO, AND JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS

EL SALVADOR, 2 NOVEMBER 1989

TST3-MUC4-0017

SAN SALVADOR, 14 APR 89 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [TEXT] FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] URBAN COMMANDOS HAVE DENIED REPORTS THEY PARTICIPATED IN AN ATTACK ON VICE PRESIDENT-ELECT FRANCISCO MERINO'S HOME.

AT 0530 THIS MORNING, UNIDENTIFIED INDIVIDUALS PLACED THREE EXPLOSIVE DEVICES AT THE MAIN ENTRANCE OF MERINO'S HOME IN THE MACHILIGUAS NEIGHBORHOOD. TWO OF THE DEVICES EXPLODED.

REPORTS INDICATE THAT THE PERPETRATORS, WHO ARRIVED IN A VEHICLE, ALSO FIRED AT THE GUARDS PROTECTING MERINO'S RESIDENCE. EARLY REPORTS POINTED TO URBAN COMMANDOS AS THE PRESUMED PERPETRATORS, BUT A SPOKESMAN FOR THE MODESTO RAMIREZ CENTRAL FRONT, IN A TELEPHONE CALL, DENIED THE REPORT.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [UNIDENTIFIED FMLN SPOKESMAN] ON THIS OCCASION, THE FMLN MUST EXPLAIN THAT OUR FORCES DID NOT PARTICIPATE IN THE ATTACK IN QUESTION. THE FMLN WARNS THAT THE ARMED FORCES ARE TAKING ADVANTAGE OF THE SITUATION TO CREATE CONFUSION AND PROMOTE TRUE STATE TERRORISM.

THE FMLN CONDEMNS THE [WORD INDISTINCT] AGAINST OUR PEOPLE AND WARNS THAT THESE ACTIONS WILL NOT BE ALLOWED TO TAKE PLACE WITHOUT THE APPROPRIATE RESPONSE. THE FMLN CLAIMS RESPONSIBILITY FOR ACTIONS IN WHICH IT IS DIRECTLY INVOLVED. IN THIS CASE, WE WERE NOT DIRECTLY INVOLVED. THE FMLN WARNS THAT THE ARMED FORCES ARE TAKING ADVANTAGE OF THIS SITUATION TO PERPETRATE ATTACKS ON INDIVIDUALS AND INSTITUTIONS WHICH CAN BE EASILY ATTRIBUTED TO THE FMLN. [END RECORDING]

THE FMLN DESCRIBED STATEMENTS MADE BY PRESIDENT-ELECT ALFREDO CRISTIANI AS IRRESPONSIBLE. THE PRESIDENT-ELECT IMMEDIATELY CONDEMNED THE ATTACK AND ATTRIBUTED IT TO THE URBAN COMMANDOS. AS A RESULT OF THE ATTACK, A 15-YEAR-OLD GIRL WAS WOUNDED AND CONSIDERABLE DAMAGE WAS REPORTED. MERINO IS CURRENTLY OUT OF THE COUNTRY.

TST3-MUC4-0018

SAN SALVADOR, 25 MAY 89 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] GUERRILLAS ATTACKED THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE GARRISON AND THE NATIONAL POLICE STATION IN SAN SALVADOR'S SACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD TONIGHT.

ACCORDING TO PRELIMINARY REPORTS, AT LEAST SIX FMLN GUERRILLAS WERE KILLED DURING THE ATTACK. THREE POLICEMEN, A SOLDIER OF THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE, AND FOUR CIVILIANS WERE WOUNDED AND TAKEN BY THE RED CROSS TO THE LOCAL HOSPITAL.

URBAN GUERRILLAS BEGAN THE ATTACK AT 1805. THEY STRUCK BOTH THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE AND THE NATIONAL POLICE STATION IN THE SACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [UNIDENTIFIED MILITARY OFFICER] THE GUERRILLAS USED 60-MM MORTARS AND RPG-18 ROCKET LAUNCHERS. THE TERRORISTS TRAVELED IN CARS. THEY DESTROYED SEVERAL POWER POLES ON 29TH STREET AND MACHINEGUNNED SEVERAL TRANSFORMERS. THE ATTACK CAME MAINLY FROM THE SOUTH, WHERE THE COHACHE ORGANIZATION IS LOCATED, AND FROM THE HONDUA CHURCH HERE. THEY ALSO ATTACKED FROM THE NORTHEAST, BUT MOST OF THE ATTACKERS CAME FROM THE DIRECTION OF THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY, FIRING FROM THERE AT SOME [WORD INDISTINCT] WE HAVE IN THE AREA. WE HAD REMOVED THE CORDON AROUND THE UNIVERSITY 4 OR 5 DAYS AGO, AND [WORDS INDISTINCT] FIRED FROM THERE.

THE WOUNDED INCLUDE AT LEAST THREE CIVILIANS, ONE OF WHOM IS IN SERIOUS CONDITION AND HAS ALREADY BEEN TAKEN BY OUR TROOPS TO THE MILITARY HOSPITAL; PERHAPS FIVE TRAFFIC POLICEMEN, ALTHOUGH THIS HAS NOT BEEN CONFIRMED; AND A SOLDIER OF THE BELLOSO BATTALION.

NO DAMAGE WAS CAUSED HERE AT THE GARRISON. ONLY A FEW SHELLS HIT THE GARRISON, AND THESE WERE 60-MM MORTAR SHELLS, WHICH ARE NOT POWERFUL ENOUGH TO CAUSE DAMAGE. WE FOUND SIX [WORDS INDISTINCT]. AS FOR THE RPG'S, WE FOUND ONLY ONE [WORDS INDISTINCT] BEHIND THE ANTEL [NATIONAL ADMINISTRATION FOR TELECOMMUNICATIONS] OFFICE [WORDS INDISTINCT]. WE FOUND SIX HOLES FROM M-79 SHELLS, BUT THEY DID NOT CAUSE GREAT DAMAGE.

ONE OF OUR CIVILIAN EMPLOYEES CAME OUT SLIGHTLY WOUNDED FROM THE [WORD INDISTINCT].

[REPORTER] COLONEL, OUR COUNTRY WILL HAVE A NEW PRESIDENT IN A FEW DAYS. THE FMLN HAS CALLED A NEW TRANSPORTATION STOPPAGE BEGINNING ON 31 MAY AND HAS NOW ATTACKED THE 1ST BRIGADE. BASED ON THIS EVIDENCE, DO YOU FEEL THE FMLN WILL INTENSIFY ITS MILITARY ACTIONS IN SAN SALVADOR?

[MILITARY OFFICER] OF COURSE, WE ARE EXPECTING THIS. CHANNEL 12 HAS ALREADY REPORTED THAT A TRANSPORTATION STOPPAGE WILL BEGIN ON 31 MAY. THEREFORE, WE BELIEVE VIGILANCE MUST BE INCREASED. WE EXPECTED THIS KIND OF ATTACK. WE HAVE ALWAYS SAID WE ARE PREPARED TO REPEL ANY TERRORIST ATTACK, AND THIS WAS A TYPICAL TERRORIST ATTACK. FROM A MILITARY STANDPOINT, I DO NOT THINK THE ATTACK WAS VERY EFFECTIVE. THE GUERRILLAS USED MORTARS BUT MOSTLY HURT CIVILIANS. [END RECORDING]

TST3-MUC4-0021

SAN SALVADOR, 16 JUN 89 (RADIO CADENA SONORA) -- [INTERVIEW WITH SALVADORAN VICE PRESIDENT AND INTERIOR MINISTER FRANCISCO MERINO BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] SALVADORAN VICE PRESIDENT AND INTERIOR MINISTER FRANCISCO MERINO REFERRED TO THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] DOCUMENT ISSUED HOURS AGO, WHICH DENIED ANY RESPONSIBILITY IN DR JOSE ANTONIO RODRIGUEZ PORTH'S DEATH:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MERINO] THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] HAS BEEN ACTING ERRATICALLY FOR SOME TIME; ALL ITS ACTIONS ARE QUITE ERRATIC. THE FMLN PLANS THAT THE ARMED FORCES RECENTLY SEIZED INCLUDE A STRATEGY IN WHICH THE FMLN IS TO CREATE CONFUSION AMONG THE POPULATION BY NOT CLAIMING RESPONSIBILITY FOR CERTAIN KINDS OF ACTIONS AND CRIMES. UNDER THESE GUIDELINES, THE FMLN HAS NOT CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR ITS ACTIONS, TO INSINUATE...[CHANGES THOUGHT] TO CREATE CONFUSION OR GIVE THE IMPRESSION THIS IS A VIOLENT SITUATION THAT HAS ARISEN BETWEEN POLITICAL GROUPS IN THE COUNTRY.

FORTUNATELY THERE IS EVIDENCE. THE ARMED FORCES HAVE THE DOCUMENTS THAT PROVE THAT THIS IS A STRATEGY CARRIED OUT BY TERRORIST GROUPS TO PERPETRATE THIS KIND OF ACTION AND PROVOKE A CONFRONTATION BETWEEN THE POLITICAL AND DEMOCRATIC FORCES IN THE COUNTRY.

OTHER VALUABLE INFORMATION HAS BEEN UNCOVERED, BUT I BELIEVE IT IS MORE APPROPRIATE FOR THE PUBLIC SECURITY AUTHORITIES TO REVEAL THIS. TERRORISTS HAVE RECENTLY ISSUED DECLARATIONS REVEALING THIS STRATEGY, THEIR MODUS OPERANDI, AND THE PLANS THEY HAVE FOR THE NEAR FUTURE. THEY HAVE PLANS TO CONTINUE DEALING BLOWS AGAINST THE NEW ADMINISTRATION THROUGH ITS OFFICIALS TO FORCE CONDITIONS FOR NEGOTIATIONS IN THE NEAR FUTURE -- AS THEY DID WITH FORMER PRESIDENT DUARTE'S GOVERNMENT. [END RECORDING]

VICE PRESIDENT MERINO ALSO REFERRED TO ANOTHER TOPIC IN THE NEWS, THE ANTITERRORIST LAW:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MERINO] WE UNDERSTAND THE BILL HAS ALREADY BEEN SENT TO THE NATIONAL ASSEMBLY. THERE IS [WORDS INDISTINCT] FOR THE DEFENSE OF DEMOCRACY, AND ANOTHER ONE THAT REFERS TO THE ANTITERRORIST LAW. THE TRUTH IS THAT THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH HAS BEEN QUITE CLEAR IN ITS POSITION, WHICH WAS STATED BY THE VICE PRESIDENCY.

THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH HAS CLEARLY STATED IT CANNOT LET THESE PEOPLE CONTINUE OPERATING WITHOUT RESTRICTIONS OR CONTROLS, VIOLATING THE LAW, DISRUPTING SOCIAL LIFE, AND DIRECTLY AFFECTING THE [WORDS INDISTINCT]. THE GOVERNMENT AND THE PEOPLE MUST BE PROTECTED BY EFFECTIVE LAWS SO THE PUBLIC SECURITY FORCES CAN CONTROL THE SITUATION AND SO THEIR ACTIVITIES ARE NOT INTERPRETED AS AN ABUSE OF AUTHORITY. [WORDS INDISTINCT] PENAL CODE THAT CONTEMPLATES ALL THE SENTENCES FOR TERRORIST CRIMES; HOWEVER, THEY HAVE PROVED INEFFECTIVE BECAUSE THEY MAY LACK THE PROCEDURES NEEDED IN OUR CURRENT SITUATION. THOSE LAWS DATE BACK MANY DECADES; IT WAS NEVER FORESEEN THAT EL SALVADOR COULD REACH THE CURRENT DETERIORATED SITUATION, IN WHICH PEOPLE ARE KILLED AND THE CULPRITS CALMLY WALK AWAY. NEWSPAPERS [WORDS INDISTINCT] SAY THAT SINCE WE ARE AT WAR, IT IS EASY FOR THEM TO KILL.

[REPORTER] IT IS RUMORED THAT THE LAW [PASSAGE INDISTINCT].

[MERINO] THE PROVISIONS ALREADY EXIST; ALL WE HAVE TO DO IS HARMONIZE THEM. WE MUST FULFILL OUR OBLIGATION. THE CONSTITUTION [WORDS INDISTINCT] STATED THAT EVERY SECONDARY LAW SHOULD BE HARMONIZED WITH THE CONSTITUTION. IN THIS CASE, THE PENAL CODE, THE PROVISIONS HAVE BEEN NEGLECTED TO A CERTAIN POINT, AND IT IS IMPERATIVE -- IF WE ARE GOING TO ABIDE BY THE CONSTITUTION -- TO ADAPT THEM TO OUR SITUATION. [WORDS INDISTINCT] SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND NO OFFICIAL OF A FRIENDLY COUNTRY CAN INTERFERE WITH THIS.

I RECENTLY TOLD SOME JOURNALISTS WHO ARE MY FRIENDS THAT VICE PRESIDENT QUAYLE'S GOAL WAS TO COME AND REAFFIRM HIS GOVERNMENT'S SUPPORT OF THE NEW SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT. HE DID IT ON THIS DATE BECAUSE ON 1 JUNE HE WAS IN CHARGE OF THE U.S. PRESIDENCY WHILE PRESIDENT BUSH WAS IN EUROPE. HIS VISIT TO EL SALVADOR WAS NOT A MERE COINCIDENCE. HE CAME TO REAFFIRM THE U.S. GOVERNMENT'S SUPPORT OF PRESIDENT CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT. [END RECORDING]

TST3-MUC4-0023

MOSCOW (USSR), 12 JUL 89 (PRAVDA) -- [STATEMENT] [SOVIET COMMITTEE FOR SOLIDARITY WITH LATIN AMERICAN PEOPLES] [TEXT] BLOOD IS FLOWING IN COLUMBIA, MORE ABUNDANTLY EVERY YEAR. LAST YEAR, ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL STATISTICS, THERE WERE 4,600 VICTIMS OF POLITICAL VIOLENCE. ABOUT HALF OF THOSE KILLED WERE PEASANTS. AN "INTERNAL WAR," UNLEASHED BY THE OLIGARCHY MANY YEARS AGO, IS BEING WAGED AGAINST THEM. THE ACTIVISTS OF THE COALITION OF LEFT-WING PARTIES AND ORGANIZATIONS, WITH THE PARTICIPATION OF THE COMMUNISTS -- THE PATRIOTIC UNION -- COME NEXT, AFTER THE PEASANTS. THE PEOPLE KILLED INCLUDE JAIME PARDO LEAL, PRESIDENT OF ITS NATIONAL COORDINATION COMMITTEE, AROUND 30 DEPUTIES, AND MANY MUNICIPAL ADVISORS AND MAYORS.

THE ORGANIZERS OF THE "DIRTY WAR" AND THE LEADERS OF THE "DEATH SQUADS," AND OTHER ULTRA-RIGHT-WING FORMATIONS AND THEIR HIRED KILLERS, FEEL THAT THEY CAN GO UNPUNISHED. THE RESPONSE TO THE TERROR OF THE RIGHT HAS THE ARMED STRUGGLE WHICH HAS CONTINUED FOR MANY YEARS AND LEFT-WING EXTREMISM.

IN THE PAST FEW YEARS, VICTIMS OF POLITICAL TERROR ALSO INCLUDED REPRESENTATIVES OF THE RULING CIRCLES AND THEIR LAW-ENFORCEMENT ORGANS, WAGING AN UNEQUAL STRUGGLE AGAINST THE POWERFUL NARCOTICS MAFIA. AS A "SHADOW ECONOMY," IT IS TRYING TO BECOME PART OF THE STATE STRUCTURE. IN THE PAST YEAR THE NARCOTICS BUSINESS HAS "ENRICHED" THE COUNTRY'S ECONOMY WITH $2 BILLION AND EVEN PROPOSED THAT IT WOULD PAY OFF THE GIGANTIC FOREIGN DEBT. THE NARCOTICS MAFIA CARRIES OUT REPRISALS AGAINST ITS OPPONENTS. THE MINISTER OF JUSTICE, A MEMBER OF THE SUPREME COURT, A DIRECTOR OF THE BIGGEST NEWSPAPER ESPECTADOR, AND, A FEW DAYS AGO, ANTONIO ROLDAN BETANCUR, GOVERNOR OF THE DEPARTMENT OF ANTIOQUIA WERE KILLED. MANY PROSECUTORS AND JUDGES ARE LEAVING THE COUNTRY THROUGH FEAR FOR THEIR OWN LIVES AND THOSE OF THEIR RELATIVES.

THE VIOLENCE IS ESCALATING AND THE IMPRESSION IS BEING FORMED THAT CERTAIN FORCES ARE TRYING TO TAKE THE ATTENTION OF THE 30 MILLION STRONG POPULATION OF COLOMBIA AWAY FROM THE URGENT RESOLUTION OF PRESSING SOCIAL PROBLEMS BY DESTABILIZING INTERNAL LIFE.

SOVIET SOCIETY, IN THE NAME OF OBSERVING BASIC HUMAN RIGHTS AND CHARITY, CONSIDERS THAT OUR CONSCIENCE CANNOT BE RECONCILED WITH THE ORGY OF POLITICAL TERROR OVERWHELMING COLOMBIA. WE APPEAL TO THE PUBLIC OF THE WORLD TO RAISE THEIR VOICES AGAINST THIS EVIL IN THE NAME OF THE COMMON SOLIDARITY OF MANKIND. DRASTIC ACTIONS ARE NEEDED PARTICULARLY ON BEHALF OF INTERNATIONAL AND NATIONAL LAW ENFORCEMENT ORGANIZATIONS.

WE CONSIDER THAT IN COLOMBIA ITSELF, DIALOGUE BETWEEN OPPOSING SIDES THAT ARE TAKING THE STAND OF PATRIOTISM AND POLITICAL REALISM IS NECESSARY. THE FRUITFULNESS OF NATIONAL DIALOGUE HAS BEEN PROVED IN PRACTICE IN THE PAST FEW YEARS BY MANY COUNTRIES. THE VITAL INTERESTS OF THE TORMENTED COLOMBIAN PEOPLE CALL FOR CIVIL PEACE.

TST3-MUC4-0024

BOGOTA, 14 JUL 89 (EMISORAS CARACOL NETWORK) -- [TEXT] FOR THE SECOND TIME, UNIDENTIFIED TERRORISTS DYNAMITED THE OIL PIPELINE BETWEEN HUILA DEPARTMENT AND BARRANCABERMEJA. MEANWHILE, ECOPETROL [COLOMBIAN PETROLEUM ENTERPRISE] WORKERS ARE REPAIRING THE CANO LIMON-COVENAS PIPELINE AND CLEANING UP THE ARAUCA RIVER ALONG THE VENEZUELAN BORDER, WHERE A HUGE OIL SPILL WAS CAUSED BY ANOTHER ATTACK AGAINST THE OIL PIPELINE.

AUTHORITIES CONFIRMED THAT THERE WAS A POWERFUL DYNAMITE EXPLOSION AT THE VINA-PUERTO SALGAR OIL PIPELINE, LOCATED APPROXIMATELY 30 KM FROM NATAGAIMA, IN NORTHERN HUILA DEPARTMENT, CAUSING AN UNDETERMINED AMOUNT OF CRUDE OIL TO SPILL.

THIS IS THE SECOND TIME IN LESS THAN 1 MONTH THAT TERRORISTS HAVE ATTACKED THE OIL PIPELINE OPERATED BY HOUSTON OIL AND ECOPETROL. A FEW WEEKS AGO, TERRORISTS DESTROYED THE PIPELINE NEAR AIPE, WHICH CAUSED ANOTHER OIL SPILL.

MEANWHILE, OPERATORS FROM THE STATE-RUN OIL COMPANY YESTERDAY BEGAN REPAIRING THE CANO LIMON-COVENAS OIL PIPELINE DYNAMITED ON THE NIGHT OF 12 JULY IN ARAUQUITA JURISDICTION, WHICH FORCED THE SUSPENSION OF OIL PUMPING FROM ARAUCA INTENDANCY'S OIL FIELDS TO THE GULF OF MORROSQUILLO.

MEMBERS OF THE CONTINGENCY TEAM SUPPORTED BY PETROVEN [VENEZUELAN PETROLEUM, INC.] AND THE VENEZUELAN ENVIRONMENT AND NATURAL RESOURCES MINISTRY ARE CLEANING UP A HUGE OIL SPILL AT THE ARAUCA RIVER CAUSED BY THE 7 JULY ATTACK AGAINST THE CANO LIMON-COVENAS OIL PIPELINE. THAT ATTACK RESULTED IN A SPILL OF 13,000 BARRELS OF OIL, WHICH SEVERELY CONTAMINATED FARMING AREAS AND THE ARAUCA RIVER, TO THE POINT THAT THE POTABLE WATER SERVICE WAS TEMPORARILY SUSPENDED IN ARAUCA'S CAPITAL CITY.

TST3-MUC4-0025

SAN SALVADOR, 21 JUL 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] SAN SALVADOR DOMESTIC SERVICE IN SPANISH AT 0202 GMT ON 21 JULY BROADCASTS A 1 HOUR AND 11 MINUTE LIVE OR RECORDED SPEECH "TO THE NATION" BY SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI ON "THE CURRENT SITUATION IN THE COUNTRY AND THE NATIONAL RECOVERY PLAN." NO DATE OR PLACE IS GIVEN.

CRISTIANI BEGINS BY SAYING THAT THIS IS HIS FIRST REPORT TO THE NATION AFTER 50 DAYS AS PRESIDENT. HE NOTES THAT SINCE HE ASSUMED POWER ON 1 JUNE, THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT HAS INCREASED ITS LEVEL OF VIOLENCE AND ITS NUMBER OF "INDISCRIMINATE KILLINGS." HE SAYS THAT THERE IS NO REASON FOR THIS SINCE HE EXPRESSED ON 1 JUNE HIS DESIRE FIND A PEACEFUL SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT IN THE COUNTRY.

CRISTIANI SAYS THAT SINCE 1 JUNE HE HAS REPEATEDLY CALLED FOR A PEACE DIALOGUE, ADDING: "IN ORDER TO BEGIN A DIALOGUE OF THIS NATURE, IT MUST BE HELD IN TWO PHASES: NATURALLY, DURING THE FIRST PHASE BOTH SIDES MUST SIT DOWN TO DISCUSS THE MECHANISMS TO DEVELOP THAT DIALOGUE PROCESS, A TIMETABLE FOR THE TALKS, AND THE PLACE WHERE THE TALKS WILL BE HELD. IN OTHER WORDS, THE FIRST PHASE WILL BE TO DETERMINE HOW THE DIALOGUE PROCESS WILL TAKE PLACE. THE SECOND PHASE -- ONCE AN AGREEMENT IS REACHED ON HOW THE DIALOGUE WILL BE HELD -- IS WHAT WILL BE DISCUSSED. IN THAT REGARD, OUR GOVERNMENT HAS NOT SET ANY CONDITIONS. WE ARE WILLING TO DISCUSS ANY TOPIC, BECAUSE WE KNOW THAT WE MUST FIND SOLUTIONS TO MANY THINGS, AND WE ARE WILLING TO DO SO. THE ONLY CONDITION WE HAVE DEMANDED FOR THIS DIALOGUE PROCESS IS THAT, ONCE IT BEGINS, IT SHOULD NOT BE INTERRUPTED FOR ANY REASON. WE BELIEVE THAT PEOPLE WANT PEACE AS SOON AS POSSIBLE, AND WE CANNOT HOLD TALKS FOR YEARS. ONCE WE SIT DOWN TO TALK, THAT DIALOGUE SHOULD CONTINUE UNTIL AN OVERALL SOLUTION IS FOUND TO THE CONFLICT. THAT IS OUR GOVERNMENT'S POSITION, AND WE MAINTAIN THAT POSITION BECAUSE WE BELIEVE IT IS THE MOST LOGICAL ONE."

TURNING TO ECONOMIC MATTERS, CRISTIANI SAYS THAT THE COUNTRY NEEDS TO SOLVE THREE PROBLEMS: THE FISCAL DEFICIT, INFLATION, AND UNEMPLOYMENT. HE SAYS THAT AS A FIRST STEP TO BEGIN THE NATIONAL ECONOMIC RECOVERY IS TO REFORM THE GOVERNMENT'S PRICING POLICY, ADDING: "WE MUST PROTECT LOW-INCOME GROUPS, AND FOR THIS REASON WE HAVE ASKED THE ECONOMY MINISTER TO BEGIN A PROCESS AIMED AT ELIMINATING PRICE CONTROLS. WE BELIEVE THAT WE CAN ELIMINATE PRICE CONTROLS ON 230 PRODUCTS WITHOUT HAVING A MAJOR IMPACT ON THE MAJORITY OF THE PUBLIC AND THAT WE CAN KEEP STAPLE PRODUCTS UNDER THE CONTROL OF THE ECONOMY MINISTRY." HE SAYS THAT PRICE CONTROLS ON STAPLES LIKE BASIC GRAINS, POWDERED MILK, FLOUR, COFFEE, SUGAR, VEGETABLE OIL AND LARD, CEMENT FOR HOUSING, AND OIL BY-PRODUCTS WILL NOT BE ELIMINATED.

REGARDING THE TRANSPORTATION SECTOR, CRISTIANI SAYS: "WE AGREED WITH THE TRANSPORTATION SECTOR TO DEREGULATE THE DIFFERENTIAL SERVICE. TO ALLOW THEM TO CONTINUE SERVING LOW-INCOME SEGMENTS OF THE POPULATION WHILE CHARGING CURRENT FARES, WE WILL ALSO ALLOW THEM TO OFFER THE HIGHER-PRICED SERVICE. IN OTHER WORDS, PEOPLE WILL BE ABLE TO CHOOSE WHAT KIND OF SERVICE THEY WANT TO USE: WHETHER THEY CONTINUE TO USE THE LOW-PRICED SERVICE OR A BETTER, MORE COMFORTABLE, AND FASTER SERVICE."

ON ELECTRICITY RATES, CRISTIANI SAYS: "WE FEEL THAT ADJUSTMENTS TO ELECTRICITY RATES SHOULD BE APPLIED AS A RESULT OF POWER THAT IS WASTED, THAT IS, BECAUSE IT IS POWER THAT IS BEING CONSUMED BEYOND WHAT IS NEEDED TO LIVE NORMALLY. THE INCREASE IN ELECTRICITY RATES WILL BE DIRECTLY PROPORTIONAL TO THE CONSUMPTION OF ENERGY IN EACH HOME. WE BELIEVE THAT WITH THIS INITIAL MEASURE, THE CEL [LEMPA RIVER HYDROELECTRIC EXECUTIVE COMMISSION] SOLVE PROBLEMS."

TURNING TO OTHER ECONOMIC MEASURES, CRISTIANI SAYS: "WE HAVE TO TAKE SHORT-TERM MEASURES TOO. IN THIS RESPECT, THE MOST LOGICAL STEP IS TO TAKE MEASURES THAT WILL AFFECT CONSUMPTION AND NOT REVENUES. THUS, WE HAVE ASKED THE FINANCE MINISTER TO TAKE MEASURES RELATED TO TAXES. HE IS TO CONSOLIDATE TAX PAYMENTS AND ONLY EXEMPT THE PREVIOUSLY MENTIONED BASIC BREAD BASKET ITEMS FROM THE PRESENT 5-PERCENT TAX. WE HAVE TO START ELIMINATING TAX EXEMPTIONS. ONLY EXPORTS SHOULD HAVE SOME TYPE OF MONETARY INCENTIVE BECAUSE OUR COUNTRY IS INTERESTED IN DEVELOPING ITS EXPORTS. THE REST OF THE COUNTRY'S ECONOMIC SECTORS SHOULD BE TAXED AT THE SAME RATE."

CRISTIANI ADDS: "WE ARE GOING TO MODIFY THE SYSTEM OF PAYING INCOME TAX. WE BELIEVE THAT THE CURRENT SYSTEM IS BASED ON UNJUST REGULATIONS, ON REVENUES EARNED THE PREVIOUS YEAR THAT DO NOT REFLECT A FIRM'S PRESENT SITUATION. THUS, WE ARE GOING TO REQUEST THAT INCOME-TAX PAYMENTS BE BASED ON A SMALL PERCENTAGE OF THE FIRM'S PRESENT SALES; THESE ARE A TRUER AND MORE ACCURATE REFLECTION OF A FIRM'S INCOME."

CRISTIANI SAYS THAT THE COUNTRY'S MONETARY POLICY MUST BE AIMED AT INCREASING SAVINGS TO PROMOTE DOMESTIC ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT. HE SAYS THAT IT IS NECESSARY TO MAKE INTEREST RECEIVED ON SAVINGS ACCOUNTS IN THE COUNTRY'S BANKS MORE ATTRACTIVE SO THAT CAPITAL DOES NOT LEAVE THE COUNTRY. REGARDING THE COUNTRY'S CURRENCY, CRISTIANI SAYS: "WE FEEL THAT CURRENCY VALUE SHOULD BE BASED ON THE AVAILABILITY OF AND DEMAND FOR FOREIGN EXCHANGE. WE DO NOT THINK IT IS APPROPRIATE FOR THE GOVERNMENT TO ARBITRARILY DEVALUE AND FIX AN EXCHANGE RATE ON THE SALVADORAN COLON. EVERYTHING MUST BE BASED ON THE FOREIGN EXCHANGE OUR COUNTRY MAY HAVE TO PAY OUT FOR IMPORTS, BECAUSE IF WE WERE TO FIX THE RATE AT 10 [COLONES] TO 1 [DOLLAR], THE CENTRAL BANKS STILL WOULD NOT HAVE ENOUGH FOREIGN EXCHANGE TO COVER ALL THE IMPORTERS' DEMANDS."

FURTHER DETAILS AS AVAILABLE.

TST3-MUC4-0026

SANTIAGO, 16 JUL 89 -- [STATEMENT] [CHILEAN SOCIALIST PARTY, PS] [TEXT]

1. DURING THE YEARS OF DICTATORSHIP, CHILEAN FOREIGN RELATIONS WERE DIVIDED INTO TWO PROCESSES. ON THE ONE HAND, AS THE DICTATORSHIP BECAME MORE AND MORE ISOLATED, IT WAS INCREASINGLY CONDEMNED IN INTERNATIONAL FORA AND REPUDIATED BY INTERNATIONAL PUBLIC OPINION. ON THE OTHER HAND, AS MORE AND MORE COUNTRIES AND ORGANIZATIONS EXPRESSED THEIR SUPPORT FOR A FREE CHILE AND GENEROUSLY GRANTED THEIR SOLIDARITY TO OUR CAUSE, OUR ORGANIZATIONS AND DEMOCRATIC PARTIES BECAME INCREASINGLY OPEN TO THE WORLD. THUS, THEY EXPANDED THEIR HORIZONS AND CONTRIBUTED THEIR EXPERIENCES.

2. DURING THIS PERIOD, THE PARTY HAS SUBSTANTIALLY STRENGTHENED ITS INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS AND ENHANCED ITS VISION OF THE INTERNATIONAL SITUATION. IT HAS STRENGTHENED ITS TIES WITH THE LATIN AMERICAN PEOPLES' REVOLUTIONARY AND DEMOCRATIC CAUSE, AND IT HAS FULLY IMMERSED ITSELF IN THE GREAT DEBATES OF WORLD SOCIALISM. TO THESE DEBATES WE BROUGHT OUR VIEWS ON A PROFOUNDLY RENEWED LEFTIST SOCIALISM COMMITTED TO DEMOCRACY, DEVELOPMENT, AND SOCIAL CHANGE.

3. OUR RELATIONS WITH THE PARTIES THAT MAKE UP THE INTERNATIONAL SOCIALIST [SI] AND WITH THE SI ORGANIZATION ITSELF HAVE BEEN ENRICHED WITHIN THIS CONTEXT. THIS STRENGTHENING OF TIES HAS BEEN THE RESULT OF TWO THINGS. FIRST, IT IS BASED ON THE POSITION THAT IN COMPLIANCE WITH ITS PRINCIPLES THE SI HAS UPHELD REGARDING THE CHILEAN SITUATION. IN OCTOBER 1973, A FEW DAYS AFTER THE COUP, SI CHAIRMAN WILLY BRANDT CONDEMNED THE END OF THE CHILEAN DEMOCRACY AND PRESIDENT ALLENDE'S ASSASSINATION AT THE UN GENERAL ASSEMBLY. AT THE TIME HE ALSO SAID THIS WAS A GREAT STEP BACKWARD FOR THOSE WHO ASPIRED TO ACHIEVE SOCIALISM THROUGH DEMOCRATIC MEANS. SINCE THEN, THE SI HAS BEEN PERMANENTLY MOBILIZED IN FAVOR OF CHILE BY MAKING THE CHILEAN CAUSE AND SALVADOR ALLENDE THE SYMBOLS OF ALL INTERNATIONAL STRUGGLE FOR DEMOCRACY AND CHANGE. IT IS WITHIN THIS FRAMEWORK OF INTEREST AND COOPERATION THAT THE VOICE OF CHILEAN SOCIALISM HAS BEEN HEARD AND OUR IDEAS AND PROPOSALS PRAISED.

4. THE SECOND REASON STEMS FROM THE PROCESS OF EXPANSION AND TRANSFORMATION EXPERIENCED BY THE SI IN THE PAST 2 DECADES. THE OVERALL PROCESS OF CHANGE THAT TOOK PLACE IN THE WORLD DURING THIS PERIOD -- THE TECHNOLOGICAL REVOLUTION, THE GROWING INTERDEPENDENCE AMONG NATIONS, EXPANSION OF COMMUNICATIONS, GLOBAL NUCLEAR AND MILITARY PROLIFERATION, THE EMERGENCE OF DEVELOPING COUNTRIES AS INTERNATIONAL COUNTERPARTS, THE WORSENING OF EXTREME POVERTY AND INTERNATIONAL INEQUALITIES, THE PROGRESS OF LIBERATION STRUGGLES IN THE THIRD WORLD, INTERNATIONAL AWARENESS OF THE VALUES OF DEMOCRACY AND HUMAN RIGHTS -- HAS ALSO EFFECTED MAJOR CHANGES IN THE IDEAS AND POSITIONS OF SOCIALIST PARTIES AROUND THE WORLD. IN THIS FRAMEWORK, THE SI HAS EXPANDED ITS OUTLOOK, HAS INCREASINGLY RENEWED ITS IDEAS AND, ABOVE ALL, HAS ACCEPTED PLURALISM WITHIN ITS FOLD AS WELL AS A BROAD INTERNAL DEBATE ABOUT THE BEST WAY TO PROMOTE THE CAUSE OF AN AUTONOMOUS, DEMOCRATIC SOCIALISM. IT SHOULD BE NOTED THAT THIS DEBATE ACQUIRED A DEMOCRATIC, ANTIFASCIST CONTENT AS A RESULT OF THE MAJOR ROLE PLAYED BY SOCIALIST FORCES THAT HAVE ENGAGED IN A LONG ANTIFASCIST STRUGGLE. [CONTINUED]

TST3-MUC4-0028

TEGUCIGALPA, 5 AUG 89 (LA VOZ DE HONDURAS NETWORK) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH HONDURAN PRESIDENT JOSE AZCONA HOYOS BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [TEXT] [REPORTER] MR PRESIDENT, ONE OF THE TOPICS TO BE DISCUSSED DEALS WITH THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN].

[AZCONA] I BELIEVE THAT AT THIS SUMMIT THE CENTRAL [WORDS INDISTINCT].

[REPORTER] HOW, MR PRESIDENT?

[AZCONA] WELL, I DO NOT KNOW. IT IS NOT EASY TO SOLVE THIS PROBLEM. NONE OF THE PROBLEMS WILL BE EASY TO SOLVE.

[REPORTER] IS THERE A POSSIBILITY FOR DIALOGUE?

[AZCONA] YES, BUT THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT WOULD ALSO HAVE TO HOLD A DIALOGUE WITH THE NICARAGUAN RESISTANCE.

[REPORTER] I AM THE VOZ DE NICARAGUA REPORTER. WHAT IS YOUR OPINION OF THE AGREEMENT REACHED BY THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT WITH THE POLITICAL PARTIES?

[AZCONA] WELL, I READ THE AGREEMENT LAST NIGHT AND BELIEVE IT TO BE A STEP FORWARD. INCIDENTALLY, I READ IT TWICE LAST NIGHT AND IT IS A VERY LONG DOCUMENT. I AM TALKING ABOUT THE AGREEMENT WITH THE PARTIES THAT ARE TRULY OPPOSITION PARTIES AND NOT THE ONE MADE WITH THE OTHER PARTIES BECAUSE THESE ARE NOT REALLY OPPOSITION PARTIES.

[REPORTER] WHAT I WANTED WAS YOUR OPINION ON THE DEMOBILIZATION OF THE CONTRAS FROM HONDURAS.

[AZCONA] OH, YOU ARE TALKING ABOUT THE SMALL DOCUMENT THAT MAKES DEMANDS, DEMANDS, AND MORE DEMANDS. THIS DOCUMENT HAS NO VALUE.

[REPORTER] I MEAN THE DOCUMENT SIGNED WITH THE 21 POLITICAL PARTIES...

[AZCONA, INTERRUPTING] THAT AGREEMENT IS VALUABLE BUT IT DOES NOT MENTION THE CONTRA DEMOBILIZATION. THE DOCUMENT STATES THAT THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT AND THE OPPOSITION PARTIES AGREE THAT THE ESQUIPULAS II AND COSTA DEL SOL AGREEMENTS SHOULD BE ABIDED BY. THIS IS THE DOCUMENT I READ TWICE, AND I BELIEVE IT IS QUITE SERIOUS AND A STEP FORWARD.

[REPORTER] WHAT WILL YOU DO TO GET THE MERCENARIES TO LEAVE YOUR COUNTRY?

[AZCONA] FIRST, I DO NOT USE DEROGATORY TERMS. THEY ARE NICARAGUANS WHO FOR DIFFERENT REASONS DISAGREE WITH THE SYSTEM IN NICARAGUA. THESE NICARAGUANS OPPOSE THE SYSTEM, AND FOR THIS AND OTHER REASONS THEY HAVE TAKEN UP ARMS AGAINST THE SYSTEM AND HAVE TAKEN REFUGE IN HONDURAS. I DO NOT USE THE TERM MERCENARY. I UNDERSTAND THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT USES IT AND IT IS ALL RIGHT FOR THEM TO DO SO, BUT I WILL NOT ANSWER A QUESTION THAT USES A TERM THAT I BELIEVE IS TOO DEROGATORY.

[REPORTER] THE DEMOBILIZATION PLAN HAS A VERY FIRM DEADLINE AND IS TO BE COMPLETED WITHIN 90 DAYS. DO YOU THINK...

[AZCONA, INTERRUPTING] NO, NO. THE 90-DAY DEADLINE IS INCLUDED IN AN AGREEMENT SIGNED BY NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT ORTEGA WITH THREE SMALL NICARAGUAN LEFTIST PARTIES. I DO NOT BELIEVE THIS DOCUMENT IS VERY IMPORTANT. I DO BELIEVE, HOWEVER, THAT THE AGREEMENT SIGNED BY THE NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT AND THE OPPOSITION PARTIES IS IMPORTANT BECAUSE IT IS BASED ON THE ESQUIPULAS II AND COSTA DEL SOL AGREEMENTS. [WORDS INDISTINCT] TERRORISTS IN EL SALVADOR AND CONTRAS ARE PRESENTLY NOT ACTIVE, SO BOTH SITUATIONS -- CONTRAS AND GUERRILLAS -- ARE DIFFERENT.

[REPORTER] IS IT TRUE THAT PRESIDENT CRISTIANI IS GOING TO PRESENT A PARALLEL PROGRAM AT THE SUMMIT?

[AZCONA] [WORDS INDISTINCT] PRESIDENT CRISTIANI COMES TO THE SUMMIT AS EL SALVADOR'S LEGITIMATE PRESIDENT. HE HAS THE RIGHT TO PRESENT HIS POINTS OF VIEW. HE HAS THE RIGHT TO CONTRIBUTE TO THE SOLUTION OF PROBLEMS IN OTHER COUNTRIES AS WELL AS TO ONES IN HIS OWN COUNTRY.

[REPORTER] IS THERE A POSSIBILITY THAT A DEMOBILIZATION PLAN FOR THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS WILL BE STUDIED AT THIS SUMMIT IF PRESIDENT CRISTINAI PRESENTS ONE?

[AZCONA] OF COURSE. HE HAS A RIGHT TO DO SO. [CONTINUED]

TST3-MUC4-0029

CLANDESTINE, 11 AUG 89 (RADIO FARABUNDO MARTI) -- [TEXT] WE HAVE REPORTS FROM THE FELICIANO AMA WESTERN FRONT AND THE ANASTASIO AQUINO PARA-CENTRAL FRONT:

THE FIRST REPORT INDICATES THAT AT 0745 ON 6 AUGUST, SNIPERS ATTACKED THE CIVILIAN DEFENSE POST IN THE VILLAGE OF EL AHOGADO, CANTON LA ISLA, METAPAN MUNICIPALITY. OUR FORCES INFLICTED ONE ENEMY CASUALTY. AT 1330 THAT SAME DAY, ENEMY POSITIONS LOCATED IN CERRO MAJATEPEQUE, MASAHUAT JURISDICTION, SANTA ANA DEPARTMENT WERE ATTACKED WITH RIFLE FIRE AND THEY SUSTAINED ANOTHER CASUALTY.

ON 7 AUGUST, OUR FORCES CLASHED WITH THE 2D INFANTRY BRIGADE, WHICH WAS CARRYING OUT AN OPERATION IN NORTHERN METAPAN. FOLLOWING IS THE RESULT OF THE CLASHES: AT 0900 WE INFLICTED TWO CASUALTIES, ONE WITH A MINE AND ANOTHER BY SNIPERFIRE NEAR FINCA EL PINAL. TWO MORE CASUALTIES WERE INFLICTED AT 1025 NEAR PLAN GALAN. WE INFLICTED TWO MORE CASUALTIES AT 1050, WHEN WE CARRIED OUT AN AMBUSH WITH RIFLE FIRE AT PUERTAS NEGRAS. TWO HELICOPTERS ARRIVED AT 1200; ONE WAS A TRANSPORT HELICOPTER AND THE OTHER WAS A ROCKET LAUNCHING HELICOPTER. OUR ANTI-AIRCRAFT UNITS OPENED FIRE [WORDS INDISTINCT] AND ONE OF THE HELICOPTERS FLEW ABOUT THE AREA FOR AN HOUR AND FIRED ROCKETS AT THE SITE OF THE CLASH. AT 1550, WE INFLICTED A CASUALTY WITH A MINE AT EL PINAL FARM, AND AT 1630 WE INFLICTED ANOTHER CASUALTY WITH A MINE. BY 1800, WE HAD INFLICTED 10 ENEMY CASUALTIES, THUS CONCLUDING THIS DAY OF VICTORIOUS COMBATS.

OUR COMBAT CONTINUED ON 8 AUGUST. OUR FORCES CLASHED WITH A COMBINED 2D INFANTRY BRIGADE AND NATIONAL POLICE PATROL IN THE VILLAGE OF LAS MARIAS, [NAME INDISTINCT] JURISDICTION. [WORDS INDISTINCT] AT FINCA MIRAMAR, INFLICTING THREE MORE CASUALTIES ON THE 2D INFANTRY BRIGADE TROOPS.

THE CLASHES CONTINUED ON 9 AUGUST: AT 1600, OUR SNIPERS ATTACKED THE 2D INFANTRY BRIGADE TROOPS NEAR FINCA EL LIMON, AND WE INFLICTED ONE CASUALTY.

IN SUM, WE HAVE INFLICTED 16 CASUALTIES ON THE ENEMY IN CLASHES THAT OCCURRED BETWEEN 6 AND 9 AUGUST.

TST3-MUC4-0030

BOGOTA, 17 AUG 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] TWO CRIMINAL ATTACKS, THE RESIGNATION OF THREE JUDGES, AND A 24-HOUR STRIKE BY WORKERS IN THE JUDICIAL SECTOR--THIS SUMS UP THE JUDICIAL SITUATION IN COLOMBIA OVER THE PAST 20 DAYS. THE CHAOTIC SITUATION UNLEASHED IN BOGOTA LAST NIGHT WITH THE ASSASINATION OF JUSTICE CARLOS VALENCIA BEGAN ON 28 JULY IN MEDELLIN, WHEN MOTORIZED PAID ASSASINS MURDERED THIRD PUBLIC ORDER JUDGE MARIA ELENA DIAZ. DIAZ' MURDER UNLEASHED A WAVE OF PROTESTS; 17,000 EMPEMPLOYEES FROM THE LEGAL SECTOR STAGED A STRIKE ON 1 AUGUST AND FORCED A STATEMENT FROM THE GOVERNMENT.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PRESIDENT OF NATIONAL ASSOCIATION OF THE JUDICIAL BRANCH ANTONIO SUAREZ] I AM WARNING THE COUNTRY THAT THE NEXT MURDER IN THE JUDICIAL BRANCH WILL NECESSARILY RESULT IN THE COLLECTIVE RESIGNATION OF ALL THE JUDGES. [END RECORDING]

PROTECTIVE MEASURES HAVE BEEN ADOPTED FOR ALL JUDGES AND WORK CONTINUES. ON 14 AUGUST, DUE TO DEATH THREATS AGAINST HIS DAUGHTER, FIRST PUBLIC ORDER JUDGE ALVARO MEDINA MORENO, WHO WAS INVESTIGATING THE WANUMEN ARMS-TRAFFICKING CASE AND THE ATTACK ON THE DAS [ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY] DIRECTOR, ANNOUNCED HIS RESIGNATION. TWO DAYS LATER, ON 16 AUGUST, DUE TO DEATH THREATS THE EIGHTH PUBLIC ORDER JUDGE IN MEDELLIN, WHO WAS INVESTIGATING THE GOVERNOR OF ANTIOQUIA'S MURDER, RESIGNED.

SHORTLY BEFORE JUSTICE VALENCIA'S MURDER YESTERDAY, THE SEVENTH PUBLIC ORDER JUDGE IN BOGOTA, WHO WAS INVESTIGATING THE SEARCH OF A BUILDING IN NORTHERN BOGOTA, DECIDED TO RESIGN AND LEAVE THE COUNTRY. TO CONCLUDE, THE INTIMIDATION OF JUDGES LED TO VALENCIA'S MURDER LAST NIGHT IN DOWNTOWN BOGOTA.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [UNIDENTIFIED WITNESSES] TWO PEOPLE APPROACHED VALENCIA AND BEGAN SHOOTING AT HIM. VALENCIA'S BODYGUARDS STOOPED DOWN, THEY DID NOT HAVE TIME TO RESPOND. WHEN THEIR ATTACKERS FLED, THE BODYGUARDS CAME OUT AND BEGAN SHOOTING WILDLY. IT WAS A DANGEROUS SITUATION FOR PEOPLE IN THE AREA. [END RECORDING]

STUPEFIED BY THE CRIMINAL ATTACKS ON THE JUDICIAL SECTOR, THE GOVERNMENT IS SEEKING WAYS TO SOLVE THE PROBLEMS OF INTIMIDATION.

MADRID EFE IN SPANISH AT 1824 GMT ON 17 AUGUST REPORTS THAT "ANTONIO SUAREZ NINO, PRESIDENT OF THE NATIONAL ASSOCIATION FOR THE JUDICIAL BRANCH (ASONAL), HAS REPORTED THAT ALL OF COLOMBIA'S JUDGES TODAY PRESENTED THEIR RESIGNATIONS BECAUSE OF THE ASSASINATION LAST NIGHT OF JUSTICE CARLOS VALENCIA GARCIA.

"THE PRESIDENT OF ASONAL ANNOUNCED THE RESIGNATION EN MASSE OF THE COUNTRY'S JUDGES, SAYING THEY WILL PRESENT THEIR RESIGNATIONS AT THE COUNTRY'S HIGHER COURTS, AND HE REQUESTED A MEETING WITH COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO.

"ASONAL PRESIDENT ANTONIO SUAREZ SAID THAT 'IN RESPONSE TO THIS HORRIBLE MASSACRE OF THE JUDICIAL BRANCH, WE HAVE DECREED AN INDEFINITE STRIKE AND THE RESIGNATION EN MASSE OF ALL THE JUDGES, BECAUSE THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE ARE NOT IN ANY CONDITION TO CONTINUE KILLING EACH OTHER WITH IMPUNITY WHILE THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH LOOKS ON ALMOST COMPLACENTLY.'"

"ASONAL ISSUED A COMMUNIQUE STATING THAT 'THIS GOVERNMENT LACKS THE AUTHENTIC POLITICAL RESOLVE TO GUARANTEE AND PROTECT THE INTEGRITY AND LIVES OF ILLUSTRIOUS FELLOW PATRIOTS SUCH AS VALENCIA.'"

TST3-MUC4-0031

HAVANA (CUBA), 19 AUG 89 (HACIENDO RADIO) -- [COMMENTARY] [ORLANDO CONTRERAS] [TEXT] DURING THE PAST FEW DAYS, VIOLENCE IN COLOMBIA HAS TAKEN SPECTACULAR TURNS. ACCORDING TO A REPORT WHICH CITES RELIABLE SOURCES, IT SEEMS THAT THE HAND OF DRUG TRAFFICKERS IS BEHIND THE ASSASSINATIONS OF JUDGE CARLOS VALENCIA, OF THE BOGOTA [WORDS INDISTINCT], WHICH OCCURRED YESTERDAY [18 AUGUST]. THE COLOMBIAN DRUG MAFIA HAS CREATED A GREAT MONEY AND CRIME EMPIRE IN COLOMBIA WITH POWERFUL RAMIFICATIONS OUTSIDE ITS BORDERS, ESPECIALLY IN THE UNITED STATES -- THE MAIN CONSUMER OF COCAINE AND OTHER DRUGS IN THE WORLD.

YESTERDAY [18 AUGUST], VENEZUELAN PRESIDENT CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ SPOKE ON THE PHONE WITH HIS COLOMBIAN COUNTERPART, VIRGILIO BARCO, AND IT IS SAID THAT THE MAIN SUBJECT OF THEIR CONVERSATION WAS THE RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN YOUTH DELINQUENCY AND DRUG TRAFFICKING. IT IS IMPORTANT TO NOTE THE WORDS OF VENEZUELAN PRESIDENT CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ. WE MUST REFLECT, SAID CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ, ON THE NEED FOR US, ALL VENEZUELANS, TO FACE DRUG TRAFFICKING IN VENEZUELA. WE MUST ALSO ACKNOWLEDGE THAT DRUG TRAFFICKING IS THE ABOMINABLE CRIME OF OUR TIMES, AND THAT THERE CANNOT BE ANY HESITATION OR COMPASSION TOWARD DRUG TRAFFICKERS. THOSE ARE THE WORDS OF VENEZUELAN PRESIDENT CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ.

IN REALITY, THE DRUG TRAFFICKING DRAMA IS SERIOUSLY AFFECTING SEVERAL LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES. WE HAVE THE DRAMATIC CASE OF COLOMBIA, BUT THE SITUATION ALSO EXISTS IN VENEZUELA, BOLIVIA, PERU, WELL, IN SEVERAL LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES. NOW, THE SOLUTION TO THAT PROBLEM...[REPHRASES] AS HAS BEEN POINTED OUT BY LATIN AMERICANS THEMSELVES AND THEIR MOST PROMINENT FIGURES, THE FINAL SOLUTION TO THE DRAMATIC DRUG TRAFFICKING PROBLEM MUST BE BASED ON PUTTING AN END TO THE CONSUMPTION OF DRUGS. THAT IS THE MAIN STUMBLING BLOCK IN THE FIGHT AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING. THE UNITED STATES IS THE MAIN CONSUMPTION CENTER OF DRUGS IN THE WORLD, AND U.S. POLICY ON DRUG TRAFFICKING IS NOT CONSISTENT WITH THE NEED TO PUT AN END AND ACTIVELY REPRESS THE CONSUMPTION OF DRUGS. U.S. POLICY, AND ALL THIS IS VERY WELL KNOWN IN LATIN AMERICA, IS BASED ON DESTROYING THE PLANTATIONS OF A NATIVE PLANT IN THE CONTINENT, WHICH IS COCA. PRESIDENTS, POLITICAL AND SOCIAL FIGURES OF THE CONTINENT HAVE SAID THAT THE SOLUTION IS NOT BASED ON THE DESTRUCTION OF A NATIVE PLANT BUT IN ACTIVE FIGHT AGAINST DRUG CONSUMPTION.

I THINK THAT THE STATEMENTS MADE BY THE PRESIDENT OF VENEZUELA AND THE DRAMATIC SITUATION THAT COLOMBIA IS FACING THESE DAYS CONFIRM THAT THE POLICY FOR FIGHTING DRUG TRAFFICKING MUST BE TENACIOUS, STRONG, WITHOUT HESITATION AND COMPASSION. IT MUST ALSO BE BASED ON ENDING DRUG CONSUMPTION BY THE UNITED STATES -- THE MAIN DRUG CONSUMER OF THE WORLD -- WHICH LIVES PRECISELY FROM DRUG CONSUMPTION AND ITS BUSINESS.

TST3-MUC4-0032

BOGOTA, 23 AUG 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] THE ISRAELI EMBASSY IN BOGOTA TODAY CONFIRMED THAT THERE ARE ISRAELI TERRORISTS IN COLOMBIA ENGAGED IN TRAINING RIGHT-WING PARAMILITARY GROUPS THAT, ACCORDING TO INVESTIGATIONS, ARE FINANCED BY DRUG-TRAFFICKING MAFIAS.

ISRAELI CHARGE D'AFFAIRS MICHEL RONEN ADMITTED THERE ARE SEVERAL ISRAELIS ENGAGED IN THAT ILLEGAL ACTIVITY, BUT WARNED THAT THEY DO SO "ON THEIR OWN AND DO NOT ACT ON BEHALF OF MY GOVERNMENT."

MOREOVER, THIS OFFICIAL DENIED THAT JUBIZ HAZVUMB, CAPTURED 22 AUGUST BY COLOMBIAN AUTHORITIES FOR HIS ALLEGED INVOLVEMENT IN THE MURDER OF SENATOR AND PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE LUIS CARLOS GALAN, WAS AN ISRAELI CITIZEN.

ACCORDING TO PRELIMINARY REPORTS REVEALED BY THE PRESS, THE SUSPECT IS AN ISRAELI MERCENARY PAID BY THE MEDELLIN CARTEL -- THE WORLD'S MOST POWERFUL DRUG-TRAFFICKING MAFIA -- THAT APPEARS TO BE DIRECTLY LINKED TO THE MURDERS OF GALAN, A HIGH-RANKING POLICE OFFICER, AND A JUDGE LAST WEEK.

REPORTS DISCLOSING THE PRESENCE OF THESE TERRORISTS IN COLOMBIA APPEARED SEVERAL MONTHS AGO WHEN TELEVISION CLIPS SHOWED A MAN GIVING INSTRUCTIONS IN HEBREW TO A RIGHT-WING PARAMILITARY SQUAD.

SIMILAR CLIPS WERE BROADCAST BY THE U.S. TELEVISION NETWORK NBC, PROMPTING A COMMUNIQUE FROM JERUSALEM WHICH REQUESTED COLOMBIAN AUTHORITIES AND INTERPOL TO PROVIDE ALL INFORMATION ON THE MATTER.

ACORDING TO THE ISRAELI OFFICIAL, THE TERRORISTS' ACTIONS IN COLOMBIA RUN "COUNTER TO ISRAEL'S POLICIES."

INVESTIGATIONS BY THE ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY (DAS) -- THE STATE'S INTELLIGENCE CORPS -- DISCLOSED THE LINKS BETWEEN THE DRUG-TRAFFICKING MAFIAS AND ULTRARIGHT-WING PARAMILITARY GROUPS.

ACCORDING TO DAS DIRECTOR GENERAL MIGUEL MAZA MARQUEZ, THE DRUG-TRAFFICKING ORGANIZATIONS, ESPECIALLY THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, SET UP SEVERAL "SCHOOLS FOR GUNMEN" IN A VAST REGION IN THE INTERIOR OF THE COUNTRY WITH ISRAELI, BRITISH, U.S. AND WEST GERMAN TERRORIST INSTRUCTORS. MOREOVER, NBC WARNED OF THE PRESENCE OF SOUTH AFRICANS.

THE PARAMILITARY SQUADS ARE ACCUSED OF HUNDREDS OF INDIVIDUAL MURDERS AND MASSACRES AGAINST POLITICAL AND LABOR LEADERS, AS WELL AS PEASANTS AND PATRIOTIC UNION LEFTIST MILITANTS IN DIFFERENT PARTS OF THE COUNTRY.

THE AUTHORITIES ARE ACCUSING THESE SQUADS' KILLERS OF BEING BEHIND THE CRIME WAVE THE COUNTRY HAS BEEN EXPERIENCING SINCE LAST WEEK, WITH THE MURDERS OF PEOPLE KNOWN FOR THEIR ACTIVITIES AGAINST COCAINE TRAFFICKING.

TST3-MUC4-0033

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (FBIS) -- [EDITORIAL REPORT] [CONTINUED] THE STATION ANNOUNCER THEN LISTS WAR BULLETINS FROM GUAZAPA, FROM THE WESTERN PART OF THE COUNTRY, FROM THE METROPOLITAN AREA, AND FROM THE FRANCISCO SANCHEZ EASTERN FRONT. THE ANNOUNCER REMINDS LISTENERS THAT THESE REPORTS WERE NOT INCLUDED IN THE WEEK'S EVENTS AND SAYS: "THE FIRST REPORT IS FROM THE MODESTO RAMIREZ CENTRAL FRONT, GUAZAPA AREA. AT 1000 ON 10 AUGUST, SAN CARLOS BATTALION TROOPS BELONGING TO THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE WALKED INTO A MINED FIELD, WHICH LEFT TWO SOLDIERS INJURED AT SAN JOSE GUAYABAL JURISDICTION, CUSCATLAN DEPARTMENT. AT 1800 ON 12 AUGUST, THE SAN CARLOS BATTALION CAME ACROSS MINES PLACED IN THEIR PATH AT LOS LIRIOS. ONE SOLDIER WAS KILLED AND TWO WERE SERIOUSLY INJURED. AT 1300 ON 13 AUGUST, ATLACATL BATTALION UNITS WALKED INTO A MINED FIELD, AND THERE WERE TWO CASUALTIES. AT 1330 ANOTHER ATLACATL BATTALION UNIT WALKED INTO A MINED FIELD AT CERRO CAMPANARIO, GUAZAPA HILL, CAUSING ONE MORE CASUALTY. AT 1900 ON 10 AUGUST, URBAN COMMANDOS TOOK A PATROL CAR BY SURPRISE. THEY DROPPED A GRENADE INSIDE THE CAR, INJURING FOUR AND PARTIALLY DESTROYING THE VEHICLE."

THE ANNOUNCER CONTINUES: "THIS SUCCESSFUL OPERATION TOOK PLACE OUTSIDE THE AVENIDA CINEMA IN SAN SALVADOR, SCARCELY ONE BLOCK FROM A NATIONAL GUARD GARRISON."

THE STATION ANNOUNCER LISTS ITS REPORTS FROM SANTA ANA: "AT 0415 ON 12 AUGUST WE INFLICTED FOUR CASUALTIES AMONG TROOPS BELONGING TO THE 2ND INFANTRY BRIGADE AT [WORDS INDISTINCT]. AT 1715 ANOTHER CASUALTY WAS INFLICTED AT EL PEAR FARM. AT 0130 ON 12 AUGUST WE INFLICTED ONE MORE CASUALTY AT PUERTAS NEGRAS."

THE ANNOUNCER ENDS HIS REPORT BY STATING: "THE FRANCISCO SANCHEZ EASTERN FRONT REPORTS THAT AT 1500 ON 12 AUGUST GUERRILLA UNITS ATTACKED AN ENEMY POSITION IN THE NORTHERN PART OF MORAZAN DEPARTMENT. THE CLASH LASTED 20 MINUTES AND WE INFLICTED TWO CASUALTIES ON THE ENEMY."

THE RADIO REPORTS FROM AN ANASTACIO AQUINO FRONT WAR BULLETIN, WHICH STATES THAT FMLN GUERRILLA UNITS AMBUSHED THE 1ST COMPANY OF MILITARY DETACHMENT NO 2 JR BATTALION AT LA PENA CANTON, VILLA VICTORIA JURISDICTION, CABANAS DEPARTMENT, AT 0745 ON 14 AUGUST, "KILLING SIX ENEMIES AND WOUNDING FOUR OTHERS."

THE RADIO ANNOUNCER THEN GIVES A REPORT COMING FROM THE MODESTO RAMIREZ FRONT IN CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT, WHICH STATES THAT GUERRILLA UNITS CLASHED WITH BRACAMONTE BATTALION TROOPS AT NUEVA TRINIDAD JURISDICTION AT 0900 ON 14 AUGUST, INFLICTING TWO CASUALTIES ON THE "DEMORALIZED BRACAMONTE BATTALION TROOPS."

ANOTHER REPORT SAYS THAT A GROUP OF FMLN GUERRILLAS OCCUPIED THE TOWN OF DULCE NOMBRE DE MARIA, CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT, DURING 5 HOURS AT 1500 ON 11 AUGUST.

THE RADIO STATION GOES ON TO AIR A REPORT STATING THAT GUERRILLA UNITS ATTACKED A MILITARY POST WITH MORTAR FIRE, GRENADES, AND M-16 RIFLE FIRE, "KILLING ONE ENEMY AND WOUNDING ANOTHER AT 1215 ON 13 AUGUST." THE ATTACK WAS CARRIED OUT "ONLY 100 METERS AWAY FROM A CHECKPOINT LOCATED AT THE ENTRANCE TO THE TOWN OF LA PALMA."

THE NEXT REPORT COMING FROM CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT SAYS THAT FMLN MILITIAS SABOTAGED POWER LINES ALONG THE ROAD LINKING NUEVA CONCEPCION TO THE NORTHERN TRUNK HIGHWAY AT 1800 ON 12 AUGUST.

THE ANNOUNCER THEN SAYS THAT GUERRILLA UNITS ATTACKED 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE TROOPS AT LOS AVELINES CANTON, GUATAJIAGUA JURISDICTION, MORAZAN DEPARTMENT, AT 1600 ON 11 AUGUST, INFLICTING FOUR CASUALTIES. THE REPORT STATES: "THE ATTACK WAS CARRIED OUT WITH HAND GRENADES AND RIFLE FIRE." "WE REPORT THAT ONE OF OUR COMRADES WAS WOUNDED IN THIS ATTACK, BUT NOT VERY SERIOUSLY."

THE NEXT REPORT STATES THAT GUERRILLA UNITS INFLICTED ONE CASUALTY AMONG THE MARINES BATTALION IN JUCUARAN JURISDICTION, USULUTAN DEPARTMENT, AT 1200 ON 12 AUGUST.

THE LAST REPORT SAYS THAT FMLN UNITS WOUNDED ONE OROMONTIQUE BATTALION CORPORAL AT EL TABLON, JUCUARAN JURISDICTION, AT 1630 ON 13 AUGUST.

TST3-MUC4-0035

TEL AVIV (ISRAEL), 3 SEP 89 (HADASHOT) -- [REPORT] [SHMU'EL ROSENBLUM] [TEXT] IN THE WAKE OF THE COLOMBIAN AFFAIR, SIMILAR ISRAELI ACTIVITY HAS BEEN REVEALED IN NEIGHBORING PERU AND BOLIVIA. THESE TWO COUNTRIES ARE KNOWN FOR THEIR COCAINE CROPS AND THE DRUG CARTEL'S ORGANIZED ACTIVITIES. IN ADDITION, EXTREMIST RIGHT-WING AND LEFT-WING ORGANIZATIONS THERE ARE ACTIVELY TRYING TO ACHIEVE POLITICAL GOALS THROUGH TERRORIST ACTIVITY.

HADASHOT HAS LEARNED FROM A SOURCE WHO WAS IN PERU FOR ABOUT 6 MONTHS THAT ELEMENTS LINKED TO THE DRUG GROWERS SPENT APPROXIMATELY $9 MILLION ON MILITARY EQUIPMENT FROM ISRAELI ARMS DEALERS IN 1987. THE EQUIPMENT INCLUDED GALIL RIFLES, FLAK JACKETS, AMMUNITION BELTS AND AMMUNITION, VARIOUS TYPES OF GRENADES, AND COMMUNICATIONS AND NIGHT VISION EQUIPMENT. IN 1988 AND 1989, IN ADDITIONAL DEALS WORTH SOME $6 MILLION, MORTARS, SHELLS, SNIPER RIFLES, AND AMMUNITION FOR LIGHT WEAPONS WERE PURCHASED.

THE ARMS WERE SENT TO PERU VIA MEXICO AND GUATEMALA. AT LEAST 3 IDF [ISRAEL DEFENSE FORCES] RESERVE OFFICERS WERE IN PERU FOR OVER 2 MONTHS IN EARLY 1988 TO ORGANIZE FIGHTING UNITS. THE PERUVIAN FIGHTERS WERE PRESENTED TO THE OFFICERS AS BELONGING TO RIGHT-WING POLITICAL BODIES IN THE COUNTRY, AND THE TEAM OF INSTRUCTORS INCLUDED MERCENARIES FROM THE NETHERLANDS AND ENGLAND.

THE TEAM OF INSTRUCTORS WAS MADE UP OF SOME 10 PEOPLE, SOME OF WHOM WERE RECRUITED THROUGH AN ISRAELI-NETHERLANDER ARMS DEALER WHO LIVES IN AMSTERDAM. THE NETHERLANDS MEDIA IS CONDUCTING A WIDE-RANGING INVESTIGATION INTO THE SUBJECT DESPITE THE SURPRISING LACK OF INTEREST BY THE NETHERLANDS AUTHORITIES IN THE AFFAIR.

AT THE SAME TIME, ISRAELIS IN NEIGHBORING BOLIVIA ACTED AS INSTRUCTORS IN A COURSE ON SAFEGUARDING BUSINESSMEN, GUERRILLA WARFARE, AND REGIONAL DEFENSE. THESE ISRAELIS REACHED BOLIVIA IN THE WAKE OF AN ARMS CONSIGNMENT WORTH SOME $12 MILLION, WHICH ARRIVED IN PERU [COUNTRY AS PUBLISHED] VIA A THIRD PARTY, WHICH PURCHASED IT IN AN AFRICAN COUNTRY, WHICH IN TURN HAD RECEIVED IT FROM ISRAEL.

FOLLOWING THE REPORTS ON DEALS BY ISRAELIS ABROAD, THE INCOME TAX INVESTIGATIONS DIVISION HAS BEGUN AN INQUIRY INTO TAX PAYMENTS ON ISRAELI ARMS DEALS AND TRAINING ABROAD.

IN THE PAST 5 YEARS, THE SCOPE OF COMMISSIONS PAID TO ARMS DEALERS IS ESTIMATED AT $1 BILLION. AT LEAST HALF OF IT WENT TO BIG DEALERS, SUCH AS SHA'UL EISENBERG, MARCUS KATZ, PESAH BEN-OR, ISRACES, AND OTHERS. THEY ARE NOT UNDER SUSPICION OF TRYING TO CHEAT OR HIDE INFORMATION FROM THE TAX AUTHORITIES.

TST3-MUC4-0036

BOGOTA, 4 SEP 89 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] THIS STATION HAS LEARNED THAT THREE PERSONS HAVE BEEN KILLED AT THE JOSE MARIA CORDOBA INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT, IN THE TOWN OF RIO NEGRO, ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT. ONE OF THE PERSONS KILLED WAS WEARING A MILITARY UNIFORM, BUT WE STILL DO NOT KNOW IF HE WAS IN DISGUISE OR IF HE BELONGED TO THE SECURITY CORPS. ACCORDING TO PRELIMINARY REPORTS FROM THE ANTIOQUIA POLICE, THIS WAS AN ATTACK ON THE INSTALLATIONS OF THE JOSE MARIA CORDOBA AIRPORT. I REPEAT: THIS IS A PRELIMINARY REPORT BY THE ANTIOQUIA POLICE. RIGHT NOW, TOP OFFICIALS AND ANTIOQUIA POLICE CHIEFS ARE ON THEIR WAY TO THE AIRPORT. THE AIRPORT HAS BEEN SEALED OFF, AND PEOPLE ARE TRAPPED INSIDE OFFICES THERE. NO ONE IS ALLOWED NEAR THE SCENE OF THE VIOLENT SHOOTING THAT TOOK PLACE THERE JUST A FEW MINUTES AGO.

A SEARCH IS UNDER WAY THROUGHOUT RIO NEGRO'S SAN NICOLAS VALLEY, WHERE THE AIRPORT IS LOCATED, FOR THE PERPETRATORS OF THIS ATTACK, WHO ARE NOW BELIEVED TO BE DRIVING TWO YELLOW RENAULTS AND ARE BEING PURSUED BY THE POLICE. I REPEAT: SO FAR, WE KNOW THAT THREE PERSONS HAVE BEEN KILLED INSIDE THE AIRPORT. ONE OF THOSE KILLED WAS WEARING A MILITARY UNIFORM. THE ANTIOQUIA POLICE HAVE REPORTED THAT THIS WAS AN ATTACK ON THE AIRPORT INSTALLATIONS.

WE STILL HAVE NOT BEEN ABLE TO LEARN IF THE ATTACK WAS TARGETED AGAINST ANYONE IN PARTICULAR.

TST3-MUC4-0037

MEDELLIN, 4 SEP 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] TWO PERSONS WERE INJURED IN DYNAMITE ATTACKS PERPETRATED THIS EVENING AGAINST TWO BANK BRANCHES IN THIS NORTHWESTERN COLOMBIAN CITY.

THE FIRST POLICE REPORTS INDICATE THAT A BOMB EXPLODED IN FRONT OF THE STATE-OWNED AGRARIAN BOARD IN THE SUBURBS OF MANRIQUE, AND ANOTHER AT THE AGRARIAN BOARD BRANCH IN THE SECTOR OF ARANJUEZ.

ONE PERSON WAS SERIOUSLY WOUNDED IN EACH OF THE TERRORIST ATTACKS, BUT NO DEATHS WERE REPORTED.

THE DEVICE WHICH EXPLODED IN MANRIQUE DESTROYED THE BANK BUILDING AND A BUS THAT WAS PARKED IN FRONT OF THE BUILDING, AND CAUSED CONSIDERABLE DAMAGE IN SEVERAL STORES NEARBY.

THE EXPLOSION IN THE OTHER BRANCH WAS OF A LESSER MAGNITUDE, AND IT BROKE WINDOWS AND CAUSED DAMAGE INSIDE THE OFFICES.

THE SCANT POLICE INFORMATION SAID THAT THE DEVICES WERE APPARENTLY LEFT IN FRONT OF THE TWO BANK BRANCHES MINUTES BEFORE THE CURFEW BEGAN FOR THE 6TH CONSECUTIVE DAY--PRECISELY TO COUNTER THE WAVE OF TERRORISM CAUSED BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS.

THESE REPRESENT THE SECOND AND THIRD DYNAMITE ATTACKS IN MEDELLIN THIS EVENING. THE PREVIOUS ONE TOOK PLACE 2 HOURS EARLIER AND BLEW UP A POLICE POST, BUT FAILED TO INJURE ITS FIVE OCCUPANTS.

TST3-MUC4-0038

BOGOTA, 13 SEP 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 2) -- [TEXT] DAS [ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY] DIRECTOR MIGUEL MAZA MARQUEZ CONFIRMED TODAY THAT THE GOVERNMENT AND THE JUDICIAL AUTHORITIES HAD KNOWN FOR OVER 1 YEAR THAT THERE WERE MERCENARIES IN OUR COUNTRY, BUT POLICE AUTHORITIES APPARENTLY PREVENTED AN INVESTIGATION THAT HAD BEEN ORDERED, AS A MATTER OF FACT, BY A FEMALE JUDGE. OUR REPORTER HERNANDO CORRALES HAS THE DETAILS:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CORRALES] IF THE AUTHORITIES IN CHARGE OF AN OPERATION NEAR PUERTO BOYACA ON 18 JULY LAST YEAR HAD NOT SABOTAGED IT, THE FOREIGN INSTRUCTORS AT THE SERVICE OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL WOULD NOW BE JAIL. ON THAT DATE, MARTA LUCIA GONZALEZ, SECOND JUDGE OF PUBLIC ORDER, WROTE A FILE NOTE SAYING THAT THE JUDICIAL INSPECTION WAS UNJUSTLY TORPEDOED WITH THE ARGUMENT THAT NOTHING HAD BEEN FOUND AND THAT THIS ARGUMENT WAS SENSELESS AND ILLOGICAL SINCE ABSOLUTELY NO ONE OTHER THAN THE UNDERSIGNED JUDGE COULD DECIDE IF HE OR SHE HAD ANYTHING TO INSPECT, OR IF HE OR SHE SHOULD OR SHOULD NOT CONDUCT THE JUDICIAL PROCEEDING.

THE DOCUMENT, WHICH IS CONTAINED IN THE DOSSIER ON THE MASSACRE IN LA HONDURA AND LA NEGRA, URABA REGION, SAYS THAT SHE WAS LEFT 2 DAYS INSIDE A PLANE AT THE AIRPORT OF THE TEXAS PETROLEUM COMPANY IN PUERTO BOYACA AND THAT THE POLICE AUTHORITIES ACCOMPANYING HER FAILED TO EXPLAIN TO HER WHY THEY HAD NOT TAKEN ANY ACTION.

[UNIDENTIFIED SPEAKER] IN FACT, SHE AND SEVERAL DAS INSPECTORS ENCOUNTERED SOME OBSTACLES. THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE WAS INFORMED OF THESE OBSTACLES IN ORDER FOR IT TO MAKE AN INVESTIGATION. I THINK THAT WHEN SHE AND THE DAS PERSONNEL WERE PREPARING TO GO TO PUERTO BOYACA IT WAS ALREADY KNOWN THAT THESE PEOPLE WOULD BE PRESENT THERE FOR THESE PROCEEDINGS AND THIS WAS QUITE WORRISOME.

[CORRALES] AS IS KNOWN, JUDGE GONZALEZ HAD TO LEAVE COLOMBIA BECAUSE HER LIFE WAS THREATENED, AND HER FATHER, FORMER BOYACA GOVERNOR ALVARO GONZALEZ SANTANA, WAS SUBSEQUENTLY MURDERED.

MOREOVER, GEN MAZA MARQUEZ SAID FURTHER THAT THE FACT THAT A PAYMENT IS BEING OFFERED FOR THE CAPTURE OF PABLO ESCOBAR AND GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA DOES NOT MEAN THAT OTHER PERSONS ACCUSED OF BEING CAPOS OF THE MAFIA ARE NOT BEING SOUGHT TOO.

[MAZA] WE ARE TAKING ACTION THE LENGTH AND BREADTH OF THE COUNTRY. WE ARE NOT SHOWING ANY SPECIAL CONSIDERATIONS BECAUSE WE INTEND TO ACT INDISCRIMINATELY. WHAT WE WANT IS TO FIGHT A SCOURGE THAT HAS GREATLY HARMED ALL COLOMBIANS.

[CORRALES] THE DAS DIRECTOR SAID THAT IF ANYONE BEING HELD IN CONNECTION WITH THE INVESTIGATION OF THE KILLING OF LUIS CARLOS GALAN IS RELEASED, THAT DOES NOT MEAN THAT THE INVESTIGATIONS ARE NOT PROCEEDING WELL. [END RECORDING]

TST3-MUC4-0039

GUATEMALA CITY, 18 SEP 89 (TELEONCE) -- [TEXT] THE TOPIC ABOUT VIOLENCE AND THE PROCEDURES ADOPTED BY THE GOVERNMENT TO COUNTER IT WERE DISCUSSED ON 18 SEPTEMBER DURING THE INAUGURATION OF THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC INTERNATIONAL WORLD ASSEMBLY. GUATEMALAN PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO GAVE THE INAUGURATION SPEECH AND REVEALED THE PLANS TO DESTABILIZE THE COUNTRY.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CEREZO] THERE ARE SOME STUBBORN PEOPLE WHO REFUSE TO ACCEPT THAT PEOPLE WANT TO LIVE PEACEFULLY AND FREELY. THERE ARE EVEN SOME PEOPLE WHO ARE USING VIOLENCE TO IMPOSE THEIR IDEAS; THERE ARE SOME PEOPLE WHO WANT TO COUNTER THE GUATEMALAN PEOPLE'S IDEAS WITH CONFRONTATION AND POLARIZATION. THOSE PERSONS ARE PREPARING RIGHT NOW A PLOT AGAINST GUATEMALA'S DEMOCRACY. IT IS PERHAPS THE MOST CRUEL, HARSH, AND AUDACIOUS PLOT EVER PREPARED IN THE NATION'S 4 YEARS OF DEMOCRATIC HISTORY, BECAUSE -- AND I WANT YOU TO CAREFULLY LISTEN TO THIS -- THEY HAVE DECIDED TO KILL PROMINENT POLITICAL AND LABOR LEADERS SO THAT THE PEOPLE BLAME THE GOVERNMENT -- REMEMBERING THE TRAGEDIES WHICH OCCURRED IN THE PAST AND THE ILLEGITIMATE GOVERNMENTS WHICH DECIDED TO KEEP, WITH DEATH AND REPRESSION, THE PRIVILEGES THAT THEY HAD NOT EARNED.

THESE PEOPLE ARE TRYING TO CREATE A RIFT BETWEEN THE GUATEMALAN PEOPLE AND GOVERNMENT; THEY WANT US TO FALL INTO A TRAP. [END RECORDING]

PRESIDENT CEREZO ADDRESSED THE DELEGATES OF 54 COUNTRIES WHO ARE PARTICIPATING IN THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC INTERNATIONAL WORLD ASSEMBLY, ASSERTING THAT THE EFFORTS TO BE EXERTED BY HIS GOVERNMENT TO COUNTER TERRORISM SHOULD BE UNDERSTOOD BY THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY. HE SAID NO ONE SHOULD CONDEMN HIS GOVERNMENT WITHOUT FULLY UNDERSTANDING THE SITUATION.

PRESIDENT CEREZO ALSO PLEDGED TO USE EVERY AVAILABLE MEANS TO LOCATE THOSE WHO PERPETRATE ACTS OF TERRORISM.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CEREZO] -- [BROADCAST IN PROGRESS] ...CRIMINALS AND WE ARE ALREADY LOOKING FOR THEM! [APPLAUSE] AND WE WILL PUNISH THEM ACCORDING TO THE LAW, TO GIVE BACK TO THE GUATEMALAN PEOPLE THE LIBERTY THAT THEY HAVE ENJOYED FOR 3 AND 1/2 YEARS -- BECAUSE IT IS THE RESULT OF MANY YEARS OF SACRIFICE! [APPLAUSE] [END RECORDING]

TST3-MUC4-0040

BOGOTA, 21 SEP 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] AUTHORITIES HAVE OFFICIALLY REPORTED THAT SEVERAL BANK OFFICES WERE ADVERSELY AFFECTED TONIGHT IN THE CHAPINERO NEIGHBORHOOD OF NORTHERN BOGOTA WHEN TWO BOMBS EXPLODED, CAUSING MINOR INJURIES TO A CHILD AND A SECURITY GUARD.

THE FIRST BOMB EXPLODED BY THE DOOR OF A BANCO DE OCCIDENTE BRANCH AT 2115 LOCAL TIME (0215 GMT), AND THE SHOCK WAVE DAMAGED OTHER NEARBY BANKS.

FOLLOWING THE EXPLOSION, A 9-YEAR-OLD BOY WHO LIVES NEAR THE BANCO DE OCCIDENTE WAS WOUNDED BY PIECES OF GLASS, SAID HIS RELATIVES, WHO TOOK HIM TO THE "MARLY" CLINIC NEAR THE AREA.

AT THE SAME TIME, ANOTHER BOMB EXPLODED AT A BANCO POPULAR BRANCH, TWO BLOCKS AWAY FROM WHERE THE FIRST EXPLOSION TOOK PLACE, POLICE SAID.

OTHER BANKS AND SHOPS WERE DAMAGED BY THE SECOND EXPLOSION, AND THE SECURITY GUARD AT THE BANCO POPULAR WAS ALSO INJURED BY PIECES OF FLYING GLASS, THE AUTHORITIES SAID.

ACCORDING TO PRELIMINARY REPORTS, TWO MEN PLACED THE EXPLOSIVE DEVICES AND LEFT THE SCENE ON FOOT.

BOTH OF THESE ATTACKS TONIGHT, ATTRIBUTED TO THE DRUG TRAFFICKING CARTELS, TOOK PLACE AFTER 10 BOMBS EXPLODED EARLY THIS MORNING IN THE TEUSAQUILLO AREA IN DOWNTOWN BOGOTA. THE BOMBS WERE PLACED IN NINE POLITICAL OFFICES OF THE LIBERAL AND SOCIAL CONSERVATIVE PARTIES AND IN ANOTHER BANK OFFICE.

TST3-MUC4-0041

BOGOTA, 28 SEP 89 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [INTERVIEW WITH GENERAL OCTAVIO VARGAS SILVA, COLOMBIAN NATIONAL POLICE OPERATIONAL COMMANDER, BY EDUARDO CARRILLO] [TEXT] [CARRILLO] I HAVE BEEN IN TOUCH WITH GENERAL OCTAVIO VARGAS SILVA, NATIONAL POLICE OPERATIONAL COMMANDER AND INSPECTOR. GEN VARGAS HAS SAID THAT THE TWO PEOPLE WHO WERE KILLED IN THE ATTACK THAT TOOK PLACE AT SUBA MUNICIPALITY LAST NIGHT HAVE NOT YET BEEN IDENTIFIED.

[VARGAS] TWO PEOPLE WERE KILLED AND FIVE OTHERS WERE WOUNDED AS A RESULT OF THE ATTACK. THE TWO PEOPLE WHO WERE KILLED ARE YET TO BE IDENTIFIED. THOSE WOUNDED INCLUDE THREE EMPLOYEES OF THE GAS STATION WHERE THE CAR BOMB WENT OFF AND TWO PEOPLE WHO WERE WALKING BY THE GAS STATION AT THE MOMENT OF THE EXPLOSION. PRELIMINARY REPORTS HAVE ESTIMATED THAT THE EXPLOSION CAUSED 70 MILLION PESOS IN LOSSES.

[CARRILLO] GENERAL, APPROXIMATELY HOW MANY KILOGRAMS OF EXPLOSIVES WERE IN THE CAR BOMB?

[VARGAS] APPARENTLY IT CONTAINED 60 KG OF DYNAMITE. THE DYNAMITE WAS PLACED INSIDE AN OLD STATION WAGON. SOMETHING MUST HAVE HAPPENED TO THE PEOPLE WHO WERE INSIDE THE VEHICLE AT THE TIME OF THE EXPLOSION -- THE TWO PEOPLE WHO WERE KILLED. APPARENTLY THE CAR BOMB WENT OFF BY ACCIDENT. IT WAS NOT SUPPOSED TO HAVE GONE OFF AT THAT GAS STATION.

[CARRILLO] HAVE THE PEOPLE WHO WERE KILLED BEEN IDENTIFIED?

[VARGAS] NO, NOT YET. WE ARE TRYING TO IDENTIFY THEM NOW.

[CARRILLO] ARE THERE SPECIAL SECURITY MEASURES TO COUNTER THIS WAVE OF TERRORISM?

[VARGAS] YES, OF COURSE. WE ARE CARRYING OUT A SERIES OF JOINT ACTIONS WITH THE BOGOTA POLICE DEPARTMENT AND ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY PERSONNEL TO NEUTRALIZE TERRORIST ACTIONS. WE ARE CARRYING OUT THOSE ACTIONS IN AREAS WE CONSIDER CRITICAL OR VULNERABLE AND IN OTHER AREAS WHERE WE ARE COUNTERACTING AND NEUTRALIZING TERRORIST ACTIONS, AS I TOLD YOU.

[CARRILLO] ARE THERE SECRET AGENTS THROUGHOUT THE ENTIRE CITY?

[VARGAS] YES, WE HAVE UNIFORMED AND CIVILIAN PERSONNEL GUARDING THE CITY RIGHT NOW. WE ALSO HAVE THE SUPPORT OF THE BOGOTA POLICE DEPARTMENT, OF DIJIN [DIRECTORATE OF JUDICIAL POLICE AND INVESTIGATIONS], AND OF CIJIN [EXPANSION UNKNOWN]. THEY ARE COOPERATING WITH US. THEY ARE GUARDING AREAS WE CONSIDER CRITICAL OR PLACES THAT COULD BE TARGETS OF TERRORIST ATTACKS.

[CARRILLO] WHAT OTHER MEASURES HAVE YOU ADOPTED ALONG WITH THE 13TH INFANTRY BRIGADE AND THE BOGOTA MAYOR?

[VARGAS] WE HAVE IMPLEMENTED A NUMBER OF MEASURES, SUCH AS INCREASING PERSONNEL ON THE STREETS AND HUMAN AND MATERIAL RESOURCES. IN ADDITION, WE HAVE ESTABLISHED CHEKCKPOINTS IN AREAS WE CONSIDER CRITICAL AND ARE CARRYING OUT A NUMBER OF OPERATIONAL ACTIVITIES THAT WILL HELP US LOCATE THESE CRIMINALS.

TST3-MUC4-0042

SAN SALVADOR, 28 SEP 89 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHAIRMAN OF THE JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF, SAID TODAY THAT THE OFFENSIVE LAUNCHED ON 26 SEPTEMBER BY THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, FMLN, WAS A MISTAKEN STEP TAKEN BY THE REBELS WITHIN THE CONTEXT OF THE DIALOGUE PROCESS WITH THE GOVERNMENT, WHICH WAS RESUMED IN MEXICO.

COL PONCE SAID THAT WITH THIS ATTITUDE THE REBELS ARE NOT SHOWING A REAL DESIRE FOR PEACE, AND HE DESCRIBED IT AS A PROPAGANDISTIC ACTION.

TODAY, DURING HIS TOUR OF VARIOUS AREAS OF CONFLICT, COL PONCE SAID THAT RECENT FMLN ATTACKS ON VARIOUS MILITARY POSITIONS AS PART OF ITS LATEST CAMPAIGN FOLLOWING THE UNILATERAL TRUCE WAS A SERIOUS MISTAKE ON THE PART OF THE REBEL COMMANDERS, AS THEY HAVE BEEN CARRIED OUT IN THE MIDST OF A DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE REBELS AND THE GOVERNMENT, WHICH HAS BEEN DESCRIBED AS CONTINUOUS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PONCE] THAT SHOWS THERE ARE, ON THE ONE HAND, THE PROPOSALS AND WHAT THE TERRORIST LEADERS CALL THEIR DESIRE FOR PEACE, AND, ON THE OTHER HAND, THE REAL ACTIONS. I THINK THAT THE CAMPAIGN THE FMLN HAS MOUNTED NATIONWIDE WAS A BAD STEP, BECAUSE IT DOES NOT SHOW A REAL AND SINCERE DESIRE TO SEEK PEACE IN OUR COUNTRY. [END RECORDING]

COLONEL PONCE ADDED THAT THE REQUEST FOR REDUCING THE NUMBER OF TROOPS AS STATED IN THE GUERRILLA PROPOSAL IS A POLITICAL MOVE. HE PLAYED DOWN THE LATEST REBEL OFFER PRESENTED TO THE GOVERNMENT IN MEXICO.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PONCE] THE PROPOSAL WAS AIMED AT IMPROVING THE FMLN'S IMAGE ABROAD, WHICH HAD DETERIORATED IN ONE WAY OR ANOTHER. THE PROPOSAL CAN BE DISCUSSED; HOWEVER, WE IN THE ARMED FORCES ARE NOT THE ONES WHO WILL DISCUSS IT OR WHO WILL DECIDE WHETHER IT CAN OR CANNOT BE ACCEPTED. IT IS A POLITICAL DECISION, AND THE ARMED FORCES WILL ACCEPT THE DECISION MADE BY THE GOVERNMENT. THE MILITARY COMMANDERS ARE NOT THE ONES WHO MUST DECIDE ON THE NUMBER OF TROOPS THE INSTITUTION SHOULD HAVE. THIS IS A DECISION TO BE MADE BY THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY, BASED ON THE REQUIREMENTS AND THREATS THE COUNTRY MAY BE FACING. [END RECORDING]

COLONEL PONCE VISITED THE POSITIONS OF THE ARMY'S BELLOSO AND ATLACATL ELITE BATTALIONS IN THE TOWNS OF PERQUIN IN MORAZAN DEPARTMENT AND LA LAGUNA IN CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT, NEAR THE HONDURAN BORDER, WHERE FIGHTING IS TAKING PLACE. DURING THIS MILITARY TOUR, COL PONCE SAID THAT IT HAS BEEN DEMONSTRATED THAT THERE IS NO LIBERATED OR PERMANENTLY OCCUPIED TERRITORY IN EL SALVADOR. HOWEVER, THE REBELS CLAIM THEY CONTROL THAT AREA OF INTENSE CONFLICT WHERE THE WAR HAS LEFT ITS INDELIBLE MARK.

TST3-MUC4-0043

NO CITY (EL SALVADOR), 29 SEP 89 -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI LIBERATION FRONT GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] SUCH AN UNCONDITIONAL CEASE-FIRE DOES NOT CORRESPOND TO THE SPIRIT OF THE ESQUIPULAS AND TELA AGREEMENTS AND THE ACCORDS THE GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN SIGNED IN MEXICO IN WHICH THE SIDES CLEARLY AGREED TO FIND SOLUTIONS IN THE AREA AND IN EL SALVADOR. ASKING FOR AN END TO THE WAR AND NEGOTIATIONS IS LIKE DEMANDING THAT THE SITUATION BE CHANGED WITHOUT HAVING WON THE WAR. IN ADDITION TO BEING UNREALISTIC, THIS IS A FORMULA FOR NOT NEGOTIATING AND CONTINUING THE WAR.

IN THE ESQUIPULAS II DOCUMENTS, THE GOVERNMENTS URGE THE SIDES TO AGREE TO A CEASE-FIRE. THE TELA ACCORDS ALSO APPEAL TO THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT TO REACH AN AGREEMENT WITH THE FMLN IN THE SPIRIT OF THE ESQUIPULAS II ACCORDS. THIS PARTICULAR AGREEMENT LINKS THE CESSATION OF HOSTILITIES TO DEMOCRATIZATION, SOCIAL JUSTICE, AND SELF-DETERMINATION AS A HARMONIOUS, INDIVISIBLE WHOLE. THIS CONCEPT IS SUPPORTED BY THE UN SECURITY COUNCIL IN ITS RESOLUTION 637 OF 27 JULY 1989. IN ADDITION, THE FIRST PARAGRAPH OF THE MEXICAN ACCORD READS AS FOLLOWS: THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN WILL TALK IN AN EFFORT TO REACH AN UNDERSTANDING THROUGH NEGOTIATIONS TO CONCLUDE THE ARMED CONFLICT THROUGH POLITICAL MEANS AS SOON AS PRACTICABLE. THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN WILL FOSTER THE COUNTRY'S DEMOCRATIZATION AND REUNITE SALVADORAN SOCIETY. THE DIALOGUE IS MEANT TO SERVE AS AN INSTRUMENT FOR REACHING AN AGREEMENT ON CESSATION OF HOSTILITIES. THE AGREEMENT THAT THE GOVERNMENT SIGNED IN MEXICO SAYS NOTHING OF TALKING ABOUT OR NEGOTIATING THE FMLN'S DEMOBILIZATION BUT MENTIONS NEGOTIATIONS TO ENCOURAGE DEMOCRATIZATION TO AGREE ON THE CESSATION OF HOSTILITIES.

BY INCREASING THE NUMBER OF HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS, CRISTIANI IS CLOSING THE DOOR TO DEMOCRATIZATION. THIS, PLUS HIS REFUSAL TO REACH AN AGREEMENT WITH THE FMLN, MAKES HIM GUILTY OF NONCOMPLIANCE WITH THE COMMITMENTS THAT THE GOVERNMENT MADE AT ESQUIPULAS.

3. IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE COMMITMENT WE MADE IN MEXICO AND WITH THE REGIONAL ACCORDS, WE REITERATE OUR FULL WILLINGNESS TO AGREE WITH THE GOVERNMENT ON A CEASE-FIRE AS SOON AS PRACTICABLE AND TO ATTEND THE UPCOMING NEGOTIATION MEETING IN COSTA RICA. FOR THIS MEETING, WE HAVE INCLUDED IN OUR PEACE PROPOSAL AN AGREEMENT ON A CEASE-FIRE BASED ON THE FOLLOWING POINTS: REFORMS TO THE JUDICIAL SYSTEM; CESSATION OF REPRESSION; TRIAL OF BOTH THOSE GUILTY OF THE MURDER OF MONSIGNOR ARNULFO ROMERO AND THOSE FOUND TO BE MEMBERS OF THE DEATH SQUADS; ENFORCEMENT OF THE 1980 ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL REFORMS; AND SUSPENSION OF THE ECONOMIC MEASURES THAT EXACERBATE THE CRISIS AND THE WAR; PURGE OF THE ARMY; CONSTITUTIONAL AMENDMENTS; HOLDING THE 1991 ELECTIONS AHEAD OF SCHEDULE; MINIMUM OPERATIONAL GUARANTEES TO ESTABLISH GEOGRAPHICAL AREAS FOR THE FORCES TO MAINTAIN AN EFFECTIVE CEASE-FIRE.

AFTER STRONG OPPOSITION TO THE PRESENCE OF THE UN AND OAS SECRETARY GENERALS' REPRESENTATIVES, WHO WILL SERVE AS WITNESSES AT THE DIALOGUE TABLE, CRISTIANI AGREED TO INVITE THEM TO THE COSTA RICA MEETING. WE HOPE HE KEEPS HIS WORD BECAUSE THIS WILL LEND SERIOUSNESS TO THE PROCESS AND GUARANTEE THE NEGOTIATIONS INITIATED IN MEXICO.

SIGNED THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND

TST3-MUC4-0045

TRUJILLO, 9 OCT 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] A PERUVIAN DIPLOMATIC SOURCE SAID TODAY THAT JUDGING BY PERU'S STANCE ON THE POLITICAL AND SOCIAL SITUATION IN THE ISTHMUS, THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT "IS UNCOMFORTABLE" WITH THE PRESENCE OF THE PANAMANIAN AMBASSADOR IN LIMA.

THE SOURCE, WHO REQUESTED ANONYMITY, ALSO SAID THAT THE PRESENCE OF PANAMANIAN AMBASSADOR BERTRAN SHERR IT "CAN ONLY BE UNDERSTOOD AS BEING OF COMMERCIAL AND PERSONAL INTEREST."

THE SOURCE TOLD EFE THAT THE EVENTUAL REMOVAL OF PANAMA FROM THE GROUP OF EIGHT AND ITS REPLACEMENT BY A NEW MEMBER WILL BE DECIDED THIS WEDNESDAY IN ICA (PERU) DURING THE SUMMIT OF THE PRESIDENTS OF ARGENTINA, BRAZIL, COLOMBIA, MEXICO, PERU, URUGUAY, AND VENEZUELA.

PANAMA'S ROLE IN THE GROUP OF EIGHT HAS BEEN SUSPENDED BECAUSE OF THAT COUNTRY'S CURRENT POLITICAL SITUATION.

THE SAME SOURCE DISMISSED THE IDEA THAT PERU MAY BE PLANNING TO BREAK DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS WITH PANAMA BECAUSE THIS WOULD AFFECT PERU'S LINKS WITH THE PANAMANIAN PEOPLE AND "THIS IS NOT THE POSITION OF THE GROUP OF EIGHT MEMBER COUNTRIES."

PANAMA HAS HAD AN AMBASSADOR IN PERU FOR 40 YEARS, BUT ONLY FOR "PERSONAL REASONS".

IN THE PRIVATE DIALOGUE WITH EFE, THE SOURCE SAID THAT "THE PANAMANIAN AMBASSADOR SEEMINGLY DOES NOT UNDERSTAND THE MESSAGES SENT BY THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT THROUGH ITS RECENT ACTIONS."

IN EARLY SEPTEMBER THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT REMOVED ITS AMBASSADOR TO PANAMA, MR MARIO CASTRO ARENAS, FOR AN INDEFINITE PERIOD AND DOWNGRADED RELATIONS BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES TO THE LEVEL OF CHARGE D'AFFAIRES. PERU DID THIS AFTER ANNOUNCING THAT IT WOULD NOT RECOGNIZE THE LEGITIMACY OF THE NEW PANAMANIAN GOVERNMENT HEADED BY FRANCISCO RODRIGUEZ.

ASKED IF THE PANAMANIAN DIPLOMAT WOULD BE INVITED TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY, THE SOURCE SAID THAT "THIS HAS NOT BEEN CONSIDERED BECAUSE THAT WOULD IMPLY BREAKING RELATIONS WITH PANAMA, AND PERU DOES NOT WANT TO GO THAT FAR."

IN COMMENTS TO A TELEVISION REPORTER LAST SUNDAY IN LIMA, FOREIGN MINISTER GUILLERMO LARCO COX SAID THAT PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA WILL PROPOSE THE DEFINITIVE EXPULSION OF PANAMA FROM THE GROUP OF EIGHT.

THE FOREIGN MINISTERS OF ARGENTINA, BRAZIL, MEXICO, URUGUAY, AND PERU BEGAN A 2-DAY MEETING IN TRUJILLO TODAY AND THEIR AGENDA INCLUDES THE SITUATION IN PANAMA, THE FIGHT AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING, TERRORISM, THE FOREIGN DEBT, AND THE INTEGRATION PROCESS.

TRUJILLO, 550 KILOMETERS NORTH OF LIMA, IS NORMALLY A QUIET AREA, BUT IT NOW GIVES THE IMPRESSION OF BEING A MILITARIZED CITY. THIS MILITARY PRESENCE IS AIMED AT DETERRING SABOTAGE AND ATTACKS BY TERRORIST GROUPS.

AT LEAST 5,000 POLICEMEN AND SOLDIERS ARE GUARDING ALL ENTRANCES TO THE CITY. THERE IS EVEN HEAVIER SECURITY AT THE PLAZA DE ARMAS ZONE, WHERE THE FOREIGN MINISTERS WILL MEET. NO VEHICLES OR PEOPLE ARE ALLOWED IN THAT AREA.

TST3-MUC4-0046

BOGOTA, 10 OCT 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] "THE EXTRADITABLES," THE ARMED BRANCH OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL HAVE CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE MURDER OF TWO EMPLOYEES OF BOGOTA'S DAILY EL ESPECTADOR PERPETRATED TODAY IN MEDELLIN, A SOURCE FROM THAT NEWSPAPER TOLD EFE.

MIGUEL SOLER RODRIGUEZ, EL ESPECTATOR'S CIRCULATION MANAGER AND MARTHA LUZ LOPEZ, THE CORRESPONDENT'S OFFICE ADMINISTRATOR, WERE KILLED TODAY IN SEPARATE ATTACKS CARRIED OUT BY GUNMEN IN MEDELLIN, COLOMBIA'S SECOND LARGEST CITY AND CAPITAL OF THE ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT.

SHORTLY AFTER THE MURDERS, AN ANONYMOUS CALL WAS RECEIVED AT EL ESPECTADOR'S OFFICE IN MEDELLIN, THREATENING TO KILL ALL THE EDITORS AND OFFICE PERSONNEL WHO DO NOT RESIGN IN 3 DAYS.

"THE EXTRADITABLES," THE VOICE SAID, "DO NOT WANT THAT NEWSPAPER CIRCULATING IN ANTIOQUIA ANYMORE."

MARTHA LUZ LOPEZ, 35, WHO WORKED FOR EL ESPECTADOR 11 YEARS, WAS KILLED BY TWO MEN ON MOTORCYCLES WHO INTERCEPTED HER CAR AT A CORNER AND SHOT HER SEVERAL TIMES. AT THE MOMENT OF THE ATTACK, SHE WAS ACCOMPANIED BY HER MOTHER MARTHA LOPEZ OROZCO DE LOPEZ, WHO WAS WOUNDED.

SOLER, WHO WAS 45-YEARS OLD AND HAD WORKED FOR 25 YEARS AT EL ESPECTATOR, WAS ALSO KILLED BY UNIDENTIFIED INDIVIDUALS WHILE HE WAS ON HIS WAY BACK TO HIS RESIDENCE.

SOLER, WHO WAS IN CHARGE OF ADVERTISING AND CIRCULATION OF EL ESPECTADOR IN MEDELLIN AND THE NORTHWESTERN AREA OF COLOMBIA, WAS MARRIED AND THE FATHER OF THREE CHILDREN.

THE MAIN OFFICES IN BOGOTA OF EL ESPECTADOR, THE NEWSPAPER MOST THREATENED BY COLOMBIA'S DRUG TRAFFICKING MAFIA, WERE PARTIALLY DESTROYED ON 2 SEPTEMBER WHEN A CAR BOMB EXPLOSION INJURED OVER 90 PEOPLE.

NEWSPAPER DIRECTOR GUILLERMO CANO WAS MURDERED AS HE WAS LEAVING HIS OFFICE ON 17 DECEMBER 1986. THIS CRIME WAS ATTRIBUTED TO THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, WHICH TOGETHER WITH THE CALI CARTEL, IS CONSIDERED TO BE AMONG THE MOST IMPORTANT ORGANIZATIONS IN THE WORLD INVOLVED IN THE TRAFFICKING AND DISTRIBUTION OF COCAINE.

NEWSPAPER ATTORNEY AND JOURNALIST HECTOR GIRALDO GALVEZ, WHO WAS THE CIVIL PROSECUTOR IN THE INVESTIGATION INTO GUILLERMO CANO'S HOMICIDE, WAS ALSO MURDERED IN BOGOTA ON 29 MARCH.

EL ESPECTADOR HAS CHARACTERIZED ITSELF BY REJECTING AND CONDEMNING DRUG TRAFFICKING AND OTHER CRIMINAL ACTIVITIES INVOLVING MAFIOSOS.

TST3-MUC4-0047

MOSCOW (USSR), 12 OCT 89 (MOSCOW) -- [REPORT] [UNIDENTIFIED ANNOUNCER FROM SANTIAGO] [TEXT] THE MOST PRESSING DEMANDS OF THE CHILEAN PEOPLE HAVE BEEN BROUGHT UP IN THE ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN. ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT ACHIEVEMENTS OF THIS CAMPAIGN HAS BEEN THE COMBINING OF THE CAMPAIGN WITH THE JUST ECONOMIC, POLITICAL, AND SOCIAL DEMANDS THAT THE DEMOCRATIC FORCES AND THE POPULAR MOVEMENT HAVE BEEN MAKING FOR THESE 16 YEARS OF DICTATORSHIP. THESE DEMANDS ARE RELATED TO THE STRUGGLE AGAINST REPRESSION, THE DEFENSE OF HUMAN RIGHTS, THE DENUNCIATION OF CRIMES COMMITTED BY THE REGIME, AND EFFORTS TO FIGHT IMMUNITY AND THE SUPPRESSION OF THE TRUTH REGARDING TORTURE, DISAPPEARANCES, AND ASSASSINATIONS. THESE QUESTIONS HAVE ONCE AGAIN COME INTO THE SPOTLIGHT NOW THAT MANY RIGHTIST CANDIDATES ARE DEMAGOGICALLY ATTEMPTING TO POSE AS DEFENDERS OF HUMAN RIGHTS AND SINCE EL MERCURIO HAS REPORTED THAT THE DICTATOR IS PLANNING TO CONVERT THE CNI [NATIONAL INFORMATION CENTER] INTO AN AGENCY OF THE ARMY SO THAT THE MAIN REPRESSIVE BODY FROM ALL THESE YEARS CAN BE UNDER HIS DIRECT CONTROL. JAIME INZUNZA, LEADER OF THE UNITED LEFT AND THE COMMUNIST PARTY OF CHILE, DISCUSSES THESE TOPICS OVER A DIRECT PHONE LINE FROM SANTIAGO, CHILE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ANNOUNCER] HOW ARE THE CHILEAN PEOPLE'S DEMANDS CONNECTED TO THE ONGOING ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN?

[INZUNZA] THEY ARE CONNECTED THROUGH THE DEMOCRATIZATION OF THE NEIGHBORHOOD BOARDS DURING THE ELECTORAL PROCESS; THE STRENGTHENING OF THE UNIFIED ACTIONS OF WORKERS; THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE COMMITTEES FOR VICTORY, WHICH WILL ALSO BE COMMITTEES FOR THE DEFENSE OF VICTORY AND COMMITTEES FOR CARRYING ON THE DEMOCRATIC TASK; THE DEVELOPMENT OF CONFIDENCE; THE STRUGGLE FOR HUMAN RIGHTS, PARTICULARLY CONCERNING TRUTH AND JUSTICE AND IMMUNITY FOR CRIMES; THE INCREASING PRESSURE BY THE IMMENSE MAJORITY OF THE POPULATION FOR THE RELEASE OF ALL POLITICAL PRISONERS; AND NATURALLY FOR THE DISSOLUTION OF THE CNI. ALL OF THESE QUESTIONS ARE BEING BROUGHT UP IN THE ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN, AND AGREEMENTS HAVE BEEN REACHED WITHIN SOCIAL ORGANIZATIONS. THIS WAS EVIDENCED A WEEK AGO BY THE SALVADORA STRIKE AND BY THE CURRENT STRIKE BY COAL MINERS. THIS PROVES THAT THE PEOPLE HAVE UNDERSTOOD THAT THE ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN HAS TO BE AN EXPRESSION OF THEIR ACTIVITIES AND A WAY TO STRENGTHEN THEIR SOCIAL ORGANIZATIONS FOR THE FUTURE STRUGGLE. [END RECORDING]

THE PRECEDING COMMENTS WERE MADE BY COMMUNIST PARTY OF CHILE LEADER JAIME INZUNZA, WHO HAS BEEN INTERVIEWED OVER THE TELEPHONE ON OUR PROGRAM "ESCUCHA CHILE." ANOTHER TOPIC DISCUSSED BY INZUNZA WAS THE EL MERCURIO REPORT ON THE CNI'S TRANSFER TO THE ARMY. THE DISSOLUTION OF THE CNI HAS BECOME ONE OF THE MOST PRESSING DEMANDS OF THE IMMENSE MAJORITY OF CHILEANS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ANNOUNCER] WHAT IS YOUR OPINION, JAIME INZUNZA, ON THE DICTATOR'S INTENTION TO MAINTAIN THE CNI AS IT IS AND TO KEEP IT UNDER HIS DIRECT COMMAND?

[INZUNZA] I BELIEVE THAT THIS ISSUE IS PARTICULARLY SERIOUS. THE INTENTION IS TO MAINTAIN INTACT THE MAIN TERRORIST APPARATUS OF THE DICTATORSHIP, WHICH HAS BEEN RESPONSIBLE FOR THE MOST FLAGRANT VIOLATIONS OF HUMAN RIGHTS THROUGHOUT THE YEARS OF ITS EXISTENCE. I UNDERSTAND THAT THE DINA [NATIONAL INTELLIGENCE DIRECTORATE, REPLACED BY CNI] AND THE CNI HAVE BEEN IN FACT A SINGLE APPARATUS AND THEREFORE THE MAIN ORGANS OF STATE TERRORRISM OVER THE PAST 15 YEARS. IF TRANSFERRED TO THE ARMY, THE CNI WOULD CONTINUE TO BE UNDER PINOCHET'S ORDERS. UNDER WHOSE ORDERS HAS IT BEEN ALL THESE YEARS? FOR WHOM HAS IT BEEN A DIRECT AGENT ALL THESE YEARS? HENCEFORTH IT WILL BE UNDER THE CONTROL OF THE OFFICE OF THE COMMANDER IN CHIEF OF THE ARMY. [END RECORDING]

COMMUNIST LEADER JAIME INZUNZA ADDED THAT PINOCHET'S INTENT IN TRANSFERRING THE CNI TO THE ARMY'S DIRECT COMMAND IS TO MAKE THE INSTITUTION AN ACCOMPLICE IN CONCEALING PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN RESPONSIBLE FOR CRIMES AND HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [INZUNZA] THE IDEA IS TO INVOLVE THE MILITARY INSTITUTION IN CRIMES FOR WHICH THE CHILEAN PEOPLE KNOWS IT WAS NOT RESPONSIBLE. THIS IS CLEAR: WHAT THE DEMOCRATIC OPPOSITION FORCES WANT IS TO HAVE THE CULPRITS BEHIND THOSE CRIMES AND HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS PROSECUTED, NOT THE MILITARY INSTITUTION. THE TRANSFER OF THE CNI TO THE ARMY IS AN ATTEMPT TO MAKE THE MEN IN UNIFORM ACT AS ACCOMPLICES OR ACCESSORIES TO THOSE CRIMES. LOYALTY IS NOT AT STAKE HERE; LOYALTY IS DEFENDING VALUES AND PRINCIPLES, NOT SOME SORT OF CRIMINAL COMPLICITY THAT IS NOT IN LINE WITH THE TRAINING OF THESE MEN. THIS SEEMS TO ME TO BE PARTICULARLY SERIOUS BECAUSE THIS TRANSFER IMPLIES MAINTAINING THE CNI UNDER THE ORDERS OF THE MAN RESPONSIBLE FOR THE CRIMES COMMITTED ALL THESE YEARS, THE DICTATOR HIMSELF. [END RECORDING]

THESE HAVE BEEN ANSWERS GIVEN BY JAIME INZUNZA, UNITED LEFT AND COMMUNIST PARTY OF CHILE LEADER, TO QUESTIONS PUT TO HIM OVER THE PHONE BY "ESCUCHA CHILE," A RADIO MOSCOW INTERNATIONAL PROGRAM.

TST3-MUC4-0048

PANAMA CITY (PANAMA), 3 NOV 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] GUATEMALAN ARCHBISHOP PROSPERO PENADOS DEL BARRIO TODAY REPORTED THE KIDNAPPING OF A NUN, DIANA MACK ORTIZ, 20 YEARS OLD, BORN IN THE STATE OF COLORADO IN THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.

THE ARCHBISHOP ALSO REPORTED THAT ANOTHER U.S. NUN, PATRICIA DENNY, LEFT GUATEMALA 17 DAYS AGO BECAUSE OF CONTINUOUS DEATH THREATS OVER THE TELEPHONE AND IN WRITING.

PENADOS SAID DIANA MACK ORTIZ WAS KIDNAPPED ON 2 NOVEMBER IN ANTIGUA GUATEMALA, 45 KM SOUTH OF GUATEMALA CITY, WHEN SHE WAS ATTENDING A SEMINAR ALONG WITH OTHER NUNS. THE ARCHBISHOP EXPLAINED THE NUN HAD BEEN RECEIVING DEATH THREATS. SHE HAD BEEN URGED TO LEAVE GUATEMALA, BUT SHE DECIDED TO CONTINUE WORKING IN THIS COUNTRY.

THE KIDNAPPED NUN, WHO HAD BEEN IN GUATEMALA FOR A YEAR, WAS TEACHING AT THE SAN MIGUEL ACATAN ELEMENTARY SCHOOL IN HUEHUETENANGO DEPARTMENT IN NORTHEAST GUATEMALA. SHE BELONGS TO THE ORDER OF THE URSILINA, PENADOS REPORTED.

PATRICIA DENNY, 54, LEFT GUATEMALA AFTER UNIDENTIFIED MEN WARNED HER THAT IF SHE WISHED TO CONTINUE LIVING SHE HAD TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY. DENNY HAD ARRIVED IN GUATEMALA IN 1984, BELONGED TO THE SISTERS OF MARY KNOLL, AND WAS WORKING AT A PARISH IN MIXCO MUNICIPALITY IN SOUTHERN GUATEMALA CITY.

THE ARCHBISHOP SAID ALL THIS IS THE "BEGINNING OF A CAMPAIGN TO INTIMIDATE THE CATHOLIC CHURCH." HE DID NOT MENTION WHICH GROUPS ARE PERPETRATING THESE INTIMIDATION ACTIONS. HOWEVER, PENADOS SAID HE IS GOING TO TALK TO GUATEMALAN PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO TODAY TO REPORT THE INCIDENTS WITH THE U.S. NUNS.

PENADOS STATED THAT THIS KIND OF ACTION "HARMED CATHOLICISM VERY MUCH IN PAST YEARS," WHEN REPRESSION SEVERELY HIT THIS SECTOR. HE POINTED OUT THAT THIS KIND OF INCIDENT HAD NOT HAPPENED SINCE PRESIDENT CEREZO TOOK OVER POWER IN GUATEMALA ON 14 JANUARY 1986.

THE ARCHBISHOP DEMANDED THAT MACK ORTIZ' KIDNAPPERS RESPECT HER LIFE AND PHYSICAL INTEGRITY.

TST3-MUC4-0050

SAN SALVADOR, 5 NOV 89 (FBIS) -- [EDITORIAL REPORT] [CONTINUED] ON 5 NOVEMBER, RADIO VENCEREMOS REPORTS THAT GUERRILLAS HAVE CARRIED OUT 2 AMBUSHES ALONG THE PANAMERICAN HIGHWAY, INFLICTING 26 ARMY CASUALTIES. THE REPORT INDICATED THAT AT 0600 ON 4 NOVEMBER, THE REBELS PLACED A BOMB ON A LIGHT TANK NEAR FLORES DE TEPEYAC, APASTEPEQUE. IT IS ESTIMATED THAT THE ACTION RESULTED IN 9 CASUALTIES; THE LIGHT TANK WAS COMPLETELY DESTROYED. THE SECOND AMBUSH OCCURRED AT 0815 ON 4 NOVEMBER. THE REBELS AMBUSHED A 10-VEHICLE MILITARY CONVOY AND LEFT AT LEAST 17 CASUALTIES. SOME TIME AFTER THE REBEL ACTION, THE ARMY DIRECTED MORTAR FIRE TO THE AREA AND THE AIR FORCE LEVELED MACHINEGUN FIRE UPON THIS POPULATED ZONE. TRAFFIC ON THE PANAMERICAN HIGHWAY WAS PARALYZED WHILE THE ARMED FORCES EVACUATED THE MANY CASUALTIES FROM THE AREA IN HELICOPTERS.

A LATER REPORT TOLD OF URBAN COMMANDOS ATTACKING A TREASURY POLICE UNIT AT 5TH AVENUE AND 5TH PONIENTE STREET IN SAN SALVADOR, RESULTING IN 2 CASUALTIES TO THE TREASURY POLICE.

ALSO, REBEL UNITS WERE SAID TO ATTACK MILITARY DETACHMENT NO 1 COMMANDOS ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF TOTONIQUE, CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT DURING THE AFTERNOON OF 3 NOVEMBER, INFLICTING TWO CASUALTIES.

IN ANOTHER ITEM, THE CENTRAL ANASTACIO AQUINO FRONT WAS REPORTED TO CLAIM TAKING PART IN ACTIONS AGAINST THE BELLOSO BATTALION. FMLN REBELS CLASHED WITH SOLDIERS IN CANTON COYOLITO IN TECOLUCA JURISDICTION, SAN VICENTE DEPARTMENT AT 0900 ON 3 NOVEMBER, AND INFLICTED THREE CASUALTIES. THAT SAME DAY, THE SAME UNIT WAS ATTACKED IN FINCA SAJELIO AND THE GUERRILLAS CLAIMED TO HAVE INFLICTED 2 MORE CASUALTIES. THE SAME TROOPS WERE SAID TO SUFFER 2 MORE CASUALTIES IN A MINED AREA ON 4 NOVEMBER.

AN FMLN UNIT WAS ALSO SAID TO HAVE SEIZED THE TOWN OF LOS HERNANDEZ IN CANTON MATASANO, CABANAS DEPARTMENT ON 4 NOVEMBER. FOUR PYLONS WERE BLOWN UP, INTERRUPTING A 46,000-VOLT ELECTRICAL LINE.

RADIO VENCEREMOS ON 6 NOVEMBER CARRIES ITS WEEKLY MILITARY REPORT:

"DURING THE PAST WEEK, RADIO VENCEREMOS REPORTED INFLICTING MANY CASUALTIES ON THE ARMED FORCES. THE TOTAL NUMBER OF CASUALTIES INFLICTED ON THE ARMED FORCES WAS 124, INCLUDING AN ARCE BATTALION OFFICER WHO WAS HIT IN [WORD INDISTINCT]. FMLN FORCES AMBUSHED FIVE MILITARY CONVOYS ALONG DIFFERENT HIGHWAYS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY. DURING THE WEEK, TWO PARAMILITARY MEMBERS WERE CAPTURED. THE FMLN RESPECTED THE LIVES OF THESE MEN AND RELEASED THEM IMMEDIATELY, BUT CONFISCATED THEIR 3 RIFLES AND 300 CARTRIDGES. WE HIGHLIGHT THE ATTACK BY OUR URBAN COMMANDOS ON COMMAND STAFF INSTALLATIONS. THIS ATTACK TOOK PLACE IN A SAN SALVADOR THAT IS TOTALLY MILITARIZED, NEVERTHELESS, WE MANAGED TO HIT THE TOP DEATH SQUADS MEMBERS' CENTRAL NERVE. GUERRILLA ACTIONS IN THE METAPAN AREA INCREASED DURING THE WEEK AND OUR MEN AMBUSHED SOLDIERS ALONG THE SANTA ANA-METAPAN ROAD SEVERAL TIMES. IN CHALATENANGO, OUR MEN CARRIED OUT CONTINUOUS ACTIONS AGAINST 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE TROOPS IN EL REFUGIO AND OTHER PLACES IN SAN IGNACIO. WE HAVE ALREADY AMPLY REPORTED HEAVY CLASHES AGAINST PARAMILITARY GROUPS IN SAN FRANCISCO CANTON, CABANAS DEPARTMENT, WHERE WE CAPTURED THE AFOREMENTIONED PRISONERS AND CONFISCATED THEIR WEAPONS. WE CARRIED OUT IMPORTANT AMBUSH OPERATIONS AGAINST MILITARY TROOPS TRYING TO TRANSIT THE PANAMERICAN AND COASTAL HIGHWAYS IN SAN VICENTE AND LA PAZ DEPARTMENTS. WE ALSO MET THE BELLOSO BATTALION TROOPS AND CAUSED THEIR FIRST CASUALTIES."

THE STATION ALSO REPORTED THAT GUERRILLAS ATTACKED A SECTION OF THE SORIANO BATTALION IN FINCA LAS MERCEDES AND INFLICTED THREE CASUALTIES ON THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE TROOPS, INCLUDING A RADIO OPERATOR. AN M-16 RIFLE WAS CONFISCATED FROM THE SOLDIERS.

REBEL UNIT WAS SAID TO HAVE AMBUSHED A MILITARY CONVOY ALONG THE COASTAL ROAD NEAR SAN CRISTOBAL IN THE TECOLUCA JURISDICTION, SAN VICENTE DEPARTMENT AT NOON OF 5 NOVEMBER. OUR MEN CONFIRM HAVING INFLICTED 6 ARMY CASUALTIES.

TST3-MUC4-0052

LIMA, 7 NOV 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT TODAY DECREED A STATE OF EMERGENCY AND MILITARY CONTROL IN FOUR LIMA PROVINCES AND EXTENDED THE MEASURE IN ANOTHER FIVE. THIS MEANS ALL OF LIMA DEPARTMENT, WITH A POPULATION OF OVER 6 MILLION PEOPLE, IS UNDER A STATE OF EMERGENCY.

THIS GOVERNMENT DECISION IS A RESULT OF THE TERRORIST ACTIVITY IN THE PROVINCES AND AN ATTEMPT TO PREVENT THE BOYCOTT OF THE ELECTION WHICH WAS DECREED BY THE MAOIST "SHINING PATH" ORGANIZATION.

LIMA DEPARTMENT IS THE LARGEST PERUVIAN DEPARTMENT IN BOTH POPULATION AND ELECTORAL STRENGTH. IT IS MADE UP OF 10 PROVINCES, INCLUDING LIMA PROVINCE, WHICH CONTAINS 90 PERCENT OF THE POPULATION, AND THE CALLAO PORT, WHICH IS RECOGNIZED AS A CONSTITUTIONAL PROVINCE.

ACCORDING TO THE DECREES PUBLISHED TODAY, THE GOVERNMENT IS ESTABLISHING A STATE OF EMERGENCY IN THE PROVINCES OF [WORDS INDISTINCT] AND CANETE, WHILE THE EMERGENCY IN EFFECT IN BARRANCA, CAJATAMBO, HUAURA, YAUYOS, AND OYON WILL BE EXTENDED ANOTHER 30 DAYS. LIMA AND EL CALLAO PROVINCES HAVE BEEN UNDER MILITARY CONTROL SINCE 1 NOVEMBER, WHEN THE GOVERNMENT DECREED A STATE OF EMERGENCY IN THE TWO PROVINCES.

OF PERU'S 24 DEPARTMENTS, 10 ARE UNDER A STATE OF EMERGENCY. THESE AREAS INCLUDE ANDEAN AND JUNGLE TERRITORIES CONTAINING MORE THAN 50 PERCENT OF PERU'S APPROXIMATELY 22 MILLION PEOPLE.

TST3-MUC4-0053

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [REPORT] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] WE ARE HEARING STATEMENTS BY COMMANDER JORGE SHAFIK HANDAL, WHO IS TALKING ABOUT COL PONCE AND CRISTIANI'S RESPONSIBILITY IN THE TERRORIST ATTACK ON FENASTRAS. THIS INCIDENT PROMPTED A VISIT TO OUR COUNTRY BY U.S. OFFICIAL BERNARD ARONSON. LET US HEAR WHAT COMMANDER HANDAL HAS TO SAY ABOUT THE U.S. OFFICIAL'S VISIT.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [HANDAL] OF COURSE, THE UNITED STATES DOES NOT WANT TO APPEAR AS IF IT WERE WITHDRAWING SUPPORT FROM PRESIDENT CRISTIANI. WE WERE JUST SAYING THAT ARONSON HAD ARRIVED AND HE LOOKED WORRIED. THE NICE LOOKING GLASS HOUSE THEY HAD BUILT HAS RAPIDLY BEGUN TO FALL APART. ARONSON APPARENTLY CAME TO SEE HOW HE COULD PATCH THINGS UP. WE RECALL A SIMILAR HIGH-LEVEL VISIT BACK AROUND 1984, IF MY MEMORY SERVES ME RIGHT, WHEN THE CURRENT U.S. PRESIDENT ARRIVED. AT THAT TIME HE WAS VICE PRESIDENT UNDER THE BUSH ADMINISTRATION, NO, THE REAGAN ADMINISTRATION, AND CAME TO SEE HOW TO IMPROVE THE SUPPOSEDLY CENTRIST GOVERNMENT AND HOW TO PUT AN END TO THE DEATH SQUADS. HE TOOK A LIST BACK WITH HIM...[CHANGES THOUGHT] LET US TAKE A LOOK AT HOW THEY OPERATE. WHEN THEY TAKE ANY ACTION THEY ARE VERY CLEAR AND DIRECT. THEY HAD A POLITICAL INTEREST IN PUTTING ALL THIS TOGETHER, SO BUSH TOOK BACK WITH HIM A LIST OF 15 MILITARY MEMBERS SO THEY COULD BE FIRED. [END RECORDING]

TST3-MUC4-0054

SAN SALVADOR, 12 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [STATEMENT] [COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHAIRMAN OF THE JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES] [TEXT] SALVADORAN PEOPLE: GOOD MORNING. I AM SPEAKING ON BEHALF OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES THAT IS ON ITS FEET AT 0115 ON 12 NOVEMBER, CONFRONTING A TREACHEROUS ATTACK BY THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] TERRORISTS WHO AT 2000 ON 11 NOVEMBER--DISPLAYING THEIR WARMONGERING STRATEGY AND WITHOUT CARING ABOUT THE SUFFERING OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE--CARRIED OUT TREACHEROUS ACTIONS IN WHICH THE CIVILIAN POPULATION WERE THE ONLY ONES WHO HAVE SUFFERED.

THE MILITARY AND PUBLIC SECURITY PERSONNEL HAVE REACTED IN AN EFFICIENT MANNER IN REJECTING THE TERRORIST ENEMY. WE ARE OBLIGATED TO REPORT TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WHAT HAS HAPPENED. THE MOST IMPORTANT ACTIONS THAT HAVE TAKEN PLACE ON THE NIGHT OF 11 NOVEMBER ARE AS FOLLOWS: AN ATTACK ON THE RESIDENCE OF THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY PRESIDENT, WHO IS UNHARMED; AND AN ATTACK ON THE CENTRAL ELECTIONS COUNCIL WHERE NO MATERIAL DAMAGE OR CASUALTIES OCCURRED. LIKEWISE, THERE WAS AN ATTACK ON THE PRESIDENTIAL RESIDENCE WHICH CAUSED SLIGHT MATERIAL DAMAGE AND NO CASUALTIES. FORTUNATELY FOR ALL SALVADORANS, THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC IS UNDER FULL PROTECTION AND HE WAS NEVER IN ANY DANGER. LIKEWISE, WE REPORT THAT THERE WAS AN ATTACK ON HIS PRIVATE RESIDENCE.

WE ALSO WANT TO REPORT TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE THAT SOME MILITARY PERSONNEL WERE HARASSED, SUCH AS THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE, THE NATIONAL POLICE GARRISON IN THE ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD, AND THE 6TH INFANTRY BRIGADE IN USULUTAN CITY WHERE ONE MINOR WAS INJURED. THERE WAS ALSO HARASSMENT OF THE 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE WITH HEADQUARTERS IN SAN MIGUEL. THERE WAS NO MATERIAL DAMAGE AND THERE WERE NO CASUALTIES. [CONTINUED]

TST3-MUC4-0055

SAN SALVADOR, 12 NOV 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS ASSURED TODAY THEY HAVE "CONSOLIDATED" FOUR OF THE MOST DENSELY POPULATED NEIGHBORHOODS IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR WHERE SOME 300,000 PERSONS LIVE.

COMMANDER AMILCAR, ONE OF THE REBEL CHIEFS WHO HAS OCCUPIED THE ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD, TOLD ACAN - EFE THAT HE AND HIS MEN CAME TO SAN SALVADOR "PREPARED, AND WITH SUFFICIENT AMMUNITION TO REMAIN FOR SEVERAL DAYS."

IN A GENERAL ASSESEMENT OF THE GUERRILLA OFFENSIVE, THE YOUNG COMMANDER SAID THAT THE ARMY "CANNOT ENTER" THE "AREA UNDER REBEL CONTROL," BUT IT IS ATTACKING THE REBELS FROM THE NATIONAL POLICE HEADQUARTERS AND USING HELICOPTER GUNSHIPS.

"HOWEVER, THE PEOPLE HAVE THE TRUMP CARD (FOR THE SUCCESS OF THE OFFENSIVE)," HE ADDED.

AMILCAR, WHO IS 26-YEARS-AGO AND LOOKS LIKE A STUDENT, WAS WALKING DOWN THE HALLWAYS OF ONE OF THE CRAMPED FIVE-STORY APARTMENT BUILDINGS IN ZACAMIL WHILE EXPLAINING THAT THE GOAL OF THE REBEL OFFENSIVE IS "TO SEEK OPTIONS FOR BUILDING PEACE IN EL SALVADOR."

HE ADDED THAT THE GUERRILLAS SEEK "TO DISRUPT THE DIALOGUE CONDITIONS, AND GO TO THE CONVERSATIONS WITH A POLITICAL AND MILITARY ADVANTAGE SO THAT THE GOVERNMENT WILL AGREE WITH US ON WHAT THE PEOPLE WANT: DEMOCRACY, A PEOPLE'S ECONOMIC POLICY, AND A PURGE IN THE ARMED FORCES, AMONG OTHER THINGS."

THE GUERRILLAS AND THE GOVERNMENT OF EL SALVADOR HAVE HELD TWO MEETINGS IN RECENT MONTHS, THE FIRST ONE IN MEXICO AND THE SECOND ONE IN COSTA RICA. A THIRD MEETING WAS TO BE HELD SHORTLY IN VENEZUELA, BUT THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] ANNOUNCED THAT IT WILL NOT ATTEND.

THE FMLN LAUNCHED THE MOST IMPORTANT MILITARY OFFENSIVE SINCE 1981 ON 11 NOVEMBER, ATTACKING 50 MILITARY POSITIONS, 20 OF THEM IN SAN SALVADOR.

IN THE FIRST 24 HOURS, THE OFFENSIVE HAS CAUSED NEARLY 300 CASUALTIES (127 DEAD AND 155 WOUNDED) ACCORDING TO THE ARMY, AND OVER 400 CASUALTIES ACCORDING TO THE GUERRILLAS.

THE OFFENSIVE HAS BEEN NAMED "OUT WITH THE FASCISTS! FEBE ELIZABETH LIVES!" IN HOMAGE TO A TRADE UNION LEADER KILLED 13 DAYS AGO ALONG WITH NINE OTHER WORKERS IN A DYNAMITE EXPLOSION IN THE CAPITAL CITY ATTRIBUTED TO THE ULTRARIGHTIST DEATH SQUADS.

ARMED WITH AN AUTOMATIC AK-47 RIFLE, AMILCAR SAID THAT THE FMLN "HAS CONSOLIDATED THE ZACAMIL, CUSCATANCINGO, MEJICANOS, AND PANAMA NEIGHBORHOODS, AND WE HAVE BESIEGED THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE."

ALL THE PLACES HE MENTIONED ARE IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR, WHERE THE BLOODIEST CLASHES BETWEEN THE GUERRILLAS AND THE GOVERNMENT TROOPS HAVE TAKEN PLACE.

AT NIGHTFALL ON 12 NOVEMBER AND PRIOR TO THE CURFEW THAT BEGINS AT 2000 (0200 GMT), THE RESIDENTS OF ZACAMIL WERE OUTSIDE THEIR BUILDINGS CARRYING CANDLES AS THERE IS NO ELECTRICITY.

AMILCAR ASSURED THAT THE GUERRILLAS HAVE INFLICTED AT LEAST 18 CASUALTIES ON THE ARMED FORCES IN THAT AREA AND HAVE SEIZED ABOUT 20 RIFLES AND 1 M-60 MACHINEGUN.

"THIS OFFENSIVE IS A MILITARY AND POLITICAL ACHIEVEMENT. AS A RESULT OF THE CLOSING OF THE COMALAPA INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT, THE MAIN AIRPORT OF THE COUNTRY, WE HAVE SUCCEEDED IN LETTING THE WORLD THAT WE ARE AT WAR AND ARE AN EMERGING POWER," THE REBEL COMMANDER SAID.

COMALAPA AIRPORT, LOCATED 50 KM SOUTH OF SAN SALVADOR, WAS CLOSED "FOR SECURITY REASONS."

ACORDING TO THE FMLN CLANDESTINE STATION, RADIO VENCEREMOS, THE GUERRILLA FIGHTERS DESTROYED THREE MILITARY HELICOPTERS ON THE GROUND AND CAUSED SOME DAMAGE ON THE AIRPORTS'S MAIN LANDING STRIP.

REFERRING TO THE GOVERNMENT'S DECISION TO IMPOSE A CURFEW AND A NATIONWIDE STATE OF SIEGE EFFECTIVE TONIGHT, COMMANDER AMILCAR SAID: "WE HAD ALREADY TAKEN THIS INTO CONSIDERATION WHEN WE LAUNCHED THE OFFENSIVE."

THE GOVERNMENT "CANNOT ACT INDISCRIMINATELY AGAINST THE CIVILIAN POPULATION," AMILCAR SAID; ADDING THAT "THE CITIZENS' RIGHTS WERE SUSPENDED TO BOMB THE PLACES TAKEN OVER BY OUR FORCES."

THE PEOPLE OF ZACAMIL AND OTHER NEIGHBORHOODS LOCATED NORTH OF THE CAPITAL HAVE LIVED IN TERROR SINCE SATURDAY, 11 NOVEMBER, WHEN THEY WERE TRAPPED IN THE CROSSFIRE BETWEEN THE REBELS AND THE MILITARY, SUBJECTED TO THE AIR RAIDS AND THE THREAT THAT LIVING WITH THE GUERRILLA MEMBERS REPRESENTS TO THEM.

AT LEAST TWO CIVILIANS HAVE DIED IN ZACAMIL AND FIVE MORE HAVE BEEN WOUNDED, INCLUDING TWO CHILDREN, AS A RESULT OF THE ARMED CLASHES.

TST3-MUC4-0056

CLANDESTINE, 13 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] WE HAVE A LAST MINUTE REPORT FROM SAN MIGUEL. AT EXACTLY 1100 1700 GMT YESTERDAY, 12 NOVEMBER, AN ARMORED PERSONNEL CARRIER WAS DESTROYED WITH AN RPG-7 ROCKET [WORDS INDISTINCT]. FOUR ENEMY CASUALTIES WERE REPORTED. WE REPEAT: AN ARMORED PERSONNEL CARRIER WAS DESTROYED BY OUR FIGHTERS IN SAN MIGUEL. OUR FIGHTERS USED AN RPG-7 ROCKET LAUNCHER TO DESTROY THE ARMORED PERSONNEL CARRIER.

NOW WE HAVE MORE INFORMATION FROM SAN SALVADOR. AT 0800 1400 GMT THIS MORNING, A C-47 PLANE FLEW OVER AND STRAFED THE MEJICANOS DOWNTOWN AREA, WHERE THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE LIVE. ACCORDING TO THE REPORT WE RECEIVED, MANY CIVILIANS HAVE BEEN INJURED. WE WERE ALSO ADVISED THAT THE C-47 LEFT THE AREA AFTER ITS ATTACK.

WE ONCE AGAIN CALL ON THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY TO PRESSURE ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT TO STOP THIS KIND OF HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATION. THESE ACTIONS ARE DIRECTED AGAINST THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. THE ARMED FORCES HAS BEEN SHELLING AND STRAFING DENSELY POPULATED AREAS IN SAN SALVADOR SINCE SATURDAY. IN THE PAST WE HAVE DENOUNCED INDISCRIMINATE SHELLING OF RURAL AREAS; HOWEVER, THESE ARE UNPRECEDENTED ATTACKS. THIS SHELLING AND BOMBING HAS ALREADY RESULTED IN MANY CIVILIAN CASUALTIES.

TST3-MUC4-0058

CLANDESTINE, 14 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] TODAY, 14 NOVEMBER, NEW ATTACKS ARE TAKING PLACE AGAINST POSITIONS OF THE JOINT STAFF OF THE ARMED FORCES. THE PINK ZONE [LA ZONA ROSA] IS TURNING BLACK FOR THE ENEMY. OUR FORCES ARE CLASHING WITH THE ZACAMIL BATTALION.

WE HAVE A REPORT FROM THE CAPITAL SAYING THAT THIS AFTERNOON, FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] FORCES WERE STRONGLY ATTACKING ZACAMIL BATTALION TROOPS. THE FMLN TROOPS ARE HARASSING THE JOINT STAFF OF THE ARMED FORCES AT THIS TIME. BARRICADES ARE BEING SET UP THROUGHOUT THE CAPITAL ON THIS 4TH DAY OF FIGHTING.

THIS IS THE SECOND ATTACK ON THE JOINT STAFF IN LESS THAN 24 HOURS BECAUSE, AS WE SAID LAST NIGHT, FMLN TROOPS INITIATED ATTACKS AGAINST THE SAN BENITO BATTALION AT THE INTERNATIONAL FAIR AND AGAINST THE FORCES DEFENDING THE JOINT STAFF OF THE ARMED FORCES.

THIS IS THE SECOND ATTACK AGAINST THE JOINT STAFF, WHICH COMPLICATES THE OVERALL SITUATION FOR THE ARMED FORCES IN THE CAPITAL. WE ARE ATTACKING THE TOP COMMAND OF THE ENEMY FORCES. FMLN FORCES ARE ATTACKING THE HEART AND THE BRAIN OF THE ENEMY.

SALVADORAN AIR FORCE PLANES ARE OVERFLYING AREAS NORTH OF THE CAPITAL, AND THEY CONTINUE MACHINEGUNNING AND BOMBING CIVILIAN AREAS. A FEW MINUTES AGO, WE REPORTED HEAVY BOMBING IN ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD.

TST3-MUC4-0059

LA PAZ, 15 NOV 89 (LA RED PANAMERICANA) -- [EXCERPT] EARLY THIS MORNING THE GOVERNMENT DECREED A STATE OF SIEGE THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY TO END THE SOCIAL CRISIS AND TO PROTECT THE INTERNAL ORDER, WHICH HAS BEEN DISRUPTED OVER THE PAST FEW HOURS. THIS REPORT IS INCLUDED IN A GOVERNMENT DECREE APPROVED BY PRESIDENT PAZ ZAMORA.

ACCORDING TO INTERIOR MINISTRY UNDER SECRETARY RAUL LOAYZA, POLICE ARRESTED 500 TEACHERS AND EDUCATION LEADERS IN THE NINE DEPARTMENTAL CAPITALS, THUS THWARTING THE EXTENDED HUNGER STRIKE.

THE STRIKE BY TEACHERS, WHO HAVE BEEN DEMANDING A BONUS OF 300 BOLIVIAN PESOS, HAS UNLEASHED VIOLENT STREET CONFRONTATIONS OVER THE PAST FEW DAYS AND AT LEAST FOUR BOMBINGS.

THE GOVERNMENT, WHICH HAS BEEN BESIEGED BY A WAVE OF SOCIAL DEMANDS AND PRESSURED BY THE 80,000 TEACHERS, HAS STATED THAT THESE DEMONSTRATIONS ARE UNDERMINING DEMOCRATIC STABILITY. IT ADDED THAT DESPITE EFFORTS TO FIND A PATH TO PEACEFUL COEXISTENCE AND DIALOGUE, IT HAS NOT BEEN POSSIBLE TO PREVENT RADICAL GROUPS INTERESTED IN THE UNION LEADERSHIP FROM PUBLICLY CHALLENGING THE GOVERNMENT.

THE GOVERNMENT DECREE STATES THAT IT WILL GUARANTEE THE 3 DECEMBER MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS AND PROTECT THE CITIZENS' RIGHT TO VOTE.

A FEW MINUTES BEFORE THE RELEASE OF THIS DECREE TO THE PRESS, POLICE PATROLS RAIDED THE CENTERS WHERE THE HUNGER STRIKES WERE TAKING PLACE. POLICE USED EXCESSIVE FORCE IN THESE RAIDS.

THE 250 STRIKERS ARRESTED IN LA PAZ WERE TAKEN IN TRUCKS AND BUSES OF THE POLICE, THE AIR FORCE, AND OTHER STATE INSTITUTIONS, TO THE EL ELTO AIR BASE.

THE GOVERNMENT REPORTED THAT 250 STRIKERS WERE ALSO ARRESTED IN THE INTERIOR OF THE COUNTRY. IT ADDED THAT THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE STRIKE WILL BE SENT TO DIFFERENT REGIONS OF THE COUNTRY. OTHER, LESS RESPONSIBLE GROUPS OF STRIKERS WILL BE TRIED BY THE REGULAR COURTS. OTHERS WILL BE RELEASED.

THE THREE LA PAZ TEACHERS' LEADERS HAVE BEEN SENT TO DIFFERENT HOSPITALS IN LA PAZ AND PLACED IN INTENSIVE CARE. THEY ARE MIGUEL LORA, TELMO ROMAN, AND LUIS ALVAREZ, WHO ARE NOT FACING ANY RISK OF DEATH, THE INTERIOR MINISTRY UNDER SECRETARY STATED. HE WARNED THAT THE BOLIVIAN LABOR CONFEDERATION UNDERGROUND SESSIONS WILL BE ILLEGAL, AND THEY ARE NOT THE MOST APPROPRIATE FOR LABOR ORGANIZATIONS, HE SAID.

THIS IS THE FIRST SOCIAL CRISIS PRESIDENT PAZ ZAMORA HAS HAD TO FACE SINCE HE ASSUMED POWER ALMOST 100 DAYS AGO.

TST3-MUC4-0060

CLANDESTINE, 16 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [HUMAN RIGHTS PROMOTION AND PROTECTION SECRETARIAT OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, FMLN] [TEXT] THE HUMAN RIGHTS PROMOTION AND PROTECTION SECRETARIAT [SECRETARIA DE PROMOCION Y PROTECCION DE LOS DERECHOS HUMANOS] OF THE FMLN STRONGLY CONDEMNS THE MASSACRE OF FIVE SPANISH-BORN JESUIT PRIESTS AND THREE SALVADORAN CITIZENS CARRIED OUT BY THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES SOLDIERS. IGNORING A MARTIAL LAW PROHIBITING ALL TRAVEL, EARLY THIS MORNING A LARGE NUMBER OF HEAVILY ARMED SOLDIERS BURST INTO THE RESIDENCE OF THE PRIESTS WHO MANAGE THE JOSE SIMEON CANAS CATHOLIC UNIVERSITY [UCA]. THE SOLDIERS BROKE INTO THE PRIESTS' BEDROOMS, CAPTURED THEM, AND BRUTALLY MURDERED THEM IN THE GARDEN.

THE VICTIMS OF THIS HATEFUL COLLECTIVE CRIME WERE: PRIEST AND DR IGNACIO ELLACURIA, THE UCA DIRECTOR; PRIEST AND DR IGNACIO MARTIN BARO, UCA DEPUTY DIRECTOR; PRIEST AND DR SEGUNDO MONTES, UCA HUMAN RIGHTS INSTITUTE DIRECTOR; PRIEST AND DR AMANDO LOPEZ, UCA DEAN; PRIEST JUAN RAMON MORENO; AND JOAQUIN LOPEZ Y LOPEZ, AS WELL AS JULIA RAMOS AND HER 15-YEAR-OLD DAUGHTER, ELVA RAMOS.

THE PERSONS WHO ORDERED THE HORRIBLE MURDER OF THE JESUITS AND THREE SALVADORAN CITIZENS ARE THE SAME ONES WHO ORDERED PILOTS, ARTILLERY MEN, AND MACHINEGUNNERS IN PLANES TO ATTACK THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. THEY ARE THE SAME ONES WHO ARE AGAINST REACHING A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT. THEY ARE THE TOP MILITARY AND POLITICAL FIGURES IN ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S ADMINISTRATION.

THE HUMAN RIGHTS PROMOTION AND PROTECTION SECRETARIAT CALLS ON THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY TO TIE THE HANDS OF THESE MURDERERS OF SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND TO AID IN FINDING A SOLUTION TO THE NATIONAL CRISIS SO WE MAY ATTAIN A JUST AND LASTING PEACE OUR PEOPLE SO DESIRE.

NO MORE BARBARIC ACTIONS IN SAN SALVADOR. NO MORE INJUSTICES. TRIAL AND PUNISHMENT FOR THE MURDERERS. THE MILITARY AND POLITICAL LEADERS OF CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT MUST BE OUSTED.

EL SALVADOR, 16 NOV 1989

TST3-MUC4-0061

MOSCOW (USSR), 14 NOV 89 (IZVESTIYA) -- [TEXT] FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] DETACHMENTS HAVE CONDUCTED THE LARGEST MILITARY OPERATION IN THE ENTIRE HISTORY OF THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT IN THE COUNTRY'S CAPITAL.

AN OFFENSIVE WAS LAUNCHED SIMULTANEOUSLY THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY'S TERRITORY; HOWEVER, SAN SALVADOR'S CITY BLOCKS, WHICH WERE THE SCENE OF FIERCE FIGHTING BETWEEN FMLN DETACHMENTS AND GOVERNMENT TROOPS, WERE THE EPICENTER OF SUNDAY'S EVENTS. THE INTENSE FIREFIGHT INVOLVING ARTILLERY AND HELICOPTERS LASTED APPROXIMATELY 18 HOURS AND ENCOMPASSED VIRTUALLY THE ENTIRE CAPITAL, COMPLETELY PARALYZING LIFE IN THE CITY. ACCORDING TO REUTER, ATTEMPTS WERE MADE TO STORM PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S OFFICIAL AND PERSONAL RESIDENCES; HOWEVER, IT IS REPORTED THAT THE PRESIDENT WAS NOT HURT.

REPORTS OF THE LOSSES ON BOTH SIDES ARE CONTRADICTORY.

A STATE OF SIEGE HAS BEEN INTRODUCED IN EL SALVADOR AND CONSTITUTIONAL GUARANTEES HAVE BEEN SUSPENDED. A CURFEW IS IN FORCE IN THE CAPITAL, AND THE INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT HAS BEEN CLOSED. ACCORDING TO PRESIDENT CRISTIANI, WHOSE SPEECH WAS BROADCAST ON THE RADIO, THESE STEPS ARE NEEDED TO "DEFEND THE POPULATION AGAINST LEFT-WING TERRORISM." ACCORDING TO THE PRESIDENT, THE MILITARY ARE IN COMPLETE CONTROL OF THE SITUATION; HOWEVER, IT IS REPORTED FROM SAN SALVADOR THAT THESE WORDS BY A. CRISTIANI WERE HEARD ON THE AIRWAVES ACCOMPANIED BY CONTINUAL EXPLOSIONS AND SHOOTING.

INTERNATIONAL OBSERVERS REGARD EVENTS IN SAN SALVADOR IN THE CONTEXT OF THE INTERRUPTED TALKS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE INSURGENTS. THE THIRD ROUND OF THESE TALKS SHOULD HAVE BEEN HELD RECENTLY IN CARACAS, BUT OPPOSITION REPRESENTATIVES REFUSED TO TAKE PART IN THEM AFTER A LEFT-WING TRADE UNION'S HEADQUARTERS WAS SUBJECTED TO ARTILLERY BOMBARDMENT RESULTING IN THE DEATHS OF AT LEAST 10 PEOPLE. ACCORDING TO THE INSURGENTS, THE GOVERNMENT DECIDED ON DIALOGUE WITH THEM SOLELY OUT OF PROPAGANDA CONSIDERATIONS, WITH NO INTENTION OF REACHING ANY AGREEMENT. SUNDAY'S OFFENSIVE WAS THUS AN ATTEMPT ON THEIR PART TO SHOW THEMSELVES TO BE A FORCE TO BE RECKONED WITH.

IN THE OPINION OF OBSERVERS, HOWEVER, EVENTS IN SAN SALVADOR PRACTICALLY RULE OUT ALL HOPES OF SUCCESS FOR FUTURE TALKS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND REPRESENTATIVES OF THE INSURGENTS. MOREOVER, THE FIGHTING IN THE SALVADORAN CAPITAL, A REUTER CORRESPONDENT BELIEVES, DEALT THE FRAGILE PEACE SETTLEMENT PROCESS IN CENTRAL AMERICA A CONSIDERABLE BLOW.

TST3-MUC4-0062

SAN SALVADOR, 16 NOV 89 -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CRISTIANI] [CONTINUED] THAT IS THE POSITION OF THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT. WITH THE INFORMATION IT HAS, THE GOVERNMENT CANNOT POINT THE FINGER AT ANYONE. IT CANNOT ACCUSE ANYONE YET, BECAUSE THERE IS NO CONCLUSIVE EVIDENCE IN THIS CASE. WE BELIEVE THERE MAY BE SOME PEOPLE WHO CAN COOPERATE WITH US IF WE HELP THEM. THERE MAY BE SOME WITNESSES, WHO MAY BE WILLING TO COOPERATE, BUT THEY MAY NOT BE AVAILABLE RIGHT NOW. [WORDS INDISTINCT] HE SAID HE WAS WILLING TO HELP. THEY WANTED THE INVESTIGATIONS TO TAKE PLACE.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[CRISTIANI] WELL, I BELIEVE MUCH DEPENDS ON THE POSITION OF THE FMLN. I HAVE LISTENED TO SEVERAL VERSIONS ALL THE WAY FROM DEMANDING MY RESIGNATION TO ASSASSINATION ATTEMPTS AGAINST ME TO FINISH EVERYTHING UP. UNDER THESE TERMS, THEY ARE SAYING WE ARE ABOUT TO CREATE A NEW LEBANON, AND THEY ARE SAYING THE FMLN HAS CONTROL OVER CERTAIN LIBERATED AREAS IN THE CAPITAL. HOWEVER, IF WE TALKED ABOUT THE SITUATION RATIONALLY AND REASONABLY, THERE COULD BE [WORD INDISTINCT].

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[CRISTIANI] WELL, WE HAVE TALKED ABOUT THE AIR FORCE SITUATION IN THE PAST. THE AIR FORCE HAS ORDERS NOT TO BOMB AND NOT TO USE ITS WEAPONS AGAINST URBAN AREAS OF THE CAPITAL UNLESS IT HAS BEEN ABLE TO DETECT AND ISOLATE A CLEAR FMLN TARGET. IN THIS REGARD, AIR FORCE BOMBS WERE NOT USED UNTIL LAST NIGHT WHEN AIR FORCE PLANES WERE ATTACKED FROM SOME SUGARCANE FIELDS NORTH OF THE 1533 LANDING STRIP [16-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION]...USE BOMBS TO STOP THE USE OF FMLN MORTARS. THE AIR FORCE USED MACHINEGUNS [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE ONLY TIME THEY WERE USED WITHIN THE URBAN AREA, TO BE SURE THEY WERE NOT ENDANGERING ANYONE, WERE TWO MORTARS INSTALLED IN THE SOCCER FIELD OF THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY. [WORDS INDISTINCT] ONE WAS FIRED AT THE POLICE BATTALION IN ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD, AND THE OTHER WAS FIRING AT THE 1ST BRIGADE. [WORDS INDISTINCT] I BELIEVE THAT AMONG THE WEAPONS THAT WERE SEIZED, THERE ARE SOME OF THAT. I AM NOT TOO SURE.

IN THE [WORDS INDISTINCT], NEAR THE SAN JACINTO HILL WERE USED TO SUPPORT TROOPS THAT WERE USING THE SAN JACINTO HILL. WE BELIEVE IT WAS THE FMLN WITHRAWING [WORDS INDISTINCT] IN SANTA MARTA. UP TO NOW, THE POSITION OF THE ARMED FORCES STAFF AND THE HIGH COMMAND IN THE USE OF THE AIR FORCE IS ONLY [WORDS INDISTINCT] AND WHEN SPECIFIC TARGETS CAN BE ISOLATED IN WHICH THE CIVILIAN POPULATION IS NOT ENDANGERED.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[CRISTIANI] I DO NOT HAVE IT WITH ME RIGHT NOW, BUT THERE WILL BE A REPORT ON THE MILITARY SITUATION [WORDS INDISTINCT] BY THE HIGH COMMAND TONIGHT. [CONTINUED]

TST3-MUC4-0063

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] A FASCIST IDEOLOGY HAS INFILTRATED THE WHITE HOUSE AND NO ONE SHOULD BE SURPRISED BECAUSE IT COINCIDES WITH THE ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] IDEOLOGY. THE U.S. GOVERNMENT HAS ACKNOWLEDGED THE BOMBINGS AFTER CYNICALLY SAYING IT KNEW NOTHING ABOUT THEM. HOWEVER, THAT ACKNOWLEDGEMENT IS EVEN MORE HAIR-RAISING THAN THE DENIAL. HEAR US WELL: THE U.S. GOVERNMENT HAS STATED THAT IT SUPPORTS THE GOVERNMENT TROOPS' EFFORTS TO CRUSH THE OFFENSIVE WHICH HAS CAUSED SO MANY PERSONAL TRAGEDIES; AND IT PRAISED THE ARMY FOR DECREEING STRICT LAWS TO PREVENT CIVILIAN CASUALTIES.

WE ALSO HEAR THE PET EXPRESSION THAT THE FMLN IS USING CIVILIANS TO PROTECT ITS FIGHTERS, AND THE PRINCIPLE OF REMOVING THE PEOPLE FROM THEIR ENVIRONMENT IS UNSCRUPULOUSLY APPLIED ONCE MORE. THIS IS WHY THE NORTHERN PART OF THE COUNTRY WAS DESTROYED, LEAVING ENTIRE TOWNS IN RUINS -- AND NOW LARGE AREAS OF THE COUNTRY'S MOST IMPORTANT CITIES ARE BEING DESTROYED. ONE DAY THOSE RUINS WILL BECOME THE EVIDENCE WE WILL SHOW OUR CHILDREN TO PROVE THAT FASCISM ONCE EXISTED IN THE COUNTRY.

HOWEVER, THE U.S. IMPERIALISM'S CLUMSINESS GOES EVEN FURTHER. THE NORTH AMERICANS APPARENTLY WANT TO BECOME INVOLVED IN A LARGE-SCALE CONFLICT -- FOR THE SAKE OF A FEW DEATH SQUAD MEMBERS WHO HAVE ALREADY EARNED THE WORLD'S SCORN -- GIVEN THE DECISION TO SEND U.S. PILOTS TO BOMB THE CIVILIAN POPULATION BY NIGHT. THE FASCIST SALVADORAN DICTATORSHIP HAS UNLEASHED THE BRUTAL TACTICS USED BY SOMOZA BEFORE LEAVING POWER. ON THAT OCCASION THE U.S. IMPERIALISM TURNED ITS BACK ON THE TYRANT.

THE UNITED STATES' FOREIGN POLICY HAVE NEVER STOOPED SO LOW AND THE DECISIONS ADOPTED BY THE U.S. GOVERNMENT HAVE NEVER BROUGHT THE POSSIBILITY OF A REGIONAL CONFLICT SO CLOSE. WHAT DOES THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT THINK ABOUT THE AIRPLANES BEING FLOWN BY U.S. PILOTS ONLY A FEW HUNDRED KM FROM ITS BORDER? WHAT WILL HAPPEN IF GUATEMALA CONTINUES TO INVOLVE ITSELF IN THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT? THE CONSEQUENCES ARE UNFORESEEABLE. THE U.S. IMPERIALISM HAS SOILED ITS HANDS WITH A NEW GENOCIDE IN EL SALVADOR. THE U.S. PEOPLE SHOULD DEEPLY REFLECT ABOUT THIS AND STOP THEIR GOVERNMENT FROM PROVOKING CONTEMPT OF THAT NATION -- WHICH IS BEING DISINFORMED AND INTOXICATED BY THE ANTI-COMMUNIST PROPAGANDA.

LARGE GROUPS OF ABRAHAM LINCOLN'S PEOPLE, THE BEST SONS OF THE UNITED STATES, HAVE REACTED AND HAVE TAKEN TO THE STREETS --DEEP INSIDE THE U.S. IMPERIALISM'S HEART. SOON, VERY SOON, THIS WILL BECOME AN UNSTOPPABLE SURGE. THE U.S. GOVERNMENT'S STRATEGIC GOAL IS CLEAR: THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. THE U.S. GOVERNMENT WANTS THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE TO [WORDS INDISTINCT]. TO QUOTE MONSIGNOR [OSCAR ARNULFO] ROMERO, THE ARMY -- AND IN THIS CASE THE NORTH AMERICANS -- ARE LIKE SERPENTS, WHICH ONLY BITE THE SHOELESS. YET THEY DO NOT KNOW THAT THE PEOPLE HAVE RISEN IN ANGER AND DIGNITY, AND THEY ARE COMING TO PULL OUT THE FASCIST SERPENT'S FANGS.

TST3-MUC4-0065

BURGOS (SPAIN), 19 NOV 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] APPROXIMATELY 1,000 PEOPLE DEMONSTRATED TODAY AT THE BURGOS MAIN SQUARE (CENTRAL) TO ASK THE SPANISH GOVERNMENT TO MEDIATE IN THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT, AND IN BARCELONA (NORTHEASTERN), A DEMONSTRATION TO EXPRESS SUPPORT FOR THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE HAS BEEN SCHEDULED FOR 22 NOVEMBER.

THE DEMONSTRATORS, CONVOKED BY THE SOLIDARITY WITH LATIN AMERICA COMMITTEE, VERBALLY ATTACKED SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI AND HAVE ASKED THE SPANISH GOVERNMENT TO OFFER ITSELF AS A MEDIATOR TO PROMOTE AN END THE ARMED CONFLICT.

SOME OF THE PEOPLE WHO ATTENDED THE DEMONSTRATION, WHICH WAS HELD WITHOUT INCIDENTS, CARRIED PLACARTS DENOUNCING THE KILLING OF SIX JESUIT PRIESTS -- FIVE OF WHOM WERE SPANISH CITIZENS -- AND TWO SALVADORAN WOMEN AT THE CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY.

MEANWHILE, CIVIC ORGANIZATIONS, STUDENT ASSOCIATIONS, LABOR UNIONS, AND POLITICAL PARTIES IN CATALUNA HAVE SCHEDULED A DEMONSTRATION IN SUPPORT OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE TO BE HELD IN BARCELONA ON 22 NOVEMBER.

THESE ORGANIZATIONS, WHICH HAVE FORMED AN EMERGENCY COMMITTEE, HAVE OPENED AN ACCOUNT AT THE "LA CAIXA" SAVINGS BANK WHERE ECONOMIC DONATIONS ARE BEING ACCEPTED TO HELP THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

IN A MANIFESTO RELEASED, THE COMMITTEE DEMANDS AN END TO THE BOMBING OF CIVILIANS, THE IMMEDIATE EVACUATION OF THE WOUNDED, AND AN END TO ATTACKS AGAINST THE UNION HEADQUARTERS AND LEADERS.

LIKEWISE, THE COMMITTEE HAS DEMANDED AN END TO U.S. INTERVENTION IN EL SALVADOR AND THAT THE GUATEMALAN AND HONDURAN ARMIES REFRAIN FROM PARTICIPATING IN THE CONFLICT.

"WE ASK THE SPANISH GOVERNMENT INSTITUTIONS AND THE EEC TO PRESSURE THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT TO BEGIN A REAL NEGOTIATION THAT WILL AN END TO THE CONFLICT AND ITS CAUSES, THE MANIFESTO STATES.

TST3-MUC4-0067

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [REPORT] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] HEAVY CLASHES ARE TAKING PLACE RIGHT NOW IN ESCALON AND SAN BENITO RESIDENTIAL AREAS. THERE IS NO GOING BACK. WE HAVE BROKEN THE DEFENSIVE LINES OF THE ENEMY. WE HAVE BROKEN [WORDS INDISTINCT] IN THE CAPITAL CITY, WE ARE FIGHTING IN FRONT OF THE DENS OF COLONEL PONCE AND OTHER OFFICERS WHO HAVE TURNED THE WAR INTO A BUSINESS. THOSE OFFICERS HAVE LUXURIOUS MANSIONS IN MIAMI. EVERY WEEKEND AND EVEN IN SPITE OF THE WAR, COL PONCE HAS ORGIES IN HIS LUXURIOUS HOMES IN THE COUNTRY'S INTERIOR. SOLDIERS, PATRIOTIC OFFICERS, WE CALL ON YOU TO JOIN THE PEOPLE AND JOIN OUR FRONT. PATRIOTIC OFFICERS, WHO ARE LISTENING TO US, DO NOT ALLOW MORE BOMBINGS IN OUR CAPITAL CITY BY THE GENOCIDAL TANDONA GROUP [1966 GRADUATING CLASS OF THE CAPT GEN GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY SCHOOL]. YOUNG OFFICERS, LIEUTENANTS WHO ARE BEING KILLED IN THE RESIDENTIAL AREAS AND NEIGHBORHOODS OF THE CAPITAL CITY, WHY SHOULD YOU BE KILLED WHILE DEFENDING PONCE'S MANSIONS? THIS IS THE LAST SCENARIO OF THE LAST CHAPTER IN WHICH THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] WILL ACHIEVE THE VICTORY OF THE PEOPLE. WE CALL ON YOUR CONSCIENCE, YOUNG PATRIOTIC OFFICER.

JUST LOOK AT WHAT HAPPENED IN THE BOMBINGS OF ZACAMIL. OVER 500 HOMES WERE RAZED. ARE YOU GOING TO ALLOW THE HIGH COMMAND TO FINISH OFF THE CITY, TO FINISH OFF THE NEIGHBORHOODS AND RESIDENTIAL AREAS WHERE YOUR RELATIVES MIGHT BE? YOU SAW WHAT HAPPENED IN ZACAMIL, MEJICANOS, SOYAPANGO. PATRIOTIC OFFICER, IT IS TIME WE SIT DOWN TO TALK, TO SEE WHAT WE CAN DO WITH OUR FATHERLAND, AND WHAT ARE WE GOING TO DO WITH LA TANDONA. PATRIOTIC OFFICERS WHO ARE LISTENING TO US: IT IS USELESS TO CONTINUE DEFENDING; TO CONTINUE DEFENDING WHAT, WE ASK YOU. THE FATHERLAND? WHAT FATHERLAND? THE FATHERLAND YOU ARE TOLD YOU ARE DEFENDING ARE THE MILLIONS AND THE MANSIONS OF COL PONCE AND OF COL ELENA FUENTES. PATRIOTIC OFFICERS: THE TIME IS HERE, TAKE ONE STEP FORWARD.

WE HAVE MORE REPORTS FROM SAN SALVADOR: EARLY THIS MORNING, COMBAT HAS BEEN RESUMED IN THE FOLLOWING PLACES: ESCALON, SAN BENITO, AND LA SULTANA RESIDENTIAL AREAS. THESE ATTACKS ARE AGAINST THE SOLDIERS FROM MILITARY DETACHMENT NO. 6 AND THE CAVALRY. COMBATS ARE ALSO REPORTED NORTH OF AYUTUXTEPEQUE, AGAINST SOLDIERS FROM THE 4TH AND 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE. THERE ARE ALSO CLASHES IN THE AREA OF METROPOLIS AND ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOODS AGAINST SOLDIERS FROM THE BRACAMONTE BATTALION.

IT IS IMPORTANT TO POINT OUT THAT IN SAN BENITO AND LA SULTANA RESIDENTIAL AREAS, WE ARE FIGHTING AGAINST SOLDIERS FROM SONSONATE, AND NOT FROM SAN SALVADOR. THE SOLDIERS ARE FROM MILITARY DETACHMENT NO. 6 OF SONSONATE. TROOPS FROM SONSONATE HAVE BEEN BROUGHT INTO SAN SALVADOR, BECAUSE THE HIGH COMMAND HAS LOST CONTROL OF THE SITUATION. IN OTHER WORDS, THERE IS A MIXTURE OF SOLDIERS FROM ALL PARTS OF THE COUNTRY IN THE CAPITAL CITY. THIS HAS YIELDED NEGATIVE RESULTS FOR THE HIGH COMMAND. IN THE CAPITAL CITY, THERE HAVE BEEN CLASHES BETWEEN THE ATLACATL BATTALION AND THE NATIONAL POLICE, AND THE NATIONAL GUARD HAS ATTACKED TROOPS FROM MILITARY DETACHMENT NO. 6. THESE ARE LITTLE SOLDIERS FROM SONSONATE WHO HAVE BEEN BROUGHT INTO THE CAPITAL CITY, AND THEY ARE NOT FAMILIAR WITH THE CITY. THEY ARE CLASHING AGAINST EACH OTHER.

CLASHES ARE ALSO REPORTED WITH THE 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE AND THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE IN AYUTUXTEPEQUE. IN OTHER WORDS, THE 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE IS FIGHTING IN AYUTUXTEPEQUE. WHAT WILL HAPPEN IN THE INTERIOR OF THE COUNTRY? THE GARRISONS HAVE BEEN LEFT EMPTY. THE SAN FRANCISCO GOTERA GARRISON HAS BEEN LEFT WITHOUT ANYONE. THE 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE IS BEING LEFT BY ITSELF, AS WELL AS THE MILITARY DETACHMENT NO. 1. THE COLONELS ARE DESPERATE AND ARE BRINGING TROOPS INTO THE CAPITAL CITY.

THIS IS A GOOD REPORT. THE 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE AND MILITARY DETACHMENT NO. 6 ARE IN THE CAPITAL. THIS IS THE SITUATION ON THIS MORNING OF VICTORIOUS BATTLES. WHO WOULD BELIEVE IT? THE SONSONATE SOLDIERS ARE FIGHTING IN THE CAPITAL CITY. THIS GIVES US A GENERAL PICTURE OF THE DEFEAT. IF THE SONSONATE TROOPS ARE FIGHTING IN THE LAST DEFENSIVE LINE, THIS MEANS THAT THE SONSONATE LINES HAVE BEEN WIPED OUT.

ATTENTION, FMLN ANTIAIRCRAFT UNITS HAVE OPENED FIRE WITH THEIR M-60 MACHINEGUNS AGAINST UH-1H HELICOPTERS THAT ARE FLYING OVER THE RESIDENTIAL AREAS OF THE OLIGARCHY. LIKEWISE, A HELICOPTER IS RIGHT NOW FLYING OVER THE ARMED FORCES GENERAL STAFF OFFICES. FMLN UNITS ARE FIRING THEIR ANTI-AIRCRAFT WEAPONS IN THE ESCALON RESIDENTIAL AREA.

TST3-MUC4-0068

SAN SALVADOR, 21 NOV 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] THE REBEL COMMANDERS WHO DIRECTED THE OCCUPATION OF SEVERAL SAN SALVADOR NEIGHBORHOODS LAST WEEK, TODAY HEADED THE SEIZURE OF THE SHERATON HOTEL, WHERE OAS SECRETARY GENERAL JOAO BAENA SOARES WAS TRAPPED FOR MORE THAN 8 HOURS.

NEWSMEN WHO ENTERED THE HOTEL THIS AFTERNOON DURING THE EVACUATION OF BAENA BY DIPLOMATS WERE ABLE TO CONFIRM THAT COMMANDER AMILCAR, KNOWN AS "EL CHOCO," WHO DIRECTED THE COMBAT OPERATIONS IN THE ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD, WAS SEEN TODAY ON THE THIRD FLOOR OF THE SHERATON HOTEL.

SEVERAL REBELS HAVE SAID THAT FACUNDO GUARDADO ("COMMANDER ESTEBAN"), ONE OF THE FOUNDERS OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT AND ONE OF THE LEADERS OF THE OFFENSIVE THAT BEGAN IN THE CAPITAL ON 11 NOVEMBER, IS SOMEWHERE NEAR THE HOTEL.

ACCORDING TO THE REBELS, GUARDADO EXPECTED TO INITIATE THIS AFTERNOON'S "NEGOTIATIONS" WITH THE MANAGER OF THE HOTEL, ROBERT NEWELL. SEVERAL U.S. MILITARY ADVISERS, AS WELL AS ONE FROM GUATEMALA AND ANOTHER ONE FROM CHILE REMAIN IN THE HANDS OF THE REBELS. EL CHOCO SAID: "WE CAN RESIST FOR AS LONG AS WE HAVE TO. ALL THEY CAN DO IS BOMB THE PLACE AND LET US SEE IF THEY ARE WILLING TO DO THAT."

ACCORDING TO THE YOUNG GUERRILLA COMMANDER, THE REBEL WITHDRAWAL FROM THE ZACAMIL, CUSCATANCINGO, AND MEJICANOS NEIGHBORHOODS, AMONG OTHERS, "WAS PART OF THE PLAN" THAT WAS COMPLETED TODAY WITH THE ARRIVAL AT THE SHERATON HOTEL AREA. THE REBEL SAID: "WE HAVE COME HERE TODAY, TO THE ESCALON COLONY, TO THEIR AREA, THE AREA OF THE BOURGEOISIE, TO SEE IF THEY DO HERE WHAT THEY DID WITH THE PEOPLE, WHO WERE HURT BY THE AIR FORCE BOMBING OPERATIONS."

AT 0430 (1030 GMT) TODAY, THE FMLN GUERRILLAS INITIATED HEAVY FIGHTING AROUND THE SHERATON HOTEL, WHERE OAS SECRETARY GENERAL JOAO BAENA SOARES WAS STAYING.

BAENA SOARES WAS EVACUATED FROM THE SHERATON HOTEL TO THE HEADQUARTERS OF THE ARMED FORCES STAFF WHERE HE MET WITH THE "HIGHEST SALVADORAN AUTHORITIES," ACCORDING TO DIPLOMATIC AND MILITARY SOURCES.

THIS AFTERNOON, THE GUERRILLAS ARE STILL OCCUPYING SEVERAL FLOORS OF THE HOTEL, WHICH HAS BULLET HOLES, DESTROYED WINDOWS, AND BROKEN FURNITURE ALL OVER THE FLOOR.

THE AREA HAS BEEN SURROUNDED BY LIGHT ARMORED TANKS AND IS BEING PATROLLED BY SEVERAL ARMED SALVADORAN AIR FORCE HELICOPTERS.

TST3-MUC4-0069

HAVANA (CUBA), 22 NOV 89 (RADIO REBELDE NETWORK) -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] THE PICTURE PUBLISHED TODAY BY THE NEWSPAPER GRANMA IN ITS THIRD EDITION SPEAKS FOR ITSELF. IN FACT, AS THE NEWSPAPER SUGGESTS, THE YANKEE HAND IS TODAY IN EL SALVADOR AS IT WAS YESTERDAY IN VIETNAM. THE WOUNDED MOTHER WHO TRIES TO COMFORT HER DAUGHTER, A VICTIM OF THE BOMBINGS, IS NOT AN ISOLATED PICTURE. IT IS A SYMBOL OF THE CRIMES THAT ARE BEING COMMITTED AGAINST THE CIVILIAN POPULATION IN THAT COUNTRY.

THE UNITED STATES IS NOT INNOCENT OF THESE CRIMES BECAUSE U.S. PILOTS ARE PARTICIPATING IN THE MASSACRE. IN THE MEANTIME, WHAT IS THE HUMAN RIGHTS CHAMPION DOING? IN FACT, HE IS DOING NOTHING THAT COULD NOT BE PREDICTED. PRESIDENT BUSH GETS ON THE PHONE AND CALLS HIS SALVADORAN CRONY ALFREDO CRISTINI TO ASSURE HIM THAT EVERYTHING IS ALL RIGHT, THAT HE CAN GO ON, THAT THE U.S. POSITION IS FAVORABLE TO HIS REGIME. THE HUMAN RIGHTS CHAMPION ASKS NO QUESTIONS ABOUT THE RECENT BRUTAL KILLINGS OF UNION LEADERS BY THE ARMY. BUSH ASKS NO QUESTIONS ABOUT THE MASSACRE OF SPANISH PRIESTS. THE PRESIDENT ONLY PRAISES THE ARMY, THE AIR FORCE, THE POLICE AND PARAMILITARY EFFORTS TO STOP THE GUERRILLA OFFENSIVE.

BUSH AND CRISTIANI COULD NOT FAIL TO MENTION THE TRITE SLOGAN OF THE CUBAN AND NICARAGUAN AID TO THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS. NOR DID BUSH FAIL TO EXPRESS THE AMERICAN PEOPLE'S SOLIDARITY. BUT, SOLIDARITY WITH WHOM? ALL WE HAVE HEARD ABOUT UP TO NOW ARE THE PROTESTS PROVOKED IN THE UNITED STATES BY THE U.S. MILITARY AID TO THE SALVADORAN REGIME. THE ONLY REALITIES ARE THE DEMONSTRATIONS STAGED FROM LOS ANGELES TO NEW YORK TO REPUDIATE THE U.S. AID. THE ONLY FACT IS THAT THE HUMAN RIGHTS CHAMPION IS BEING PUBLICLY QUESTIONED ABOUT THIS AID. THE ONLY PICTURE THAT HAS BEEN DISSEMINATED THROUGHOUT THE WORLD IS THAT OF A WOMAN WHO INTERRUPTS BUSH'S SPEECH TO SHOUT TO HIM: WHY ARE WE SENDING MONEY TO EL SALVADOR? WHY ARE WE KILLING PRIESTS IN EL SALVADOR? IT IS NOT POSSIBLE TO OVERLOOK THE U.S. GOVERNMENT'S RESPONSIBILITY IN THE CURRENT SALVADORAN SITUATION. THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY MUST BE AWARE OF THIS REALITY AND MUST ACT ACCORDINGLY.

TST3-MUC4-0070

SAN SALVADOR, 26 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI, IN PROGRESS] [TEXT] ...THAT THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] LAUNCHED AGAINST THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE ON 11 NOVEMBER. THE FMLN LAUNCHED THIS AGGRESSION WITH ALL OF ITS FORCES, CHIEFLY USING A CONCENTRATION OF WEAPONS AND FIGHTERS IN THE SAN SALVADOR METROPOLITAN ZONE, IN ZACATECOLUCA, LA PAZ DEPARTMENT, AND AT TIMES IN USULUTAN CITY, USULUTAN DEPARMENT, AND IN SAN MIGUEL CITY, SAN MIGUEL DEPARTMENT. IN THIS AGGRESSION THE FMLN DISPLAYED ITS WEAPONRY. IT DISPLAYED AN INCREDIBLE AMOUNT OF WEAPONS, WHICH....[CHANGES THOUGHT] BY THE WAY, IN RECENT DAYS THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES HAVE BEGUN A NUMBER OF SEARCHES IN SOME HOUSES WHERE IT IS BELIEVED THAT SOME OF THESE WEAPONS WERE LOCATED. WE HAVE ALREADY FOUND LARGE AMOUNTS OF WEAPONS.

IN ADDITION, THE FMLN LAUNCHED AN AGGRESSION AND HID BEHIND YOU, SALVADORAN PEOPLE. IT USED YOU AS A SHIELD, WANTING TO CONVEY THE IDEA THAT THEY HAVE THE SUPPORT OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND THAT THE PEOPLE HERE WOULD RISE UP TO SUPPORT THEM. THEY HAVE REALIZED THAT THIS VIEW IS TOTALLY FALSE. FAR FROM SUPPORTING THE FMLN, THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, SALVADORAN BROTHERS, SUPPORTED THE ARMED FORCES IN THE TREMENDOUS EFFORT IT HAS CONDUCTED TO REPEL THE FMLN AGGRESSION.

HOWEVER, WE MUST NOW CONSIDER A VERY IMPORTANT MATTER. IT IS IMPOSSIBLE TO CARRY OUT AN AGGRESSION OF THIS SIZE WITHOUT SUPPORT FROM SOMEONE ABROAD. ON THIS OCCASION, WE ARE CERTAIN THAT THIS SUPPORT CAME FROM NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT ORTEGA AND CUBAN PRESIDENT CASTRO, BUT CHIEFLY FROM ORTEGA WHO IS TRYING TO RAISE A SMOKESCREEN IN THE FACE OF THE REAL POSSIBILITY THAT MRS VIOLETTA CHAMORRO MAY DEFEAT HIM IN THE ELECTIONS, AND BECAUSE THE FMLN HAS ALWAYS BEEN THE PUPPET OF THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNIST AGGRESSION IN WHICH ORTEGA AND CASTRO PARTICIPATE. IF THIS IS NOT SO, LET US TAKE A LOOK AT WHAT HAS HAPPENED. DURING THOSE TIMES WHEN YOU WERE SUFFERING MOMENTS OF ANGUISH LAST WEEK, YOU WERE ABLE TO SEE THE LARGE NUMBER OF FOREIGNERS WHO WERE SUPPORTING THE FMLN TERRORISTS. WE HAVE ALSO MANAGED TO COLLECT EVIDENCE THAT THE ORTEGA GOVERNMENT TRAINED FMLN FIGHTERS IN THE USE OF CERTAIN KINDS OF WEAPONRY, SPECIFICALLY THE GRENADE LAUNCHERS.

WHAT HAPPENED? IN THE PAST FEW WEEKS WE BEGAN NOTICING WHAT KIND OF WEAPONS WERE BEING USED. IN THE FOILED ATTACK ON THE PRESIDENTIAL HOUSE, A SUBSEQUENT ATTACK ON THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES' JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF, AND LASTLY, AN ATTACK ON THE NATIONAL GUARD GARRISON PARTICULAR KINDS OF WEAPONS WERE BEING USED. AS A RESULT OF THE SAVAGE ACTION BY FMLN, TWO LITTLE GIRLS WERE KILLED. MOREOVER, LET US RECALL AND SEE THE CONNECTION THAT EXISTS WITH ALL THE SHIPMENTS THAT THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES HAVE BEEN STOPPING BETWEEN NICARAGUAN AND EL SALVADOR. ONE SHIPMENT WAS MADE PRIOR TO THE VISIT WE PRESIDENTS MADE TO COSTA RICA. IN THAT COUNTRY, WE DENOUNCED ORTEGA FOR CONTINUING TO SEND WEAPONS AND SUPPORTING THE FMLN IN AN OPEN VIOLATION OF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PEACE PROCESS.

AND WHAT HAS HAPPENED LATELY? ON 25 NOVEMBER, SALVADORAN PEOPLE, TWO LIGHT AIRPLANES COMING FROM NICARAGUA WERE DISCOVERED. THEIR FLIGHT COURSE INDICATES THAT THEY CAME FROM NICARAGUA, ESPECIALLY THE ONE WHERE THE WEAPONS WERE FOUND. AS ADDITIONAL PROOF, WE HAVE A DOCUMENT SHOWING THAT ONE LIGHT AIRCRAFT BELONGS TO THE SETA TRANSPORTATION COMPANY LOCATED IN NICARAGUA'S AUGUSTO CESAR SANDINO AIRPORT. IT WAS BRINGING SOPHISTICATED EQUIPMENT FOR THE FMLN. IN THAT AIRCRAFT ACCIDENT, FOUR PEOPLE WERE KILLED: THE PILOT WHO WAS WEARING CIVILIAN CLOTHES AND THREE OTHER PEOPLE WERE WEARING MILITARY UNIFORMS; I MEAN CAMOUFLAGE UNIFORMS LIKE THE ONES WORN IN MANY COUNTRIES, AND LIKE THE ONES THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCE USE. IT IS BELIEVED THAT TWO OF THOSE PEOPLE DIED AS A RESULT OF THE ACCIDENT. WE ALSO BELIEVE THAT ANOTHER PERSON KILLED HIMSELF BECAUSE HE HAD A WEAPON IN HIS HAND AND A BULLET WOUND IN FOREHEAD. HE KILLED HIMSELF BECAUSE HE SAW HIMSELF IMPLICATED IN THIS SITUATION. [CONTINUED]

TST3-MUC4-0071

CLANDESTINE, 29 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] OUR FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] FORCES HAVE TAKEN OVER BUNKERS FROM THE VARIOUS MILITARY CHIEFS IN ESCALON AND MANUEL JOSE ARCE NEIGHBORHOODS WHERE OUR UNITS SEIZED THOUSANDS OF CARTRIDGES, RIFLES, GRENADES, AND OTHER TYPES OF ARMS WHICH THESE MILITARY CHIEFS USUALLY STORE IN THE BUNKERS THAT THEY MAINTAIN IN THESE RESIDENTIAL SECTORS.

AS WE HAVE REPORTED, THE GENERAL STAFF RESPONDED WITH A 4-PRONGED DELAYED RESPONSE. THE ARMED FORCES ATTACKED FROM FOUR ADVANCED POSITIONS, ONE HELD BY THE BRACAMONTE BATTALION, WHICH ADVANCED TOWARD ESCALON; IT WAS NEUTRALIZED BY OUR AMBUSHES. OUR UNITS ARE ENTRENCHED IN THE MANSIONS OF THE OLIGARCHS IN THAT SECTOR OF ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD. THEY AMBUSHED AND REPELLED ATTACKS FROM THE VANGUARD POSITIONS LAUNCHED BY THE ARMED FORCES. THE SECOND DIRECTION IN WHICH THE ENEMY RESPONDED TO OUR PRESENCE WAS DIRECTED ON THE SOUTHERN FREEWAY. THIS SECOND POSITION WAS AMBUSHED WITH RPG-7 ROCKET LAUNCHERS AND MACHINEGUN FIRE. THE THIRD ENEMY POSITION, WHICH WAS ADVANCING ON SANTA TECLA, WAS AMBUSHED AT LA UNIVERSAL POINT AND WAS ALSO NEUTRALIZED. THE ATLACATL BATTALION DEPLOYMENT ALONG GUADALUPE GARDENS WAS ALSO NEUTRALIZED. OUR BATTALIONS ARE STAGING SABOTAGE ACTIONS ON ELECTRICITY POSTS IN THE ESCALON AND SAN BENITO NEIGHBORHOODS.

ALSO, WE HAVE A NEW REPORT WHICH INDICATES THAT FMLN UNITS HAVE SET UP DOWNED ELECTRICITY POSTS AS BARRICADES ALONG THE SOUTH FREEWAY AND IN THE ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD. WE REPEAT, ALONG THE SOUTH FREEWAY AND IN THE ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD, FMLN UNITS HAVE USED DOWNED ELECTRICITY POSTS AND VEHICLES AS BARRICADES.

THIS IS THE SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR. THROUGHOUT THE NORTHERN SECTOR OF THE CAPITAL, OUR UNITS ARE MAINTAINING POSITIONS. THE TROOPS IN THE INTERIOR PART OF THE REPUBLIC IN THAT NORTHERN REGION REFUSE TO ADVANCE TOWARD OUR POSITIONS, WHILE OUR UNITS ARE EXTENDING ALONG THE NORTHWESTERN AND SOUTHWESTERN REGION OF THE CAPITAL. OUR UNITS ARE EXTENDING AND MOVING FOWARD ALONG THESE ZONES. THE AIR FORCE HAS OPENED FIRE ON SOME OF OUR POSITIONS IN THE ESCALON AND SAN BENITO NEIGHBORHOODS. WE REITERATE THE CALL TO THE INHABITANTS OF THE ESCALON AND SAN BENITO NEIGHBORHOODS TO ABANDON ALL THOSE ZONES IMMEDIATELY. THE AIR FORCE IS BEGINNING NEW AIR RAIDS ON FMLN POSITIONS IN THOSE REGIONS. THEREFORE, WE CALL ON THE INHABITANTS OF THE ESCALON AND SAN BENITO NEIGHBORHOODS TO LEAVE THOSE AREAS.

TST3-MUC4-0072

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 1 DEC 89 (RADIO CORPORACION) -- [TEXT] LA PRENSA NEWSPAPER TODAY REPORTED THAT THE SANDINISTS DID SEND A PLANE TO EL SALVADOR. THE AIRCRAFT IS A CESSNA 310. THE IDENTITY OF THE CREWMEN IN THE NICARAGUAN PLANES THAT CRASHED IN EL SALVADOR OVER THE PAST WEEKEND CARRYING SOVIET ARMS IS A STATE SECRET ACCEDED TO BY LA PRENSA THIS MORNING AFTER GETTING IN TOUCH WITH A HIGH-RANKING SOURCE IN THE SANDINIST ARMY. THE SOURCE DISCLOSED FURTHER DETAILS OF THE BUTTERFLY OPERATION. THE ARMY SOURCE, WHICH OF COURSE REQUESTED TO REMAIN ANONYMOUS, CONFIRMED THAT THE PLANE THAT CRASHED IN SAN MIGUEL BELONGS TO NICARAGUA AND THAT THE PLANE'S REGISTRATION IS YANKEE NOVEMBER BRAVO YANKEE KILO.

THERE ARE NO REPORTS SO FAR AS TO WHETHER ANY RELATIVES HAVE CLAIMED THE BODIES OF THE FOUR MILITARY MEN WHO WERE REPORTEDLY KILLED WHEN THE PLANE CRASHED. THREE OF THE CREWMEN WERE KILLED INSTANTLY, WHILE THE FOURTH COMMITTED SUICIDE. A PICTURE OF A YOUNG CUBAN GIRL, DATED IN JULY, IS THE ONLY PUBLISHED CLUE AS TO THE IDENTITY OF THE MEN, WHETHER NICARAGUANS, CUBANS, OR SALVADORANS, COMMISSIONED FOR THIS CLANDESTINE MISSION DIRECTED FROM NICARAGUA. OUR SOURCE SAID THAT YOUNG SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS WERE TRAINED AT THE NATIONAL CIVILIAN FLIGHT SCHOOL OVER THE PAST FEW MONTHS. THE TRAINING WAS SUPERVISED BY CAPTAIN ROBIN ROMERO, THE FLIGHT SCHOOL'S DIRECTOR. THE TRAINING WAS ALSO CONDUCTED AT PUNTA HUETE AND LOS BRASILES. MOST OF THE FLIGHTS WERE MADE AT NIGHT. THE STUDENT PILOTS USED OIL LAMPS AS LANDING LIGHTS. THE SOURCE SAID THE TRAINING FLIGHTS WERE CONDUCTED IN LIGHT SINGLE-ENGINE PLANES FROM SANDINO AIRPORT TO PUNTA HUETE OR LOS BRASILES.

THE HEAD OF THIS OPERATION WAS COMMANDER CHRISTIAN PICHARDO. IN THE OPERATION ALSO PARTICIPATED TWO SALVADORAN GUERRILLA COMMANDERS WHOSE IDENTITIES ARE UNKNOWN. THE CESSNA 310 HAD BEEN LEASED BY THE NATIONAL DEVELOPMENT BANK [BND], WHICH IN TURN HAD ACQUIRED THE PLANE FROM THE ZETA NATIONAL CHARTER SERVICE, AN AERONICA SUBSIDIARY. BND ADMINISTRATIVE DIRECTOR MARCOS BLANDON GRAVY LEASED THE PLANE, ONE OF SEVERAL AIRCRAFT INTENDED TO BE SENT TO EL SALVADOR. ANOTHER SINGLE-ENGINE CESSNA, WITH REGISTRATION CHARLIE BRAVO PAPA, AND AN AERO COMMANDER, WERE ADDED TO THE INVENTORY. ACCORDING TO OUR SOURCE, THE AERO COMMANDER WAS CONFISCATED FROM COLOMBIAN DRUG TRAFFICKERS IN PUERTO CABEZAS A YEAR AGO WHEN THEY WERE INTERCEPTED BY SANDINIST AIR FORCE [FAS] PLANES. THE PLANES INVOLVED IN THE OPERATION, HOWEVER, REMAINED UNEQUIPPED TO FLY TO EL SALVADOR UNTIL FURTHER NOTICE. [CONTINUED]

TST3-MUC4-0074

SAN SALVADOR, 6 DEC 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] THE TREASURY POLICE HAVE INFORMED THIS NETWORK THAT TERRORIST [WORDS INDISTINCT] ALBERTO CHICA FERNANDEZ, A LEADER IN THE [NAME INDISTINCT] LABOR UNION, CONFESSED THAT THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] TERRORIST LEADERS MAY INITIATE SUMMARY ACTIONS WITH A VIEW TO PURGING THE LEADERS OF LEFTIST GROUPS BECAUSE OF THE FAILURE OF THE SO-CALLED "FINAL OFFENSIVE TO THE END."

CHICA SAID THAT THE TERRORIST LEADERSHIP HAS VIOLENTLY [WORD INDISTINCT] HUMBERTO CENTENO, MARCO TULIO LIMA, AND AN INDIVIDUAL IDENTIFIED ONLY AS JULIO CESAR, FROM THE UNTS [NATIONAL UNION OF SALVADORAN WORKERS], AS WELL AS OTHER LEFTIST LEADERS, FOR PROVIDING FALSE INFORMATION REGARDING THE CONDITIONS FOR A POPULAR INSURRECTION.

ACCORDING TO CHICA, THE FMLN LEADERS IN MANAGUA DECIDED TO LAUNCH THE OFFENSIVE, TRUSTING THE UNTS LEADERS' REPORTS THAT CONDITIONS WERE RIGHT FOR AN INSURRECTION BECAUSE FEBE ELIZABETH VELAZQUEZ' DEATH IN THE DYNAMITE ATTACK AGAINST FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION] HAD IGNITED THE PEOPLE'S SPIRITS. THE PRISONER SAID THAT THE FMLN MAY CARRY OUT A SUMMARY TRIAL IN THE STYLE OF COMMUNIST PARTIES AGAINST THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE FAILURE.

NOW, HE SAID, TO SAVE THEMSELVES FROM THE RESPONSIBILITY OF HAVING DECEIVED THE TERRORIST CRIMINALS WHO ALLOWED THEMSELVES TO BE LED BY LIES, THE UNTS LEADERS ARE EXPECTED TO CALL NEWS CONFERENCES TO ANNOUNCE THAT THEIR STRUGGLE CONTINUES.

MEANWHILE, A REPORT FROM ZACATECOLUCA, LA PAZ DEPARTMENT, INDICATES THAT FMLN TERRORIST CRIMINALS, USING SAM-7 MISSILES, ATTACKED A SALVADORAN AIR FORCE 0-2 AIRPLANE WHICH WAS IN THE AREA DIRECTING SUPPORT NEAR PIEDRA GRANDE ABAJO IN THE JURISDICTION OF ZACATECOLUCA. NO DAMAGES OR CASUALTIES WERE REPORTED.

ANOTHER FMLN MISSILE WAS FIRED FROM LAS PIEDRAS HILL, IN THE SAME AREA, AGAINST ANOTHER SALVADORAN AIR FORCE 0-2 AIRPLANE, BUT THE AIRPLANE WAS NOT DAMAGED. THE SOURCE SAYS THE MISSILE EXPLODED IN THE AIR OVER ZACATECOLUCA.

THE AIR FORCE, TO WHICH EXPERIENCED PILOTS LEND THEIR PROFESSIONAL SERVICES, IS ADMIRED BY THE PEOPLE, WHO ARE GRATEFUL TO THEIR ARMED FORCES.

TST3-MUC4-0075

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (RADIO CADENA CUSCATLAN) -- [TEXT] [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY UNIDENTIFIED MODERATOR AND REPORTERS] [CONTINUED] [MODERATOR] MARCO ANTONIO GUEVARA, OF THE "UP TO DATE" NEWSCAST.

[GUEVARA] HOW DO THE FIVE PRESIDENTS CONCEIVE THE DEMOBILIZATION OF THE FMLN? HOW DOES THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT CONCEIVE THIS HAPPENING?

[CRISTIANI] I BELIEVE THERE HAVE BEEN SUBSTANTIAL CHANGES IN THIS PRESIDENTIAL MEETING AS COMPARED TO PREVIOUS MEETINGS. TO EXPLAIN THIS BETTER, MARCO ANTONIO, WE MUST SAY WE WILL NOT FALL INTO WHAT HAS BEEN USED IN THE PAST, THAT IS, THE FAMOUS SYMMETRY. ON THIS OCCASION, WE HAVE BEEN VERY CLEAR AND CATEGORICAL WHEN WE SAID THAT WE WERE NOT WILLING TO CONTINUE CONTRIBUTING SACRIFICES AND OTHER THINGS FROM THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IN ORDER TO SOLVE THE NICARAGUAN PROBLEM EXCLUSIVELY. WE DEMANDED UNIFORMITY, AND ANY OTHER COUNTRY CONFRONTING THE AGGRESSION OF AN IRREGULAR FORCE -- ANY OTHER COUNTRY IN CENTRAL AMERICA -- ALSO HAS THE RIGHT TO BE TREATED IN A UNIFORM MANNER, AS FAR AS MEASURES AND CRITERIA THAT MAY BE ADOPTED IN THE PRESIDENTIAL MEETINGS.

THAT IS WHY TODAY FOR THE FIRST TIME YOU ARE SEEING HOW THE MEASURES ADOPTED FOR THE NICARAGUAN RESISTANCE -- THAT HAD BEEN GRANTED MOST OF THE ATTENTION UP TO NOW -- ARE ALSO BEING ADOPTED FOR THE FMLN.

WE CANNOT ALLOW A COUNTRY TO CLAIM IT IS THE ONLY TARGET OF AN AGGRESSION BY AN IRREGULAR ARMED FORCE SUPPORTED FROM ABROAD. HERE IN EL SALVADOR WE NOW HAVE GREATER EVIDENCE FOLLOWING THIS 11 NOVEMBER TERRORIST AGGRESSION THAT THE FMLN IS A MOVEMENT THAT CAN SURVIVE ONLY WITH SUPPORT FROM ABROAD, AND THAT IT OBEYS AND EXISTS BECAUSE OF INTERNATIONAL MOVEMENTS.

IN THE SECOND PLACE, IT HAS DEMONSTRATED THAT IT ONLY HAS THE CAPACITY TO GENERATE TERRORISM, WHICH HAS BEEN MENTIONED IN THIS DOCUMENT. WE CANNOT CONTINUE JUST TALKING ABOUT DEMOBILIZATION AND PACIFICATION IN NICARAGUA. IT IS TIME TO APPLY THIS TO ALL IRREGULAR GROUPS, BE IT THE URNG [GUATEMALAN NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY UNITY] IN GUATEMALA, OR ANY OTHER IRREGULAR ARMED GROUP THAT MAY COME UP AND MAY TRY TO HINDER THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS IN THE AREA.

WE SEE THIS AS SOMETHING THAT HAS GONE DEEP INTO THE MINDS OF ALL THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS, AND FROM NOW ON, WE WILL HAVE GREATER UNIFORMITY IN TREATING ALL OF THOSE IRREGULAR GROUPS THAT OPERATE IN THE REGION.

[MODERATOR] RENE HURTADO OF EL MUNDO.

[HURTADO] MR PRESIDENT, FOLLOWING THE TELA AND COSTA DEL SOL MEETINGS, NICARAGUA HAS CHANGED ITS STAND. IN COSTA RICA, PRESIDENT ORTEGA WAS ASKED IF HE HAD SOLD OUT THE FMLN IN EXCHANGE FOR THE DEMOBILIZATION OF THE CONTRAS AND OTHER RESULTS OF THE SUMMIT IN FAVOR OF NICARAGUA. I WOULD LIKE TO KNOW YOUR OPINION ABOUT THIS, AND ALSO HOW YOU INTERPRET THE FACT THAT PRESIDENT ORTEGA HAS ACCEPTED SOME ISSUES ABOUT THE FMLN THAT HE DID NOT ALLOW IN TELA OR COSTA DEL SOL? ON THE OTHER HAND, WILL THE DEMOBILIZATION OF THE FMLN BE THE RESULT OF A DIALOGUE OR NEGOTIATIONS LATER ON?

[CRISTIANI] IN THE FIRST PLACE, I BELIEVE THAT DANIEL ORTEGA WAS UNABLE TO PULL ANY MORE TRICKS OUT OF HIS HAT, AND HE WAS FACING A FACT HE COULD NO LONGER HIDE: HE IS THE ONE WHO IS SPREADING ARMED REVOLUTIONS IN CENTRAL AMERICA AND TRYING TO HAMPER DEMOCRATIC PROCESSES IN THE REGION. ONCE MORE HE HAS BEEN CAUGHT NOT HONORING THE COMMITMENTS AGREED ON IN TELA, BUT RATHER VIOLATING THESE COMMITMENTS. ON THIS OCCASION HE HAS BEEN LEFT WITH NO POSSIBLE DEFENSE.

THEREFORE, IN OUR OPINION, HE HAS NO OPTION OTHER THAN TO ACCEPT THE REALITY OF WHAT IS HAPPENING IN CENTRAL AMERICA, OR SEE HIMSELF TOTALLY ISOLATED AMID A PEACE PLAN THAT HAS INTERNATIONAL SUPPORT. THIS SITUATION WOULD CAUSE HIM MANY PROBLEMS AND HEADACHES IN POLITICAL AND DIPLOMATIC MATTERS.

TST3-MUC4-0076

CLANDESTINE, 13 DEC 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] COMRADES: A NEW ELEMENT THAT WE MUST ANALYZE AND EXPLAIN EMERGED AT THE CONCLUSION OF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS' EMERGENCY MEETING. LET US SEE FIRST WHY THE MEETING TOOK PLACE. THE MAIN REASON IS THE VERY COMPLICATED PREDICAMENT IN WHICH OUR OFFENSIVE HAS PLACED CRISTIANI AND THE HIGH COMMAND. AS YOU WILL REMEMBER, THE GOVERNMENT HAS MET WITH MUCH INTERNATIONAL DISREPUTE AND ISOLATION BECAUSE OF THE BRUTAL ASSASSINATION OF JESUIT PRIESTS AND THE BOMBING OF THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. LET US RECALL, AS A SIGNIFICANT FACT, THAT THE UNITED NATIONS HAS CONDEMNED THE GOVERNMENT BECAUSE OF ALL IT HAS DONE, ESPECIALLY BECAUSE OF THE LATEST ATROCITIES. ON THAT OCCASION, EL SALVADOR WAS THE ONLY COUNTRY THAT VOTED AGAINST THAT RESOLUTION WHILE 96 COUNTRIES VOTED IN FAVOR.

WE MENTION THIS CASE AS A MOST SIGNIFICANT ONE, BUT THE FACT IS THAT THERE HAS BEEN SO MUCH WORLDWIDE CONDEMNATION THAT THE DICTATORSHIP HAS FOUND ITSELF IN A REALLY DESPERATE SITUATION. THIS WAS A CAUSE OF CONCERN FOR THE NORTH AMERICANS.

TO WHOM COULD THEY TURN AT A TIME WHEN ALL INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS HAD TURNED THEIR BACKS ON CRISTIANI? THE NORTH AMERICANS HAD TO RESORT TO SOME FORUM THAT WOULD NOT CONDEMN THE GENOCIDAL REGIME AND THAT, ON THE CONTRARY, WOULD PROVIDE SUPPORT IN SPITE OF ALL THE ATROCITIES THE REGIME HAS COMMITTED.

THE MOST SUITABLE IDEA WAS TO PROMOTE AN EMERGENCY MEETING OF CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS, BECAUSE IN CENTRAL AMERICA, AS WE ALL KNOW, THE NORTH AMERICANS HAVE HAD THEIR BACKYARD AND MOST OF THESE COUNTRIES SERVE THEIR INTERESTS.

THE MEETING WAS CALLED TO TRY TO PULL CRISTIANI OUT OF INTERNATIONAL ISOLATION.

UNDER WHAT CONDITIONS DID SUMMIT TAKE PLACE? WE HAVE TO SAY FIRST THAT THE PRESIDENTS OF EL SALVADOR AND COSTA RICA, AND PROBABLY OF GUATEMALA, HAD REACHED AN AGREEMENT PRIOR TO THE MEETING. THE SUBJECT OF THE DISCUSSION WAS A DOCUMENT DRAFTED BY ARIAS AND CEREZO. THIS DOCUMENT EXPRESSED SUPPORT FOR CRISTIANI FROM THE VERY BEGINNING. JOSEPH SULLIVAN, A U.S. STATE DEPARTMENT OFFICIAL IN CHARGE OF LATIN AMERICAN AFFAIRS, AS WELL AS OTHER U.S. STATE DEPARTMENT OFFICIALS, WERE PRESENT AT THE MEETING. THE COSTA RICAN AMBASSADOR TO NICARAGUA -- A PRO-U.S. MAN WHO INTRODUCED THE NICARAGUAN CONTRAS AT THE MEETING -- WAS ALSO PRESENT, CONSPIRING ALL THE TIME. THE FMLN WAS NOT EVEN ALLOWED TO ENTER COSTA RICA.

HOWEVER, IN SPITE OF THE FACT THAT THE MEETING HAD BEEN FIXED AND IN SPITE OF THE U.S. PRESENCE, THE AGREEMENT TO SUPPORT CRISTIANI WAS ACHIEVED ALMOST AT THE PRICE OF KILLING THE ESQUIPULAS AGREEMENT. IT WAS NOT EASY. THE U.S. WILL TO CONDEMN THE FMLN AND TO BACK CRISTIANI PREVAILED IN THE MIDST OF MUCH BICKERING AND THE INSOLENCE OF THE HONDURAN PRESIDENT.

AS YOU CAN SEE, IT WAS NOT EASY TO FIND SUPPORT FOR THE GENOCIDAL REGIME EVEN IN PLACES WHERE THE NORTH AMERICANS THINK THEY HAVE THE BULL BY THE HORNS.

LET US SEE, AS A THIRD POINT, IN WHAT THE DECLARATION CONSISTS. [CONTINUED]

TST3-MUC4-0077

BOGOTA, 15 DEC 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] IN VIEW OF THE SUCCESSFUL OPERATION TODAY IN WHICH GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, HIS SON FREDDY, AND SEVERAL OF HIS BODYGUARDS WERE KILLED, PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO TODAY CALLED AN URGENT COUNCIL OF MINISTERS MEETING TO DISCUSS THE SITUATION AND RECEIVE A FULL REPORT FROM MILITARY AND POLICE AUTHORITIES. HERE IS THE SECOND PART OF THE NEWS CONFERENCE FEATURING DAS DIRECTOR GENERAL MIGUEL MAZA MARQUEZ.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MAZA] THE DAS HAS EVIDENCE SHOWING THAT THIS INDIVIDUAL MASTERMINDED TWO ATTACKS INCLUDING THE THE MOST RECENT AND WORST ONE IN WHICH MORE THAN 60 INNOCENT PEOPLE WERE KILLED.

[REPORTER] HOW DO YOU KNOW THAT GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA MASTERMINDED THE RECENT ATTACK ON DAS?

[MAZA] BECAUSE THE INVESTIGATIONS THAT WE HAVE CONDUCTED ALONG WITH THE NATIONAL POLICE EVER SINCE THE ATTACK OCCURRED POINT IN THAT DIRECTION. IF WE COMPARE THE MODUS OPERANDI OF RODRIGUEZ AND HIS PEOPLE, WE COME TO THE CONCLUSION THAT THE PERIOD BETWEEN THE [WORD INDISTINCT] AND THE ACTION ITSELF ARE VERY SIMILAR. FURTHERMORE, THIS MAN WAS IN THERE CELEBRATING THE GENOCIDE THAT HE HAD COMMITTED IN BOGOTA.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[MAZA] BECAUSE THE INTELLIGENCE REPORTS INDICATE THIS, AND ACCORDING TO CERTAIN STATEMENTS WE HAVE, HE WAS OVERJOYED BY THE DAMAGE THAT HE HAD CAUSED IN THE CITY GIVEN THE LARGE NUMBER OF PEOPLE WHO WERE KILLED; SEEING HIM SUNBATHING AND SWIMMING ON THE ATLANTIC COAST LED US TO BELIEVE THIS.

[REPORTER] IS THIS A POLICE REACTION TO THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS' ATTACK ON DAS?

[MAZA] NO, I AM NOT SAYING THAT IT IS A REACTION. THIS IS THE RESULT OF VERY PROFESSIONAL WORK ON THE PART OF THE NATIONAL POLICE. THAT IS WHAT I TOLD THE PRESIDENT TODAY. I BRIEFED HIM ON THE EVENTS WHICH LED TO THE ACTION THAT HAS CHANGED THE SITUATION WHICH HAD PREVAILED IN THE COUNTRY JUST A FEW HOURS AGO. [END RECORDING]

TST3-MUC4-0079

QUITO, 18 DEC 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] ACCORDING TO A COMMUNIQUE GIVEN TO AFP, THE INTERNATIONAL REBEL ORGANIZATION, THE AMERICA BATTALION, WILL "CONTINUE ITS CONTINENTAL STRUGGLE FOR LIBERTY, JUSTICE, AND LATIN AMERICAN DIGNITY." IN ADDITION TO THE COMMUNIQUE, PHOTOGRAPHS OF REBELS IN MOUNTAIN AREAS WERE ALSO GIVEN TO AFP.

SIGNED BY THE AMERICAN BATTALION'S GENERAL COMMAND, THE COMMUNIQUE -- WRITTEN ON A SHEET WITHOUT THE ORGANIZATION'S LETTERHEAD -- STATES THAT THEY BACK THE DECISIONS MADE BY THE 19 APRIL MOVEMENT (M-19) OF COLOMBIA AND ALVARO LIVES, DAMMIT! OF ECUADOR TO SIGN PEACE AND DEMOCRACY AGREEMENTS WITH THEIR RESPECTIVE GOVERNMENTS.

THESE TWO ORGANIZATIONS, TOGETHER WITH THE TUPAC AMARU MOVEMENT OF PERU, FOUNDED THE AMERICAN BATTALION IN COLOMBIA 5 YEARS AGO. THE BATTALION SUFFERED HEAVY CASUALTIES IN COLOMBIA AND IT WAS BELIEVED TO HAVE DISAPPEARED. TODAY'S COMMUNIQUE, HOWEVER, ANNOUNCED THE EXISTENCE OF OTHER ORGANIZATIONS FORMING THE AMERICAN BATTALION.

THEY REQUEST THAT THE M-19 GIVE THEM THE SWORD OF LIBERATOR SIMON BOLIVAR AND RECALLED THEIR ORGANIZATION'S PRINCIPLES AND CAMILO TORRES' WORDS TO THE LIBERATOR: "GENERAL, AS LONG AS YOUR SWORD LIVES, THE FATHERLAND IS NOT DEAD."

THE REBELS ALSO STATE THAT THEY BACK SINCERE LATIN AMERICAN EFFORTS TO ATTAIN PEACE FOR THE REGION AND "FIND POLITICAL SOLUTIONS WITH THE LOWEST SOCIAL COST AND LOSS OF BLOOD FOR OUR PEOPLE."

THE INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATION TOLD THE ANDEAN PRESIDENTS MEETING AT THE GALAPAGOS ISLANDS THAT "TODAY THAT THEY HAVE THE POWER," THEY SHOULD "EXERT IT IN FAVOR OF THE PEOPLE, IN FAVOR OF A TRUE DEMOCRACY." HOWEVER, THEY CRITICIZED "THE MURDERS IN STREETS OF CARACAS," THE MURDERS IN THE JAILS OF PERU," AND "THE TORTURE IN THE JAILS OF ECUADOR."

WITH REGARD TO THE ANDEAN LEADERS, THE REBELS NOTED THAT "EITHER THEY ARE WITH LATIN AMERICA OR THEY ARE WITH THE NORTHERN TYRANTS," REFERRING TO THE UNITED STATES.

THE MOVEMENT STATES THAT THEY HAVE GATHERED ON REPRESSION AND STATES THAT 4,000 UNION MEMBERS HAVE BEEN ILLEGALLY ARRESTED AND THAT 200,000 HAVE "DISAPPEARED."

"THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE ARE NOT ALONE," ADDS THE COMMUNIQUE AND STATES THAT AT THE REQUEST OF THE PEOPLE OR THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, WE ARE "WILLING TO MOVE OUR MEN AND DECLARE WAR ON THE FACISTS' FOREIGN ECONOMIC INTERESTS," INCLUDING "PRESIDENT (ALFREDO) CRISTIANI'S DIPLOMATIC REPRESENTATIVES" IN THE REGION.

CONCLUDING, THE COMMUNIQUE STATES: "IF LATIN AMERICANS HAVE TO GO WITH BOLIVAR'S SWORD TO SAN SALVADOR AND CENTRAL AMERICA, WE WILL DO SO."

THE DOCUMENT IS SIGNED BY THE COMMANDERS OF THE VICTORS' PACE REGIMENT [REGIMIENTO A PASO DE VENCEDORES], SAN MARTIN SOUTHERN FRONT [FRENTE SUR SAN MARTIN], B-5-R NOBODY SURRENDERS HERE [B-5-R AQUI NADIE SE RINDE], AND E.R.P. [REVOLUTIONARY PEOPLES ARMY] BRIGADES.

TST3-MUC4-0080

SAN SALVADOR, 8 JAN 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] OFFICIAL SOURCES TODAY REPORTED THAT AT LEAST EIGHT PEOPLE, INCLUDING SOLDIERS, REBELS, AND CIVILIANS, WERE KILLED DURING CLASHES BETWEEN THE ARMY AND GUERRILLAS OVER THE PAST WEEKEND IN VARIOUS POINTS OF THE COUNTRY.

MILITARY SPOKESMEN FOR THE 6TH INFANTRY BRIGADE, HEADQUARTERED IN THE EASTERN USULUTAN DEPARTMENT, TOLD ACAN-EFE THAT TWO REBELS WERE KILLED AND ONE WOUNDED DURING A CLASH WITH GOVERNMENT TROOPS IN SAN AGUSTIN.

MEANWHILE, THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE (COPREFA) REPORTED THAT THE BODIES OF TWO GUERRILLAS, WHO WERE PRESUMABLY KILLED DURING CLASHES WITH THE ARMY, WERE FOUND BY SOLDIERS IN THE OUTSKIRTS OF SANTA TECLA, IN THE CENTRAL LA LIBERTAD DEPARTMENT.

COPREFA REPORTED THAT TWO SOLDIERS WERE KILLED DURING A CLASH WITH MEMBERS OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) IN COMASAGUA, ABOUT 28 KM TO THE SOUTHWEST OF [SAN] SALVADOR, WHERE A REBEL ATTACK ON A COFFEE PROCESSING PLANT WAS SUCCESSFULLY REPELLED.

IT REPORTED THAT A CIVILIAN WAS KILLED IN THE CROSSFIRE AND THAT A SOLDIER WAS ALSO KILLED DURING CLASHES IN ZARAGOZA, SOUTH OF SAN SALVADOR, WHERE TWO GUERRILLAS WERE WOUNDED.

THE MILITARY REPORT STATED THAT 10 REBELS WERE WOUNDED IN TECOLUCA, SAN VICENTE DEPARTMENT, ABOUT 60 KM EAST OF THE CAPITAL, DURING AN ARMED CLASH BETWEEN INSURGENTS AND THE 5TH [INFANTRY] BRIGADE, HEADQUARTERED IN THAT DEPARTMENT.

THREE OTHER SOLDIERS WERE WOUNDED DURING AN FMLN AMBUSH IN GUAZAPA, NORTH OF [SAN] SALVADOR, ONE OF THE GUERRILLAS' MAIN BASTIONS.

THE SALVADORAN [AIR] FORCE THIS MORNING BOMBED REBEL POSITIONS IN THE OUTSKIRTS OF JUCUAPA, USULUTAN DEPARTMENT, BUT NO RESULTS ARE YET AVAILABLE, AREA RESIDENTS TOLD ACAN-EFE.

THE FMLN THIS MORNING HARRASSED [ARMY POSITIONS STATIONED NEAR] AYUTUXTEPEQUE, NORTH OF [SAN] SALVADOR, WITHOUT INFLICTING ANY CASUALTIES.

COPREFA ALSO REPORTED THAT THE [ARMED] FORCES SEIZED FROM THE GUERRILLAS 500 ELECTRIC CATAPULTS, IN THE NORTHERN [CHALATENANGO] DEPARTMENT, WHICH THE FMLN HAD USED SINCE LAST YEAR TO ATTACK [SAN] SALVADOR GARRISONS.

SALVADORAN [RED] CROSS SOURCES TODAY REPORTED THAT A 48-YEAR-OLD WOMAN IDENTIFIED AS MARIA LUZ LOPEZ WAS WOUNDED LAST NIGHT WHEN A POWERFUL BOMB, WHICH DAMAGED SEVERAL BUSINESSES IN [SAN] SALVADOR, EXPLODED.

THE BOMB WAS PLANTED IN A HEAVILY COMMERCIAL AREA OF DOWNTOWN [SAN] SALVADOR CAUSING HEAVY PROPERTY LOSES, ACCORDING TO THE OWNERS WHO PROVIDED NO SPECIFIC FIGURES.

THIS IS THE FOURTH DYNAMITE ATTACK ON BUSINESSES IN [SAN] SALVADOR SO FAR IN 1990.

THE GUERRILLAS INTENSIFIED THEIR ACTS OF SABOTAGE AGAINST THE ECONOMY, ESPECIALLY AGAINST THE ENTIRE ELECTRICAL POWER SYSTEM, ON 2 JANUARY WHEN AN UNILATERAL MILITARY TRUCE THEY DECREED OVER THE CHRISTMAS AND NEW YEAR HOLIDAYS HAD EXPIRED.

TST3-MUC4-0081

LIMA, NO DATE (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [TEXT] [BEGIN RECORDING] [LARCO COX] GOOD EVENING. I HAVE CALLED THIS NEWS CONFERENCE TO READ A FOREIGN MINISTRY COMMUNIQUE: [WORDS INDISTINCT] TODAY THE PANAMANIAN GOVERNMENT TOLD LUIS SANDIGA CABRERA, OUR CHARGE D'AFFAIRES IN PANAMA, THAT HE MUST LEAVE PANAMA IN 72 HOURS.

2. WE HAVE EXPRESSED TO THE PANAMANIAN GOVERNMENT, THROUGH THE PANAMANIAN CHARGE D'AFFAIRES IN LIMA, OUR SURPRISE AND STRONG PROTEST OVER THAT DECISION.

3. IN VIEW OF THIS DECISION, THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT HAS DECIDED TO REDUCE THE PERSONNEL OF ITS DIPLOMATIC MISSION IN PANAMA AND TO MAINTAIN ITS RELATIONS WITH THAT COUNTRY AT THE FIRST SECRETARY LEVEL. PERU WILL IN THIS WAY CONTINUE TO FULFILL THE HUMANITARIAN MISSION OF PROTECTING THOSE WHO HAVE SOUGHT ASYLUM IN ITS EMBASSY IN PANAMA WHILE THE PANAMANIAN GOVERNMENT ISSUES THE SAFE-CONDUCTS THAT WE REQUESTED IN ACCORDANCE TO THE CONVENTION ON DIPLOMATIC ASYLUM SIGNED IN CARACAS ON 28 MARCH 1954.

PERU IS CONTACTING THE MEMBERS OF THE PERMANENT MECHANISM FOR CONSULTATION AND POLITICAL AGREEMENT [GROUP OF EIGHT] TO EXPLAIN THE SITUATION AND TO ASK FOR SOLIDARITY AND COOPERATION IN OVERCOMING THIS MOMENTARY CRISIS.

THE DELICATE SITUATION REGARDING THE PEOPLE AT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY HAS PROVOKED OUR JUSTIFIED ALARM AND IMPELLED US TO BEGIN TALKS TO ENSURE THAT THEIR DIPLOMATIC ASYLUM WILL BE RESPECTED. WE HAVE TALKED WITH THE AMBASSADORS FROM THE COUNTRIES OF THE PERMANENT MECHANISM FOR CONSULTATION AND POLITICAL AGREEMENT. I HAVE PERSONALLY SPOKEN WITH THE AMBASSADORS OF VENEZUELA, MEXICO, AND COLOMBIA.

I AM NOW READY TO ANSWER ANY QUESTIONS:

[REPORTER] MR LARCO COX, UNOFFICIAL SOURCES HAVE SAID THAT THE PEOPLE IN THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY IN PANAMA ARE NOT EXACTLY POLITICAL REFUGEES BUT COMMON CRIMINALS. WHAT DO YOU SAY ABOUT THIS?

[LARCO COX] THE COUNTRY THAT GRANTS ASYLUM DETERMINES THIS. WE HAVE BEEN VERY CAREFUL TO REVIEW EACH ONE OF THEM AND THEIR FILES. WE HAVE CHECKED TO SEE IF ANY OF THEM WERE FACING ANY TRIALS IN PANAMA OR THE UNITED STATES. OUR INVESTIGATION HAS REVEALED THAT NONE OF THEM ARE FACING ANY TRIALS. THE CHARGES WERE MADE AFTERWARD. WE SEE THIS AS A RESULT OF THE EMOTIONAL CLIMATE PRESENTLY EXISTING IN PANAMA.

[REPORTER] WHAT IS YOUR PERSONAL OPINION OF THE INCIDENT?

[LARCO COX] IT IS THE DIPLOMATIC WAY TO EXPRESS A PROTEST OVER WHAT THEY HAVE BEEN LED TO BELIEVE. ACCORDING TO PANAMANIAN REPORTS, CHARGE D'AFFAIRES LUIS SANDIGA HAS MADE STATEMENTS ON THE SITUATION THAT DID NOT PLEASE THE GOVERNMENT. THE TRUTH IS THAT SANDIGA HAS NOT MADE ANY DECLARATIONS. HOWEVER, FORMER AMBASSADOR CASTRO ARENAS IS IN PANAMA AND HE HAS EMBARKED ON A CAMPAIGN IN WHICH HE IS SEEKING RETALIATION AGAINST THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT. HE COULD NOT THINK OF ANYTHING BETTER THAN TO POINT AT SANDIGA AS THE PERSON RESPONSIBLE FOR ALLEGED STATEMENTS. SANDIGA HAS NOT SAID A WORD ABOUT THE SITUATION BECAUSE THAT IS NOT HIS JOB. BESIDES, HIS CAR AND THE CAR BELONGING TO ONE OF THE EMBASSY'S MILITARY ATTACHES HAVE BEEN STOLEN; THERE IS NO WAY TO BEGIN AN INVESTIGATION.

[REPORTER] ARE YOU SAYING THAT FORMER AMBASSADOR CASTRO ARENAS IS DIRECTLY RESPONSIBLE FOR THE SITUATION?

[LARCO COX] YOU CAN MAKE YOUR OWN CONCLUSIONS.

[REPORTER] IF THE SITUATION DETERIORATES, WILL PERU RECALL ALL OF ITS PERSONNEL FROM PANAMA?

[LARCO COX] WE CANNOT GO TO THAT EXTREME BECAUSE WE ARE FULFILLING A HUMANITARIAN CAUSE, AS WE SAID IN THE COMMUNIQUE. OUR FIRST RESPONSIBILITY AT THIS TIME IS TO SEE THAT THE RIGHT OF ASYLUM IS RESPECTED. AS LONG AS THE REFUGEES REMAIN IN THE EMBASSY, WE WILL MAINTAIN OUR REPRESENTATION AT THE LEVEL OF FIRST SECRETARY. [END RECORDING]

TST3-MUC4-0082

BOGOTA, 24 JAN 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE COLOMBIAN LEFTIST ALLIANCE, PATRIOTIC UNION (UP), WAS THE FIRST PARTY TO REGISTER A PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE IN THE UPCOMING 27 MAY ELECTIONS WHEN IT OFFICIALLY REGISTERED BERNARDO JARAMILLO OSSA, 34, AS ITS CANDIDATE TODAY.

PRIOR TO JARAMILLO OSSA'S ARRIVAL AT THE NATIONAL REGISTRY OFFICE, ACCOMPANIED BY 12 BODYGUARDS, EXPLOSIVES EXPERTS FROM THE SECRET POLICE DEPARTMENT CHECKED THE BUILDING AND CORDONED OFF THE ENTRANCE HE WAS GOING TO USE.

UP WAS FOUNDED IN 1985 AND HAS LOST ALMOST 1,000 MEMBERS AND REGIONAL LEADERS IN VIOLENT ATTACKS. IT HAS ALSO LOST MOST OF ITS REPRESENTATIVES IN BOGOTA, INCLUDING JAIME PARDO LEAL, THE PARTY FOUNDER AND A PREVIOUS PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE WHO WAS MURDERED IN 1987.

COLOMBIAN COMMUNIST PARTY PRESIDENT GILBERTO VIEIRA AND THE ENTIRE UP DIRECTORATE ATTENDED BERNARDO JARAMILLO'S REGISTRATION.

LAST WEEK, THE STATE COUNCIL, COLOMBIA'S HIGHEST LEGAL AND ADMINISTRATIVE BODY, HAD ACCREDITED BERNARDO JARAMILLO AS UP'S PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE.

BEFORE MAKING HIS CANDIDACY EFFECTIVE, BERNARDO JARAMILLO TOLD EFE THAT HE WOULD ATTEMPT TO BECOME "THE WILL OF A WIDE AND DEMOCRATIC SECTOR OF THE PEOPLE AND AN ALTERNATIVE TO TRADITIONAL COLOMBIAN BIPARTISANSHIP." HE ADDED: "OUR MOVEMENT WANTS TO TRANSCEND THE LIMITS OF THE UP AND OBTAIN FOLLOWERS FROM OTHER SECTORS OF THE DEMOCRATIC LEFT WHO SUPPORT NEW GOVERNMENT ALTERNATIVES."

HE DID NOT REJECT THE POSSIBILITY THAT UP AND THE 19TH APRIL MOVEMENT (M-19), A REBEL MOVEMENT THAT IS MAKING EFFORTS TO JOIN THE COUNTRY'S LEGAL POLITICAL SYSTEM, WILL PRESENT JOINT ELECTORAL TICKETS IN SOME REGIONS IN THE COUNTRY.

"THERE IS NOTHING CONCRETE ON THIS," HE ADDED, "BUT IT COULD BE AN ALTERNATIVE IF THEY PROPOSE IT."

UP PRESIDENT DIEGO MONTANA STATED THAT "OUR PARTY'S MAIN OBJECTIVE IN THESE ELECTIONS IS TO BREAK THE LIBERAL AND SOCIAL CONSERVATIVE HEGEMONY." THESE TWO SECTORS HAVE SHARED POWER DURING COLOMBIA'S ENTIRE REPUBLICAN PERIOD.

"WE PRESENT OUR CANDIDATE TO OTHER POLITICAL MOVEMENTS WITH THE HOPE THAT HIS CANDIDACY WILL BE BACKED AND THAT WE CAN CREATE A NEW AND WIDER FORCE WITH POSSIBILITIES OF ATTAINING VICTORY," HE NOTED.

JARAMILLO'S CAMPAIGN SLOGAN, "COUNTRYMEN, GIVE ME YOUR HAND" APPEARED IN POSTERS THROUGHOUT BOGOTA TODAY.

AFTER REGISTERING, BERNARDO JARAMILLO ATTENDED THE FUNERAL OF A FELLOW PARTY MEMBER, VLADIMIR ESCOBAR, A SOACHA MUNICIPAL OFFICIAL WHO WAS SHOT BETWEEN THE EYES AND KILLED THIS WEEK. THE SOACHA MUNICIPALITY IS CLOSE TO BOGOTA.

TST3-MUC4-0083

CLANDESTINE, 31 JAN 90 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] [TEXT] CONCERNING THE PROSPECTS FOR THE DIALOGUE - NEGOTIATION BASED ON THE MEDIATION OF UN SECRETARY GENERAL JAVIER PEREZ DE CUELLAR AND THE DEBATE IN THE U.S. CONGRESS ON THE AID TO EL SALVADOR, THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] REPORTS:

1. WE HAVE VIEWED WITH GREAT CONCERN THE GOVERNMENT AND ARMY'S REJECTION MR PEREZ DE CUELLAR'S PARTICIPATION IN THE DIALOGUE - NEGOTIATION PROCESS AS A MEDIATOR. THIS ATTITUDE IS AN OBSTACLE TO A PROCESS THAT COULD FACILITATE THE NEGOTIATION EFFORT. ON OUR PART, WE HAVE ACCEPTED THIS MEDIATION AND WE HAVE UNDERTAKEN EFFORTS TO ACHIEVE IT.

2. THE STATE OF SIEGE, THE ASSASSINATION OF SOCIAL DEMOCRATIC LEADER HECTOR OQUELI, THE DOUBTFUL AND INSUFFICIENT INITIAL RESULTS IN THE CASE OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS, THE ABSENCE OF CONDITIONS FOR THE POLITICAL ACTIVITY OF THE OPPOSITION, THE CONTINUATION OF THE PERSECUTION OF CHURCHES, AND THE LACK OF FREEDOM OF SPEECH THROUGH THE DIRECT OR COVERT GAGGING OF THE PRESS SHOW THAT CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT IS CARRYING OUT A POLICY OF CONFRONTATION WITH ALL THE COUNTRY'S SOCIAL AND POLITICAL FORCES. FOR THIS REASON, THE TERMS OF THE DIALOGUE - NEGOTIATION MUST BE REORIENTED SO THAT IT WILL BE TURNED INTO A NATIONAL PROCESS WITH THE PARTICIPATION OF ALL THOSE FORCES.

3. WE VIEW AS GRAVELY ERRONEOUS THE PERSISTENCE OF A GOVERNMENT POLICY BASED ON THE IDEA OF THE FMLN'S ALLEGED MILITARY WEAKNESS. THIS POSITION, SIMILAR TO THE ONE THAT WAS PUT FORTH PRIOR TO 11 NOVEMBER [DATE OF THE BEGINNING OF THE FMLN MILITARY OFFENSIVE] WILL ONLY LEAD THE COUNTRY TO GREATER LEVELS OF CONFRONTATION.

4. WE REAFFIRM OUR WILLINGNESS TO HOLD THE MEETING OF BOTH SIDES WITH THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL SOON. WE HOPE THAT MR CRISTIANI'S VISIT TO THE UNITED NATIONS WILL LEAD TO SUCH A MEETING AND THAT WE CAN AGREE WITH THE MEDIATOR ON THE DATE TO HOLD IT.

5. WE BELIEVE THAT THE U.S. AID TO THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IS DIRECTED AGAINST DEMOCRATIZATION AND A POLITICAL SOLUTION. THE SENDING OF SIGNALS TO ONE OR ANOTHER SECTOR OF THE GOVERNMENT OR ARMY, USING THE PRESSURE OF SETTING CONDITIONS OR THREATENING THE END OF AID, DOES NOT RESOLVE THE PROBLEM. WE BELIEVE THE MEMBERS OF THE U.S. CONGRESS CAN MAKE AN IMPORTANT CONTRIBUTION TO END THE WAR IN OUR COUNTRY BY AGREEING TO SUSPEND THAT AID, SOMETHING WHICH COULD FORM PART OF A NEGOTIATED AGREEMENT THAT WOULD SIMULTANEOUSLY ENTAIL A CEASE-FIRE.

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND

COMMANDERS SALVADOR SANCHEZ CEREN, SHAFIK JORGE HANDAL, FRANCISCO JOVEL, EDUARDO SANCHO, JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS

30 JANUARY 1990

TST3-MUC4-0085

HAVANA (CUBA), 10 FEB 90 (INTERNATIONAL SERVICE) -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] SMARTLY DRESSED AND SPEAKING IN NEARLY PERFECT ENGLISH, SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI HAS AGAIN VISITED THE UNITED STATES, WHERE HE TRIED TO APPEAR AT THE CONGRESS AND THE UNITED NATIONS AS A STATESMAN AWARE OF HIS RIGHTS.

THIS IS, HOWEVER, A CRITICAL MOMENT FOR THE SALVADORAN PRESIDENT, AND HE KNOWS IT. BUT THIS POINT WAS ALSO STRESSED BY THE LARGE NUMBERS OF PEOPLE WHO BOOED HIM AT NEARLY EVERY LARGE U.S. CITY HE VISITED. ALTHOUGH THE GHOSTS OF THE ASSASSINATED JESUITS SHADOWED HIM ALL DURING HIS TOUR, THE ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] REPRESENTATIVE, JUST AS HIS PREDECESSOR JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE DID, FLEW TO THE UNITED STATES TO TRY TO CONVINCE THE LEGISLATORS, PARTICULARLY THE DEMOCRATS, THAT HE INTENDS TO RESUME THE DIALOGUE FOR PEACE AND CHECK THE ARMY'S CRIMINAL ASPIRATIONS. WAVING THE HUMAN RIGHTS FLAG HAS BEEN THE MOST IMPORTANT THING FOR CRISTIANI, PARTICULARLY BECAUSE HE IS AWARE THAT WITH THIS ACTION HE CAN CONTINUE TO RECEIVE WASHINGTON'S FINANCIAL SUPPORT FOR HIS GOVERNMENT.

ACCORDING TO TO SOME EXPERTS, CRISTIANI WENT FARTHER THAN HIS PREDECESSOR. HE ASKED THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL TO HELP IN THE RESUMPTION OF TALKS WITH THE GUERRILLAS, REPLACED SEVERAL MILITARY OFFICERS OF DOUBTFUL REPUTATION, AND ASSURED HE WILL PUNISH SEVERELY EIGHT SOLDIERS ACCUSED OF ASSASSINATING THE SIX JESUIT PRIESTS. WE MUST KEEP IN MIND THAT, PRIOR TO HIS TRIP, THE SALVADORAN PRESIDENT SUCCEEDED IN CURBING A COUP ATTEMPT STAGED BY ARMY REACTIONARY GROUPS. MEMBERS OF THE SALVADORAN OPPOSITION HAVE COINCIDED IN THER VIEW THAT NEVER BEFORE HAD A HEAD OF STATE CHALLENGED THE MILITARY HIERARCHY TO SUCH AN EXTENT, A HIERARCHY THAT OPPOSES ALL NEGOTIATION WITH THE GUERRILLAS. THE EXPERTS ALSO SAID, HOWEVER, THAT THE COUNTRY'S INTERNAL SITUATION HAS NEVER BEEN SO SERIOUS.

THE REBEL OFFENSIVE LAUNCHED IN NOVEMBER IS A LANDMARK, AFTER WHICH EVERYTHING WILL BE DIFFERENT IN EL SALVADOR, BEGINNING WITH THE GOVERNMENT PARTY, WHICH WAS LEFT IN A VERY DELICATE SITUATION IN THE EYES OF INFLUENTIAL U.S. POWER CIRCLES. THE GUERRILLA DRIVE ALSO DEMONSTRATED THAT ONLY TWO ALTERNATIVES ARE LEFT FOR THE COUNTRY. IF SERIOUS PEACE NEGOTIATIONS ARE NOT INITIATED, THE COUNTERINSURGENCY POLICY WILL BE AGGRAVATED. THIS COULD EVEN GIVE THE UNITED STATES A PRETEXT TO INTERVENE DIRECTLY IN THE COUNTRY.

ALTHOUGH PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH SAID HE WOULD CONTINUE TO AID EL SALVADOR, A LARGE NUMBER OF LEGISLATORS FOR A LONG TIME HAVE BEEN QUESTIONING WHAT USE HAS BEEN NEARLY $4 BILLION DELIVERED TO THE SALVADORAN ARMY IN 10 YEARS OF WAR. IF FOR THE WHITE HOUSE THE ALTERNATIVE IS TO CONTINUE TO GIVE MILITARY AID TO EL SALVADOR OR RESIGN ITSELF TO AN EVENTUAL VICTORY OF THE REBELS, FOR CRISTIANI THE SITUATION IS EVEN MORE DIFFICULT BECAUSE, TO GET MORE MONEY, HE MUST ENSURE THAT HUMAN RIGHTS ARE RESPECTED. THIS IS EQUIVALENT TO INFLUENCING THE MOST REACTIONARY MILITARY OFFICERS AND GUARANTEEING THE FULFILLMENT OF THE FAMOUS ECONOMIC RECOVERY PLAN ADVOCATED BY HIS PARTY. THESE POINTS ARE NEARLY IMPOSSIBLE TO COMPLY WITH IN A COUNTRY IMMERSED IN WAR. IF THE ECONOMY IS WEAK, RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS IS EVEN WEAKER. ANYWAY, THE U.S. GOVERNMENT IS PLANNING TO INCREASE AID FOR THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT. THIS CONTRIBUTES TO PUTTING FAR INTO THE DISTANCE ANY PLANS TO END THE WAR.

TST3-MUC4-0086

NO CITY, NO DATE (PARIS AFP) -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] "WHILE FARC COMPLIED AND CONTINUES TO COMPLY WITH THE UNILATERAL CEASE-FIRE, THE ARMY HAS BEEN CONDUCTING MILITARY OFFENSIVES AGAINST SEVERAL FARC FRONTS, SUCH AS 1, 5, 10, 26, 38, 24, 18, 11, 23, 19, 41, 46, AND OTHERS.

"FARC, HOWEVER, PERSISTS IN ITS EFFORT TO COMPLY WITH ITS PLEDGED WORD, NATURALLY WITHOUT RELINQUISHING ITS LEGITIMATE DEFENSE WHEN IT COMES TO MILITARY OPERATIONS," THE LETTER TO THE NOTABLES ADDED.

"OUR SAYING THAT THROUGH YOU WE ARE PROPOSING TO THE GOVERNMENT A CEASE-FIRE SO THE MARCH LEGISLATIVE ELECTIONS AND THE MAY PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS CAN BE HELD IN A CLIMATE OF PEACE AND DEMOCRATIC GUARANTEES DOES NOT CHANGE OUR PREVIOUS STAND REGARDING OUR UNILATERAL CEASE-FIRE.

"WE ARE NOW PROPOSING THAT THIS CEASE-FIRE BE GENERAL DURING THE ELECTIONS AND THAT THE EMINENT ADDRESSEES OF THE LETTER BECOME SUPERVISORS OF WHAT COULD BE A NEW PROCESS OF RECONCILIATION AND PEACE IN THE COLOMBIAN FAMILY," THE LETTER STATED.

THE REBEL LEADERS SAID THAT, BECAUSE NEW DISAGREEMENTS AND CONFLICTS HAVE APPEARED IN THE MIDST OF A CRISIS NEVER BEFORE HEARD OF IN THE COUNTRY, "WE ARE INSISTING ON THIS GENERAL CEASE-FIRE PROPOSAL."

THE LETTER SAID FURTHER: "BECAUSE, FAR FROM DIMINISHING, CRIMES AGAINST PUBLIC ORDER, SUCH AS ABDUCTIONS, EXTORTION, AND THREATS, NOT ONLY HAVE INCREASED IN THE PAST FEW MONTHS BUT PREVAIL IN VARIOUS AREAS OF COLOMBIA, WE COULD HARDLY ASK THE ARMED FORCES TO STOP THEIR FUNCTIONS OF PROTECTING THE LIVES AND PROPERTIES OF THE PEOPLE.

"WE THINK IT IS NECESSARY TO CLARIFY THAT THERE IS A DIFFERENCE BETWEEN THE POLICE CASES AND THOSE OF PUBLIC ORDER THAT ARE THE RESPONSIBILITY OF THE ARMED FORCES, ACCORDING TO THE CONSTITUTION. SIMILARLY, WE MUST CLARIFY THAT KIDNAPPINGS, EXTORTION, AND THREATS ARE NOT PART OF THE POLICY OF THE FARC STAFF.

"WE ARE HEREBY PROPOSING TO THE EMINENT SUPERVISORS TO JOIN US IN THE SEARCH FOR WAYS LEADING TO PEACE AND INDEPENDENT PROGRESS IN THE COUNTRY.

"FARC STAFF, IN THE MOUNTAINS OF COLOMBIA. MANUEL MARULANDA, ALIAS "TIROFIJO," JACOBO ARENAS, ALFONSO CANO, RAUL REYES, AND TIMOLEON JIMENEZ."

TST3-MUC4-0087

TEGUCIGALPA, 22 FEB 90 (SAN PEDRO SULA TIEMPO) -- [TEXT] CONTRA COMMANDER ISRAEL GALEANO, ALIAS FRANKLIN, HAS TOLD TIEMPO THAT THE ANTI-SANDINIST REBELS WILL STAY ARMED, REGARDLESS OF THE RESULTS OF THE 25 FEBRUARY ELECTIONS IN NICARAGUA, TO MAKE SURE THE DEMOCRATIC CHANGES TAKE PLACE.

"WE WILL MAINTAIN OUR ORGANIZATION INTACT EVEN IF THE UNO [NATIONAL OPPOSITION UNION] WINS, WAITING FOR PROFOUND DEMOCRATIC CHANGES AND AN END TO THE REPRESSIVE REGIME IMPOSED BY THE SANDINISTS," SAID THE CHIEF OF STAFF OF THE NICARAGUAN RESISTANCE (RN).

THIS PAST JANUARY, THE 29-YEAR-OLD GALEANO BECAME THE LEADER OF ABOUT 12,000 NICARAGUAN RIGHTIST REBELS BASED IN HONDURAS WHEN THE POST OF COMMANDER IN CHIEF OF THE RN ARMY, A POST ENRIQUE BERMUDEZ HAD HELD FOR 10 YEARS, WAS ELIMINATED.

NICARAGUA WILL HOLD ELECTIONS ON SUNDAY, 25 FEBRUARY, AND THE MAIN CANDIDATES RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT ARE DANIEL ORTEGA OF THE SANDINIST NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FSLN) AND VIOLETA DE CHAMORRO OF THE UNO.

THE REBELS, SUPPORTED BY THE UNITED STATES, HAVE URGED NICARAGUANS TO VOTE FOR THE UNO CANDIDATE.

"IF THE UNO WINS, WE WILL MAINTAIN OUR ORGANIZATION INTACT TO SEE IF ON 25 APRIL THERE IS A TOTAL TRANSFER OF POWER AND PROFOUND REFORMS, AND PARTICULARLY TO SEE IF THE REPRESSIVE SYSTEM DISAPPEARS," GALEANO SAID.

"IF THE SANDINISTS WIN OR STEAL THE ELECTIONS, THERE WILL BE A SOCIAL DISRUPTION AGAINST THE SYSTEM AND THE HARDEST STRUGGLE OF RECENT YEARS WILL TAKE PLACE," HE ADDED.

THE CONTRA MILITARY CHIEF SAID THAT "IF THE PEOPLE DO NOT ACCEPT A SANDINIST VICTORY, "WE WILL HAVE TO CONTINUE FIGHTING."

HE ASSURED THAT THE NICARAGUANS WILL NOT ACCEPT AN FSLN VICTORY IN THE 25 FEBRUARY ELECTIONS.

GALEANO ADDED THAT THE SANDINISTS HAVE DEPLOYED APPROXIMATELY 30,000 TROOPS IN THE NORTHERN NICARAGUAN DEPARTMENTS IN ORDER TO "INTIMIDATE AND MURDER" UNO FOLLOWERS AND TO PREVENT APPROXIMATELY 300,000 NICARAGUANS FROM VOTING.

GALEANO POINTED OUT THAT THE PRESS AND THE FOREIGN OBSERVERS OF THE ELECTIONS HAVE NO ACCESS TO THE AREAS WHERE THE NICARAGUAN TROOPS HAVE DEPLOYED.

"EVEN THOUGH THE FOREIGN OBSERVERS CLAIM THAT THE CAMPAIGN WAS FREELY HELD, THE PEOPLE HAVE HAD TO MAKE SACRIFICES," HE SAID.

GALEANO SAID THAT ABOUT 5,000 OF HIS MEN ARE INSIDE NICARAGUA, AND BETWEEN 10,000 TO 12,000 MEN ARE IN BASES IN HONDURAS, "NOT MOVING, BUT JUST OBSERVING THE ELECTORAL PROCESS" IN NICARAGUA.

THE REBELS IN HONDURAS ARE RECEIVING U.S. HUMANITARIAN AID IN EL PARAISO DEPARTMENT AND HAVE REJECTED A DEMOBILIZATION PLAN APPROVED BY THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS. THE REBELS CLAIM THEY DO NOT HAVE ANY GUARANTEES FOR THEIR PERSONAL SECURITY AND FOR THE IMPLEMENTATION OF A DEMOCRATIC PROCESS.

"THE DEMOBILIZATION IS BASED ON THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT CREATING CONDITIONS THAT WILL ENCOURAGE THE MEMBERS OF THE ARMED RN TO JOIN CIVIC LIFE," HE ADDED.

GALEANO SAID THAT THE DISMANTLING OF HIS FORCES DOES NOT "DEPEND OF A SIMPLE ELECTIONS," BUT RATHER ON "THE SANDINISTS LEAVING POWER COMPLETELY."

THE CONTRA LEADER WARNED THAT "WE CANNOT LAY DOWN OUR WEAPONS WHEN THE CAUSES THAT LED TO OUR TAKING UP ARMS HAVE NOT DISAPPEARED. THERE STILL IS REPRESSION, A LACK OF FREEDOM, AND ALL OF THIS WAS GENERATED BY THE SANDINISTS."

HE POINTED OUT THAT IN THE EVENT THE UNO SHOULD WIN THE 25 FEBRUARY ELECTIONS, "WE WOULD HAVE TO CARRY OUT A MUTUAL DEMOBILIZATION. THE NICARAGUAN PROBLEM CAN BE SOLVED WITH AN INTER-AMERICAN PEACE FORCE THAT WILL RECEIVE ALL THE WEAPONRY AND SOVIET TANKS OF THE SANDINISTS. THEN, WHEN WE ARE AT AN EVEN LEVEL OF FORCES, WE WILL TURN OVER OUR OWN WEAPONS."

THE CONTRA CHIEF SUGGESTED A NATIONAL POLICE BE CREATED IN NICARAGUA.

FRANKLIN SAID THAT THE CONTRAS ARE WILLING TO CONTINUE THE PEACE TALKS, BUT PERHAPS AFTER THE ELECTIONS, WITH THE NEW NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT.

HE ASSURED THAT THE REBEL FORCES WILL NOT CARRY OUT "ANY OFFENSIVE OPERATIONS BEFORE, DURING, OR AFTER THE ELECTIONS, AND WILL WAIT AND SEE IF THERE ARE CHANGES IN NICARAGUA."

HE SAID THAT THE CONTRAS ARE WILLING TO LEAVE THEIR CAMPS IN YAMALES IF REQUESTED BY THE GOVERNMENT OF RAFAEL LEONARDO CALLEJAS.

"IF POLITICAL CONDITIONS DO NOT ALLOW US TO REMAIN, WE WILL LEAVE (FOR NICARAGUA), BUT OUR REFUGEEES WILL STAY, AS REFUGEES," HE ADDED.

THE CHIEF OF STAFF OF THE CONTRAS SAID THAT HIS FORCES WILL NOT ATTACK THE UN PEACE OBSERVERS IN THE HONDURAN-NICARAGUAN BORDER AREA.

HE SAID THAT RN RELATIONS WITH THE UNITED STATES ARE NORMAL, BUT DECLINED TO COMMENT ON THE OUSTING OF BERMUDEZ, ARGUING THAT THIS IS A FAIT ACCOMPLI.

TST3-MUC4-0088

BOGOTA, 24 FEB 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] CALM APPEARS TO BE RETURNING TO THE COUNTRY FOLLOWING THE DEATH OF ONE NONCOMMISSIONED OFFICER AND SIX SOLDIERS ON 23 FEBRUARY AS A RESULT OF GUERRILLA ATTACKS IN FIVE ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT MUNICIPALITIES, THE KIDNAPPING OF A MAYOR, A GOVERNMENT OFFICIAL, AND A CANDIDATE IN CAUCA DEPARTMENT, AND THE DEATH OF A GUERRILLA IN GUAVIARE.

THE GUERRILLA ACTIONS BEGAN ON THE EVENING OF 22 FEBRUARY WHEN A LARGE COLUMN OF THE POPULAR LIBERATION ARMY [ELN] ENTERED TURBO MUNICIPALITY, NORTHEAST OF ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT, AND SABOTAGED THE POWER SYSTEM LEAVING THE ENTIRE AREA WITHOUT ELECTRICITY. NATIONAL ARMY SPOKESMEN SAID THAT ONE NONCOMMISSIONED OFFICER AND SIX SOLDIERS WERE KILLED, FOUR WERE WOUNDED, AND 15 OTHERS WERE KIDNAPPED DURING THE ATTACKS AGAINST MILITARY BASES AND POLICE INSTALLATIONS IN SEGOVIA BY THE 4TH FRONT OF THE FARC [REVOLUTIONARY ARMED FORCES OF COLOMBIA].

MEANWHILE IN BOGOTA, MILITARY FORCES COMMANDER NELSON MEJIA HENAO DENIED THAT COLOMBIA IS IN GUERRILLA HANDS AND REAFFIRMED THE TROOPS' UNYIELDING DETERMINATION TO DEFEND NATIONAL ORDER AND DEMOCRACY. THE HIGHEST-RANKING OFFICER, WHO EXPRESSED REGRET OVER THE DEATHS OF THE SOLDIERS IN SEGOVIA, ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT, SAID THAT THIS TYPE OF INCIDENT IS NORMAL WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF THE WAR THAT THE GOVERNMENT IS WAGING AGAINST ARMED SUBVERSION.

LAST NIGHT, PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO VARGAS, AFTER THE CLOSING CEREMONY OF THE 25TH AGRARIAN CONGRESS OF THE (FAC) [EXPANSION UNKNOWN], SAID THAT THE GUERRILLAS ARE DESPERATE AND THIS IS REFLECTED IN THEIR ACTIONS. NEVERTHELESS, THE ARMED FORCES WILL CONTINUE TO FIGHT SUBVERSION ANYWHERE IN THE COUNTRY, HE ADDED. THE PRESIDENT EXPRESSED HIS SATISFACTION AT THE RELEASE OF SANTANDER DEPARTMENT SENATOR JORGE SERRANO GONZALEZ, WHOM HE DESCRIBED AS ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT PEOPLE THAT COLOMBIAN DEMOCRACY HAS AT THIS MOMENT. HE ADDED FINALLY: I HOPE THAT IS HE ALREADY AT HOME WITH HIS FAMILY.

TST3-MUC4-0089

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY MODERATOR AND REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [CRISTIANI] THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT MAINTAINS ITS STANCE REGARDING THE DIALOGUE PROCESS AND ITS RESUMPTION. WE BELIEVE IT CONSTITUTES THE MOST EXPEDIENT WAY TO ACHIEVE PEACE IN THE COUNTRY, AND WE ARE GOING TO CONTINUE ALONG THAT PATH.

[MODERATOR] AIDA MONTALVO.

[MONTALVO] IN REGARD TO THE RENEGOTIATION OF THE FOREIGN DEBT, WHEN ARE YOU PLANNING TO GO TO MEXICO, AND HOW WILL THE SALVADORAN DEBT WITH THAT COUNTRY BE RENEGOTIATED?

[CRISTIANI] THE TIMETABLE FOR THE TRIP IS STILL UNDECIDED. THERE IS NOT DEFINITE DATE. I THINK IT MAY TAKE PLACE IN APRIL OR MAY OF THIS YEAR. OUR FIRST SCHEDULED VISIT WILL BE TO VENEZUELA.

[MODERATOR] CARLOS MARIO MARQUEZ OF AGENCE FRANCE PRESSE.

[MARQUEZ] [WORDS INDISTINCT] SOCIAL ASPECTS. I WOULD LIKE TO KNOW WHAT THE STATUS IS OF THAT, SINCE SOME SUPPORT HAVING PRIMARY MEETINGS AND THEN A SUMMIT, SO TO SPEAK?

[CRISTIANI] I DO NOT THINK THAT IS THE CAUSE OF THAT PROBLEM. WE SAID THAT THE RESUMPTION OF THE TALKS MUST TAKE PLACE WHEN THE FMLN ENTERS THE DIALOGUE PROCESS WITH A SERIOUS ATTITUDE. WE MAINTAIN OUR STANCE THAT THEY MUST STOP ALL VIOLENCE THAT IS DIRECTLY AND INDIRECTLY AFFECTING CIVILIANS, THAT IS, ALL THE TERRORIST ACTIVITIES THE FMLN CONDUCTS. THIS IS A SMALL REQUEST THAT OBTAINED THE SUPPORT OF ALL THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS AT THE SAN ISIDRO CORONADO MEETING IN COSTA RICA.

I THINK THAT THIS IS THE CAUSE OF THE PROBLEM. THEY HAVE ASKED FOR CHANGES IN FORMAT, AND WE SAID WE HAD NO PROBLEM WITH MOST OF THE REQUESTS WE HAVE RECEIVED. WE ARE NOW WAITING FOR THE FMLN, SINCE THEY ASKED FOR TIME TO ANALYZE THINGS A LITTLE BEFORE HAVING THE MEETING. WE ARE AWAITING THE VISIT OF MR. DE SOTO IN EARLY MARCH. OBVIOUSLY, THE DIALOGUE HAS NOT TAKEN PLACE BECAUSE THERE ARE SOME DIFFERENCES, [WORDS INDISTINCT]. I THINK THE CHIEF DIFFERENCE IS THAT THE FMLN DOES NOT WANT TO AGREE TO STOP TERRORIST ACTIONS, AND THAT IS WHY THERE IS NO DIALOGUE NOW.

[MODERATOR] EPIGMENIO IBARRA.

[IBARRA] MR. PRESIDENT, YESTERDAY IN NICARAGUA, DANIEL ORTEGA SAID AT A RALLY THAT HE WILL WAGE A CONSTRUCTIVE OPPOSITION. HE SAID THAT THE REVOLUTION DID NOT DIE WITH THE ELECTIONS. HE SAID THAT THE SANDINIST NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FSLN] WILL RULE FROM BELOW. WE SENSE A PRETTY COMPLEX CLIMATE FOR THE TRANSITION IN NICARAGUA. WHAT DO YOU THINK ABOUT DANIEL ORTEGA'S STATEMENTS? HOW DO YOU VIEW THE POSSIBILITY THAT THERE MAY BE A TRUE TRANSITION FROM POWER TO POWER INSTEAD OF A TRANSITION OF GOVERNMENT IN NICARAGUA?

[CRISTIANI] AS I HAVE SAID BEFORE, STATEMENTS BY ORTEGA AND OTHER REPRESENTATIVES OF THE SANDINIST FRONT ARE A SOURCE OF CONCERN. THEY COULD INDICATE THAT THE ELECTIONS MAY HAVE BEEN VERY FREE AND HONEST, BUT ALSO A FARCE AS FAR AS IMPROVING THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS IS CONCERNED. THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE WOULD BE DENIED THE RIGHT TO FREELY PICK THEIR RULERS AND THE RIGHT OF THESE RULERS TO ACT AS THEY DEEM BEST. I WOULD SAY THAT THE NICARAGUAN REVOLUTION BELONGS NOT JUST TO THE FSLN. THE FSLN WAS ONE OF THE PARTICIPANTS IN THE REVOLUTION IN NICARAGUA AGAINST ANASTASIO SOMOZA. THE FACT IS THAT A CONSENSUS EXISTED AMONG ALL SECTORS THAT SUPPORTED THAT REVOLUTION. THE FSLN HAS NO MONOPOLY ON OR EXCLUSIVE CONTROL OVER THAT REVOLUTION.

I BELIEVE THAT IN IDEOLOGICAL TERMS THERE ARE DIFFERENCES BETWEEN THE VIEWS OF MS. CHAMORRO AND UNO [NATIONAL OPPOSITION UNION], THAT IS, THE NEW GOVERNMENT-ELECT, AND THE VIEWS OF THE FSLN. YET, THE PEOPLE PICKED THE GOVERNMENT. IT IS WORRISOME TO HEAR SOME STATEMENTS THAT THE FSLN WILL RULE FROM BELOW. WE BELIEVE THEY WOULD SEEK TO DO THAT BY KEEPING CONTROL OVER THE ARMY. LET ME REPEAT: THERE IS NOTHING DEMOCRATIC ABOUT A POLITICAL PARTY CONTROLLING THE ARMY. THE ARMY MUST RESPOND TO THE GOVERNMENT AND THE COUNTRY'S DEMOCRATIC PROCESS, AND NOT TO JUST ONE POLITICAL PARTY. WE BELIEVE THINGS HAVE NOT BEEN SETTLED YET. WE BELIEVE THAT THERE ARE STILL MANY THINGS LEFT PENDING. [CONTINUED]

TST3-MUC4-0090

GUATEMALA CITY, 6 MAR 90 (TELEONCE TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THE EMBASSY COMMUNIQUE POINTS OUT THAT THE UNITED STATES DID NOT SUBMIT EITHER ONE OF THE TWO HUMAN RIGHTS RESOLUTIONS ON GUATEMALA THAT ARE CURRENTLY UNDER DISCUSSION IN GENEVA. ACCORDING TO THE OBSERVERS, THIS CLARIFICATION CAME IN REPLY TO STATEMENTS MADE BY CEREZO THAT THE U.S. POSITION IN THIS REGARD DIFFERS FROM THAT OF MOST COUNTRIES WITHIN THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CEREZO] ALL THESE ACTIONS [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE UNITED STATES POINTING THE FINGER TO HUMAN RIGHTS ISSUES ARE AIMED AT [WORD INDISTINCT] IN GENEVA, BECAUSE I HAVE THE IMPRESSION THAT WHAT IT WANTS AT THIS TIME IS TO HAVE GUATEMALA CONDEMNED AND TO A CERTAIN EXTENT TARNISH OUR INTERNATIONAL IMAGE, BECAUSE THE SUCCESS OF THE ESQUIPULAS II PLAN GAVE GUATEMALA, AS AN AUTONOMOUS AND INDEPENDENT COUNTRY, A LOT OF ROOM FOR ACTION.

THAT IS WHAT IT WANTS TO DO, BECAUSE IT IS NOT GOOD FOR LARGE COUNTRIES TO SEE COUNTRIES LIKE GUATEMALA, WITH A CERTAIN DEGREE OF AUTONOMY AND INDEPENDENCE, ACHIEVE HISTORIC SUCCESSES BY SHOWING THAT OUR COUNTRY IS RIGHT IN DISCUSSIONS WITH CERTAIN U.S. GROUPS. THEY NOW WANT [WORDS INDISTINCT]. MY PERSONAL OPINION IS THAT THEY NOW SORT OF WANT TO GET BACK AT US FOR THE ESQUIPULAS II PLAN. [END RECORDING]

IN REPLY TO THESE STATEMENTS BY PRESIDENT CEREZO, THE U.S. EMBASSY POINTED OUT IN ITS COMMUNIQUE OF 6 MARCH THAT THE U.S. GOVERNMENT HAD SUPPORTED THE ESQUIPULAS II PEACE PROCESS FROM THE VERY BEGINNING. IT ADDED THAT EVER SINCE THE SIGNING OF THE ESQUIPULAS ACCORD, GUATEMALA HAS RECEIVED $600 MILLION IN U.S. AID. THIS SHOWS, ACCORDING TO THE EMBASSY, THAT U.S. SUPPORT FOR GUATEMALAN DEMOCRACY CONTINUED TO BE STRONG AFTER THE SIGNING OF THE ESQUIPULAS II DOCUMENT.

IN ANY CASE, FROM PRESIDENT CEREZO'S PERSPECTIVE THE U.S. ATTITUDE IN THIS SITUATION REFLECTS THE TRADITIONAL INCLINATION OF THAT COUNTRY'S GOVERNMENTS THROUGHOUT HISTORY TO DICTATE RULES TO OTHER NATIONS REGARDING WHAT THEY SHOULD DO. CEREZO COMPARED GUATEMALA'S SITUATION IN MATTERS OF CRIMINAL INVESTIGATION TO THE SITUATION IN SEVERAL U.S. CITIES WHERE THE POLICE ARE UNABLE TO CONTROL CRIME. AS AN EXAMPLE, HE CITED WASHINGTON, D.C., WHERE ASSAULTS, MURDERS, AND CRIMES FREQUENTLY RELATED TO DRUG CONSUMPTION HAVE REACHED VERY ASTONISHING LEVELS IN THE PAST FEW YEARS.

AS FOR THE DEPARTURE OF AMBASSADOR STROOK, CEREZO SAID THAT THE DIPLOMAT HAS NOT BEEN WITHDRAWN FROM GUATEMALA, BUT RETURNED TO THE UNITED STATES FOR CONSULTATIONS BY ORDER OF THE STATE DEPARTMENT. IN STATEMENTS MADE MINUTES AFTER RECEIVING THE CREDENTIALS OF THE NEW FRG AMBASSADOR, HOWEVER, CEREZO SAID THAT HIS RETURN WAS, TO A CERTAIN EXTENT, DUE TO A DECISION WE MADE.

TST3-MUC4-0091

SANTIAGO, 21 MAR 90 (RADIO CHILENA NETWORK) -- [EXCERPTS] GENERAL GUSTAVO LEIGH GUZMAN, A FORMER MILITARY REGIME GOVERNMENT JUNTA MEMBER AND FORMER COMMANDER IN CHIEF OF THE AIR FORCE, AND AIR FORCE GENERAL ENRIQUE RUIZ, RETIRED, A PARTNER IN LEIGH'S REAL ESTATE OFFICE, WERE SERIOUSLY INJURED DURING AN ATTACK THIS MORNING.

ACCORDING TO WITNESSES' REPORTS, TWO 23 TO 25-YEAR-OLD INDIVIDUALS WALKED TO GEN. LEIGH'S OFFICE, ON THE FOURTH FLOOR OF THE BUILDING LOCATED AT 95 LUIS TALLE OJEDA STREET. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

WITNESSES SAID THEY HEARD TWO BURSTS OF GUNFIRE: ONE BURST OF THREE SHOTS LASTING THREE SECONDS AND ANOTHER BURST OF SEVEN TO EIGHT SHOTS LASTING LONGER. GEN. LEIGH'S SECRETARY, JOANNA SANTIS RETAMAL, CAME TO A WINDOW TO REPORT THE INCIDENT.

OTHER REPORTS SAID THAT THE TWO INDIVIDUALS BROKE INTO THE OFFICES AND ENTERED GEN. LEIGH'S PRIVATE OFFICE. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

THE INDIVIDUALS USED 9 MM SEMIAUTOMATIC PISTOLS. ACCORDING TO THE EXPERTS, GEN. RUIZ WAS HIT THREE TIMES AND GEN GUSTAVO LEIGH WAS HIT FIVE TIMES. THE BULLETS HIT GEN. LEIGH IN HIS EYE, NOSE, RIGHT ARM, RIGHT LEG, AND STOMACH.

THE TWO ATTACKERS THEN WALKED DOWN THE STAIRS AND ESCAPED TOWARD PROVIDENCIA. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

THE GOVERNMENT HAS EXPRESSED ITS STRONG CONDEMNATION OF THE ATTACK ON GEN. GUSTAVO LEIGH, THE FORMER COMMANDER IN CHIEF OF THE AIR FORCE AND MEMBER OF THE MILITARY REGIME'S GOVERNMENT JUNTA. ON HIS WAY TO THE HOSPITAL ON EXPRESS ORDERS OF THE PRESIDENT, INTERIOR MINISTER ENRIQUE KRAUSS REJECTED THE ATTACK:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [KRAUSS] WE HAVE ASKED THE POLICE AUTHORITIES TO FULLY CLARIFY THIS INCIDENT. THESE ATTITUDES AND ACTS DO NOT HELP IN THE EFFORT REQUIRED TO REUNITE ALL CHILEANS. [END RECORDING]

KRAUSS SAID IT WAS A REGRETTABLE INCIDENT BECAUSE IT HURT THE SPIRIT AND PURPOSE OF THE GOVERNMENT AND OPPOSITION'S WORK. THE ATTACK AGAINST LEIGH WOULD MAKE A GOOD PATHOLOGICAL STUDY, THE MINISTER ADDED. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

THE NATIONAL COORDINATING BOARD FOR POLITICAL PRISONERS HAS SAID THE ATTACK ON GUSTAVO LEIGH DOES NOT REFLECT THE CURRENT SITUATION IN THE COUNTRY. COMMUNIST PARTY LEADER JORGE MARTINEZ, MOVEMENT OF THE REVOLUTIONARY LEFT [MIR] LEADER CARLOS RUIG, AND MANUEL RODRIGUEZ PATRIOTIC FRONT [FPMR] LEADER FRANCISCO ESCOBAR HEARD THE NEWS WHILE HOLDING A NEWS CONFERENCE AT THE PRISON HOUSE.

THE FPMR'S FRANCISCO ESCOBAR SAID HE IS SURE HIS ORGANIZATION WAS NOT INVOLVED IN THE INCIDENT BECAUSE, AS HE SAID, WE ARE NOT GOING TO ACHIEVE ANYTHING WITH IT. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

MIR REPRESENTATIVE CARLOS RUIG SAID THAT THE MIR WOULD NOT CARRY OUT ANY ARMED ACTION AT THIS TIME, IRRESPECTIVE OF THE LEVEL OF GEN. LEIGH'S INVOLVEMENT IN PAST REPRESSIONS.

COMMUNIST LEADER JORGE MARTINEZ SAID THAT HE IS COMMITTED TO RESPECTING THE DEMOCRATIC TRANSITION. HE SAID THAT HE DOES NOT BELIEVE THAT THIS TYPE OF ACTION WILL CONTRIBUTE TO THE COUNTRY'S PROGRESS AND STABILITY.

TST3-MUC4-0092

PANAMA CITY (PANAMA), 21 MAR 90 (CRITICA LIBRE) -- [ARTICLE] [JUSTINO GONZALEZ JR.] [TEXT] THE PANAMANIAN GOVERNMENT IS PREPARED TO FACE A RUPTURE OF DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS WITH MEXICO AND PERU TO ENFORCE THE LAW, FOREIGN MINISTER DR. JULIO E. LINARES ASSERTED WHEN REFERRING TO FORMER COLLABORATORS OF FORMER GENERAL NORIEGA WHO SOUGHT SHELTER IN THESE EMBASSIES SEVERAL WEEKS AGO.

THE MEXICAN EMBASSY IN PANAMA CITY HAS ANNOUNCED THAT IT HAS GRANTED DIPLOMATIC ASYLUM TO RAFAEL AROSEMENA, FORMER MANAGER OF THE NATIONAL BANK OF PANAMA. HOWEVER, THE PANAMANIAN AUTHORITIES HAVE CONFIRMED THAT THEY WOULD NOT GRANT HIM A SAFECONDUCT TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY, AND THEY SENT A NOTE TO THE MEXICAN EMBASSY URGING IT TO DESIST FROM OFFERING HIM PROTECTION.

ACCORDING TO THE PUBLIC PROSECUTOR'S OFFICE, RAFAEL AROSEMENA IS INVOLVED IN AUTHORIZING THE PAYMENT OF CHECKS FOR $12 MILLION, MADE OUT TO CASH BY FORMER COLONEL MARCOS JUSTINES. MEANWHILE, HERACLIDES SUCRE AND GONZALO GONZALEZ, FORMER MAJORS IN THE NOW DEFUNCT DEFENSE FORCES, HAVE SOUGHT ASYLUM AT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY IN PANAMA CITY. THEY ARE ACCUSED OF KILLING MAJOR MOISES GIROLDI, WHO LED THE FOILED COUP D'ETAT AGAINST NORIEGA IN OCTOBER 1989.

"WE ARE WILLING TO PAY WHATEVER PRICE IS NECESSARY TO ENFORCE THE LAW, BECAUSE THESE POLITICAL REFUGEES ARE COMMON CRIMINALS AND THEY HAVE NO RIGHT TO THAT BENEFIT," LINARES STATED WHEN ASKED BY CRITICA LIBRE IF PANAMA WOULD BE WILLING TO STOP THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE SOUGHT ASYLUM AT THE MEXICAN AND PERUVIAN EMBASSIES FROM LEAVING THE COUNTRY WITHOUT FACING A TRIAL FOR THE CRIMES THEY REPORTEDLY PERPETRATED DURING THE PREVIOUS REGIME.

LINARES SAID THAT PANAMA WILL MAINTAIN ITS POSITION OF NOT GRANTING SAFE-CONDUCTS TO THESE REFUGEES, EVEN IF THE MEXICAN AND PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT INSIST ON GRANTING THEM DIPLOMATIC ASYLUM, AND ADMITTED THAT THIS WILL LIKELY CREATE AN INTERNATIONAL CONFLICT.

NEVERTHELESS, LINARES SAID THAT HE HOPES THERE WILL BE NO NEED TO BREAK DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS WITH EITHER OF THESE COUNTRIES, WHICH INSIST ON KEEPING FORMER COLLABORATORS OF FORMER GEN NORIEGA AS REFUGEES, AND HE EMPHASIZED THE NEED TO REACH AN UNDERSTANDING WITH THESE NATIONS.

"WE HOPE THAT RELATIONS WITH MEXICO WILL NOT COOL OFF OR REACH A BREAKING POINT GIVEN THE AFFECTION THAT UNITES US AS FREE NATIONS," LINARES ADDED.

HE REVEALED THAT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY SENT A NOTE TO THE PANAMANIAN GOVERNMENT STATING THAT IT WILL CONTINUE TO GIVE DIPLOMATI PROTECTION TO THE REFUGEES IN ITS EMBASSY, BECAUSE LEGAL PROCEEDINGS WERE STARTED AGAINST THEM AFTER THEY HAD BEEN ACCEPTED BY THE DIPLOMATIC MISSION.

"WE ARE PREPARING A NOTE OF REPLY TO THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT," FOREIGN MINISTER LINARES SAID.

THE FOLLOWING PERSONS ARE STILL REFUGEES AT THE ECUADORAN EMBASSY: FORMER PUBLIC WORKS MINISTER RENE BULTRON, FORMER LABOR MINISTER CESAR MARTANS, FORMER NATIONAL MORTGAGE BANK MANAGER JULIO SHAIK, FORMER IRHE [INSTITUTE OF HYDRAULIC RESOURCES AND ELECTRIFICATION] DIRECTOR LEOVIGILDO HERRRERA, AND FORMER TOURISM DIRECTOR BERNARDO DOMINGUEZ.

LAST WEEK THE FOREIGN MINISTER REVIEWED THE POSSIBILITY OF GRANTING SAFE-CONDUCTS TO FIVE OF THESE FORMER OFFICIALS IN THE PREVIOUS REGIME, PROVIDED THERE IS NO CASE PENDING AGAINST THEM. ACCORDING TO THE OFFICIAL, THESE REFUGEES FACE CHARGES FOR PLOTTING AGAINST THE STATE'S SECURITY, A POLITICAL CRIME.

REFERRING TO THE CASE OF FORMER LEGISLATOR LUIS GOMEZ, WHO SOUGHT ASYLUM AT THE CUBAN EMBASSY, LINARES SAID THEY WILL HAVE TO MAKE AN EVALUATION.

TST3-MUC4-0093

BOGOTA, 23 MAR 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [REPORT] [ORLANDO GUERRERO] [TEXT] GOOD EVENING, A COMMUNIQUE HAS JUST BEEN ISSUED AT THE NATIONAL CAPITOL. THE COMMUNIQUE HAS BEEN SIGNED BY ALL THE DEMOCRATIC FORCES OF THE COUNTRY, WITH THE EXCEPTION OF THE LIBERAL PARTY. THE COMMUNIQUE ASKS THE GOVERNMENT TO OFFER FULL GUARANTEES DURING THE ELECTIONS PROCESS AND TO POSTPONE THE ELECTIONS. THE FOLLOWING IS THE COMMUNIQUE THAT HAS BEEN ISSUED IN THE ELIPTICO ROOM OF THE NATIONAL CAPITOL:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [UNIDENTIFIED SPEAKER] WE REPORT TO THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE AND THE PEOPLE OF THE WORLD THE FOLLOWING:

1. WE ONCE AGAIN CONDEMN THE VILE MURDER OF PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE DR. BERNARDO JARAMILLO. THIS MURDER HAS MADE EVIDENT THE LACK OF GUARANTEES IN THE COUNTRY, GUARANTEES THAT THE GOVERNMENT HAS SYSTEMATICALLY DENIED THE OPPOSITION PARTIES. WE REJECT THE MANIPULATIONS IN WHICH OFFICIAL ORGANIZATIONS ARE ENGAGED IN CONNECTION WITH INVESTIGATING THIS CRIME.

2. WE DENOUNCE THAT THE OFFICIAL APPARATUS IS AT THE SERVICE OF ONLY ONE CANDIDATE AND THAT IT IS PREPARED TO ESTABLISH PARTY PREDOMINANCE THAT WOULD IN PRACTICE BE A REJECTION OF DEMOCRATIC PLURALISM.

3. WE DEMAND FULL GUARANTEES FOR ALL THE FORCES PARTICIPATING IN THE ELECTIONS AND EQUITABLE ACCESS TO THE STATE MEDIA SO THAT THESE FORCES CAN MAKE KNOWN THEIR POLITICAL POSITIONS.

4. WE REQUEST GUARANTEES THAT THE NEW ELECTORAL SYSTEM WILL NOT HAVE THE SAME DIFFICULTIES THAT EXISTED DURING THE 11 MARCH ELECTIONS, THE RESULTS OF WHICH ARE STILL UNKNOWN.

5. UNDER THE CURRENT CONDITIONS, WE ASK OUR REPRESENTATIVES IN THE NATIONAL ELECTORAL COUNCIL TO ABSTAIN FROM PARTICIPATING IN DISCUSSIONS AND DECISIONS OF THAT COUNCIL.

6. IN VIEW OF THESE CIRCUMSTANCES, WE HAVE AGREED TO TEMPORARILY SUSPEND OUR ELECTION CAMPAIGNS AND DEMAND A POSTPONEMENT OF THE PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS SCHEDULED FOR 27 MAY.

7. WE INSIST THAT THE RATIFICATION OF CARLOS LEMOS SIMMONDS IN THE GOVERNMENT MINISTRY REPRESENTS THE BIGGEST OBSTACLE TO THE DEMOCRATIC OPPOSITION TO FINDING AN INSTITUTIONAL INTERLOCUTOR IN NATIONAL GOVERNMENT.

8. WE ANNOUNCE THE IMMEDIATE PRESENCE OF INTERNATIONAL [WORDS INDISTINCT] TO VERIFY THAT THE ELECTORAL GUARANTEES WE ARE DEMANDING ARE GRANTED AND TO OBSERVE THE ELECTIONS PROCESS.

9. THE PERMANENT COMMITTEE OF THE OPPOSITION HEREBY STATES ITS DECISION TO WORK FOR THE FORMATION OF A CONSTITUENT NATIONAL ASSEMBLY THAT MUST HAVE A DEMOCRATIC AND PLURALISTIC COMPOSITION WITH THE DECIDING PARTICIPATION OF THE NATIONAL [WORD INDISTINCT] TO APPROVE A NEW CONSTITUTION AND TO CONTRIBUTE TOWARD FINDING POLITICAL SOLUTIONS TO THE SOCIAL CONFLICT OF COLOMBIA. WE APPEAL TO THE LEADERS OF THE COUNTRY TO URGE THE NATIONAL GOVERNMENT TO DEFEND AND RESPECT HUMAN RIGHTS.

10. WE REITERATE OUR POSITION THAT THE ONLY WAY OUT OF THE ARMED CONFLICT IN THE COUNTRY IS A NEGOTIATED POLITICAL SOLUTION.

11. WE URGE THE LIBERAL PARTY TO POSTPONE ITS NATIONAL CONVENTION IN SOLIDARITY WITH THE PATRIOTIC UNION AND THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE.

12. WE ACKNOWLEDGE THE CATHOLIC CHURCH'S CALL AND WE WILL PROMOTE THIS CALL THROUGH THIS COMMITTEE.

13. IN DEFENSE OF A PLURALISTIC DEMOCRACY WE WILL MAINTAIN THE PERMANENT COMMITTEE OF THE OPPOSITION WE HAVE CREATED. WE HEREBY ASK OUR FOLLOWERS AND ALL OUR COUNTRYMEN TO REMAIN ON A STATE OF ALERT.

THIS COMMITTEE WILL HOLD A NEW MEETING TUESDAY 27 MARCH, AT 1500, IN THE CHAMBER OF REPRESENTATIVES. WE URGE ALL POLITICAL AND SOCIAL FORCES INTERESTED IN THESE OBJECTIVES TO ACTIVELY PARTICIPATE IN THIS MEETING.

RESOLUTION;

DEMOCRATIC SOCIALISM, THE POPULAR MOVEMENT [WORDS INDISTINCT], THE BROAD FRONT [WORDS INDISTINCT], THE NATIONALIST ACTION FOR PEACE, AND THE 19 APRIL MOVEMENT [M-19] WANT TO LEAVE ON RECORD THE FOLLOWING:

THE NEGOTIATION PROCESS BETWEEN THE NATIONAL GOVERNMENT AND M-19 THAT BEGAN ON 10 JANUARY 1989 AND THAT PRODUCED ON 9 MARCH 1990 A PEACE AGREEMENT WILL BE AFFECTED BY THE MURDER OF BERNARDO JARAMILLO, BUT WILL NOT RESULT IN AN END TO THE SEARCH FOR PEACE BY THE TWO PARTIES.

WE WILL CONTINUE TO WORK FOR A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE ARMED CONFLICT IN COLOMBIA. [END RECORDING]

TST3-MUC4-0094

SAN SALVADOR, 6 APR 90 (EL DIARIO DE HOY) -- [TEXT] FMLN-FDR [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT-REVOLUTIONARY DEMOCRATIC FRONT] TERRORIST GROUPS HAVE CONTINUED THEIR TREACHEROUS ATTACKS AGAINST CIVILIANS AND POLICE OFFICERS IN THE CAPITAL AND THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRYSIDE, OPENLY IGNORING THE AGREEMENTS REACHED BY THEIR LEADERS WITH A GOVERNMENT DELEGATION IN GENEVA, SWITZERLAND.

THE ARMED FORCES TELECOMMUNICATIONS INSTRUCTION CENTER (CITFA) REPORTED THAT A MAN AND A WOMAN WERE CRITICALLY WOUNDED WHEN THE VEHICLE IN WHICH THEY WERE TRAVELLING NEAR OLOCUILTA, LA PAZ DEPARTMENT, WAS MACHINEGUNNED BY FMLN TERRORISTS ON THE EVENING OF 4 APRIL.

THE WOUNDED ARE MAURICIO CAMPOS AND CONCEPCION HERRERA, WHO WERE TAKEN TO A HEALTH CENTER BY THE RED CROSS, THE SOURCES ADDED.

THE NATIONAL POLICE REPORTED THAT TWO OF ITS AGENTS AND A CIVILIAN WERE FIRED AT BY TERRORISTS AT 1800 ON 4 APRIL, AS THEY INSPECTED A CAR CRASH BETWEEN THE HIGHWAY TO COMALAPA AIRPORT AND 49TH SOUTH AVENUE IN THE MONTSERRAT NEIGHBORHOOD.

"THE POLICEMEN WERE MACHINEGUNNED DOWN BY PEOPLE IN A MOVING VEHICLE AND SUSTAINED WOUNDS WHICH HAVE LEFT THEM IN EXTREMELY CRITICAL CONDITION," A SECURITY CORPS SPOKESMAN SAID.

THE TWO AGENTS WERE ASSISTED BY PEOPLE WHO REPUDIATED THE ATTACK.

A PEDESTRIAN, LATER IDENTIFIED AS MANUEL ALVARO MENDOZA, WAS ALSO STRUCK BY THE BULLET AND HE IS AT ROSALES HOSPITAL.

A MILITARY SPOKESMAN ALSO REPORTED THAT A GROUP OF PERSONS WHO IDENTIFIED THEMSELVES AS FMLN-FDR MEMBERS KIDNAPPED A PEASANT, JOSE MANUEL POSADA, NEAR LA COLMENA, IN EL CARMEN DISTRICT, CUSCATLAN DEPARTMENT.

MEANWHILE, 9-YEAR-OLD YOHALMO ANTONIO ORTIZ WAS INJURED BY SHRAPNEL WHEN TERRORISTS THREW A BOMB AT CIVIL DEFENSE MEMBERS IN NEJAPA, NORTH OF SAN SALVADOR, WHILE HARASSING THE PARAMILITARY GROUP'S OUTPOST. THE BOY IS AT BLOOM HOSPITAL.

IN THE DOCUMENT SIGNED BY THE GOVERNMENT DELEGATION AND THE FMLN-FDR LEADERS, THE LATTER PLEDGED NOT TO ENGAGE IN TERRORISTS ATTACKS THAT MIGHT DAMAGE ASSETS OR INJURE PERSONS, BUT "URBAN COMMANDOS" OR "TERRORISTS SQUADS" THAT OPERATE IN SAN SALVADOR HAVE EITHER NOT BEEN INFORMED OF THIS RESOLUTION OR THEY ACT INDEPENDENTLY, THE MILITARY SOURCES SAID.

REFERRING TO THE 2 APRIL CAR BOMB EXPLOSION PERPETRATED IN SANTA TECLA, THE FMLN-FDR CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACK IN A COMMUNIQUE, AND SAID THAT IT WAS "AN ACTION AIMED DIRECTLY AT THE POLICE" AND THAT "THEY REGRET THE DEATH OF A CIVILIAN," BUT THEY DID NOT MENTION COMPENSATION FOR THE RELATIVES.

ALSO, THE FMLN-FDR CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACK ON GENERAL RAFAEL HUMBERTO LARIOS'S SON-IN-LAW, ACCUSING HIM OF BEING A MILITARY PILOT -- WHEN IN FACT HE HAS BEEN A CIVILIAN PILOT AND HE WAS WORKING IN A SMALL AUTOMOBILE SPARE PARTS DISTRIBUTION COMPANY AT THE TIME OF THE ATTACK.

THE YOUNG MAN, OTTO MILLA, IS STILL IN A COMA AND HIS PANCREAS WAS REMOVED IN THE LATEST SURGICAL OPERATION.

TST3-MUC4-0095

NO CITY, NO DATE (FBIS) -- [EDITORIAL REPORT] [TEXT] FOLLOWING IS A COMPILATION OF REPORTS ON DRUG SEIZURES AND ARRESTS RELATED TO DRUG TRAFFICKING IN BUREAU COVERAGE AREA FROM 15 TO 21 APRIL.

COLOMBIA

THE COLOMBIAN POLICE TODAY CONFISCATED A 162 KG SHIPMENT OF PURE COCAINE FROM THE CARIBBEAN PORT OF SANTA MARTA, MAGDALENA DEPARTMENT. THE COCAINE WAS TO BE SHIPPED TO GENOA, ITALY, IT WAS OFFICIALLY REPORTED.

ACCORDING TO THE PORT POLICE COMMANDER MAJOR ORLANDO REYES, THIS SHIPMENT IS ONE OF THE LARGEST CONFISCATED IN THE PAST FEW MONTHS. LAST AUGUST THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT DECLARED "WAR" ON DRUG TRAFFICKING MAFFIAS.

THE CONFISCATION OF THE COCAINE OCCURRED AS THE COLOMBIAN AUTHORITIES WERE PURSUING THREE SICILIAN GANGSTERS WHO RECENTLY CAME TO COLOMBIA TO NEGOTIATE LARGER DRUG SHIPMENTS TO EUROPE WITH THE CARTELS.

ECUADOR

EARLY ON THE MORNING OF 20 APRIL, AN ECUADORAN ARMY PATROL SEIZED A BOAT SAILING THE SAN MIGUEL RIVER AND FOUND 83 55-GALLON BARRELS OF ACETONE, WHICH IS USED TO PROCESS COCAINE. THE BOAT'S DESTINATION WAS APPARENTLY PUTUMAYO, COLOMBIA. ONE COLOMBIAN AND TWO ECUADOREANS WERE ARRESTED.

MEXICO

THE FEDERAL JUDICIAL POLICE HAS REPORTED THAT APPROXIMATELY 6.5 TONS OF MARIJUANA AND A CLANDESTINE AIRSTRIP WERE FOUND IN SAN JUAN NEPOMUCENO MUNICIPALITY IN CHIHUAHUA STATE. POLICE ARRESTED 20-YEAR OLD JOSE ANTONIO ROBLES GARCIA AND 30-YEAR OLD JOSE GUADAULUPE BENAVIDES CARBAJOLD. THE SUSPECTS HAD ATTEMPTED TO HIDE THE MARIJUANA IN PAPAYA SHIPMENTS TO THE UNITED STATES.

MEXICAN DRUG AGENTS HAVE ARRESTED U.S. CITIZEN STEVEN ANDREW HENRY FOR POSSESSION OF 8 KG OF COCAINE. THE POLICE FOUND TRACES OF COCAINE WHEN THEY SEARCHED HIS VEHICLE ON A ROAD NEAR CHETUMAL AND WHEN THEY WENT TO HIS HOUSE ON PUNTA PUNTITIC BEACH, SOUTH OF CANCUN, THEY FOUND 8 KG OF COCAINE.

FEDERAL JUDICIAL POLICE AGENTS HAVE ARRESTED FIVE MEMBERS OF A DRUG TRAFFICKING GANG AND SEIZED 1 KG OF PURE COCAINE AT A CLANDESTINE AIRSTRIP IN OCAMPO MUNICIPALITY IN COAHUILA STATE. THE POLICE ARRESTED ABELICA GARCIA SANCHEZ, FRANCISCO VASQUEZ SANCHEZ, ALFREDO VILLAREAL GUZMAN, JESUS PRESAS ARREDONDO, AND FERNANDO QUINTELA GALINDO. THE AIRSTRIP WAS BEING USED TO BRING IN DRUGS FROM COLOMBIA. THE DRUGS WERE THEN UNLOADED AND TAKEN TO THE UNITED STATES THROUGH SANTA ELENA, LOCATED 40 KM FROM PIEDRITAS.

FEDERAL JUDICIAL POLICE AGENTS HAVE ARRESTED THREE U.S. CITIZENS AND A MEXICAN WHO OPERATED A CLANDESTINE LABORATORY TO PRODUCE CRACK IN PUERTO PENASCO, SONORA STATE. JOHN MURPHY, DIANA FOSTER, DANY CHILDRES, AND JOSE GONZALEZ OLIVA WERE ARRESTED.

ATTORNEY GENERAL ENRIQUE ALVAREZ DEL CASTILLO REPORTED IN IXTAPA ON 20 APRIL THAT THE POLICE SEIZED 2.2 TONS OF PURE COCAINE WHEN THEY ARRESTED THE MEMBERS OF A DRUG TRAFFICKING GANG IN CABORCA, SONORA STATE.

THE MEXICAN POLICE HAVE DEALT A HUGE BLOW TO DRUG TRAFFICKING BY SEIZING MORE THAN 1.5 TONS OF COCAINE BASE DURING AN OPERATION IN CULIACAN, SINALOA STATE. DRUG AGENTS ARRESTED THREE MEMBERS OF THE DRUG TRAFFICKING GANG.

POLICE IN SONORA, MEXICO SEIZED 2,536 KG OF PURE COCAINE, THE LARGEST SEIZURE OF THE YEAR SO FAR, IT WAS ANNOUNCED TODAY. AT A NEWS CONFERENCE THE AUTHORITIES SAID THAT THE COCAINE WAS SEIZED BETWEEN 17 AND 19 APRIL NEAR THE TOWN OF CABORCA, WHERE POLICE DISCOVERED CLANDESTINE LANDING STRIPS, PRESUMABLY USED BY AIRPLANES COMING FROM COLOMBIA. DURING A SHOOTOUT BETWEEN POLICEMEN AND APPROXIMATELY 10 PRESUMED DRUG TRAFFICKERS, NINE OF THE LATTER ESCAPED AND ONE WAS CAPTURED. SINCE PRESIDENT SALINAS DE GORTARI TOOK OFFICE IN DECEMBER 1988, MEXICAN AUTHORITIES HAVE SEIZED MORE THAN 45 TONS OF COCAINE.

TST3-MUC4-0096

BOGOTA, 26 APR 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] GOOD AFTERNOON, WE HAVE JUST RECEIVED A STATEMENT ISSUED BY PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO VARGAS CONCERNING THE MURDER OF MR. CARLOS PIZARRO LEONGOMEZ. THE MESSAGE READS AS FOLLOWS:

CARLOS PIZARRO'S MURDER IS A MONSTROUS CRIME THAT HAS CUT SHORT THE LIFE OF A MAN WHO HAD SHOWN HIS WILL FOR PEACE AND HIS COMMITMENT TO COLOMBIA. THE CRIME WAS DIRECTED AT HINDERING THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE ELECTORAL PROCESS AND DESTROYING THE RECONCILIATION PROCESS THAT THE GOVERNMENT AND M-19 [19 APRIL MOVEMENT] CAREFULLY CONSTRUCTED, SURPASSING MANY OBSTACLES. IN THIS CASE, AS IN MANY OTHERS, THIS PAINFUL TRAGEDY SHOULD SERVE TO CONSOLIDATE THE IDEALS OF PEACE AND PLURALISM FOR WHICH SO MANY COLOMBIANS HAVE STRUGGLED -- ONE OF THEM, CARLOS PIZARRO. IT SHOULD SERVE TO REASSERT OUR REPUDIATION OF VIOLENCE AND OUR FAITH IN DEMOCRATIC PROCEDURES.

FURTHER ON THE PRESIDENT'S MESSAGE NOTES:

PIZARRO'S RELATIVES AND HIS FOLLOWERS KNOW THAT THE GOVERNMENT, AND I PERSONALLY, FEEL STRONG WRATH AND SADNESS, BUT WE WILL NOT BE DISCOURAGED. WE WILL UPHOLD THE BANNERS OF RECONCILIATION, PLURALISM, AND THE RIGHT TO FREELY AND PEACEFULLY EXPRESS ANY IDEA. WE WILL ALSO CONTINUE TO UNMASK AND COMBAT ENEMIES OF PEACE.

THE PRESIDENT ADDS IN HIS MESSAGE:

I INTERPRET THE DESIRE OF ALL COLOMBIANS WHO ADMIRED CARLOS PIZARRO'S DEMOCRATIC VOCATION, BY WARNING THOSE WHO ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR THIS TRAGIC MURDER THAT THEY WILL NOT MANAGE TO DESTROY WHAT HAS BEEN WORKED FOR SO HARD AND WITH THE SUPPORT OF POLITICAL FORCES AND THE PEOPLE WHO VOTED FOR PEACE ON 11 MARCH TO OPEN A ROAD FOR PEACE THAT IS CLEAR, POSSIBLE, AND DEFINED.

THE PRESIDENT'S MESSAGE CONTINUES:

YOU KNOW THAT DURING THIS PEACE PROCESS, MANY ENEMIES AND DIFFICULTIES WERE SURPASSED, BUT NONE HAS BEEN SO LARGE AS THIS TRAGEDY THAT HAS SHAKEN ALL COLOMBIANS. THE OBLIGATION THAT LIES BEFORE US IS TO KEEP OPEN THE ROAD TO PEACE THAT THE MURDERERS OF CARLOS PIZARRO WANT TO DESTROY. ARTICLE 95 OF THE ELECTORAL CODE INDICATES THAT WHEN A PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE DIES, ANOTHER PERSON IN HIS OWN MOVEMENT HAS THE RIGHT TO TAKE HIS PLACE. IN COMPLIANCE WITH THIS NORM, THE GOVERNMENT WILL OFFER EVERY FACILITY FOR THE REGISTRY OF A NEW M-19 PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE, SO THAT HE CAN CONTINUE TO HOIST THE FLAGS OF PEACE AND PLURALISM AS IS PROPER FOR A DEMOCRATIC DEBATE.

THE PRESIDENT ALSO SAYS IN HIS MESSAGE:

I HAVE ASKED THE GOVERNMENT MINISTER AND THE PEACE ADVISER TO MEET AS SOON AS POSSIBLE WITH M-19 REPRESENTATIVES SO THAT TOGETHER THEY MAY STUDY ALTERNATIVES TO CONFRONT SUCH A SERIOUS SITUATION. AS SOON AS POSSIBLE, THE GOVERNMENT MINISTER WILL ALSO DIRECT CONTACTS WITH THE REST OF THE POLITICAL FORCES TO REQUEST THEIR OPINIONS ABOUT THE PRESENT SITUATION AND TO CONTINUE TO GIVE ALL THE NECESSARY GUARANTEES SO THAT THE ELECTORAL PROCESS MAY DEVELOP ACCORDING TO WHAT IS ESTABLISHED IN THE CONSTITUTION AND OUR LAWS.

THE MESSAGE ENDS:

I INVITE ALL COLOMBIANS WHO ARE TIRED OF SO MUCH VIOLENCE TO COME TO THE POLLS IN THE NEXT ELECTIONS AND VOTE FOR PEACE AND PLURALISM. I INVITE ALL POLITICAL AND SOCIAL FORCES TO JOIN IN SOLIDARITY WITH THE ELECTORAL PROCESS AND DEFEND THE INSTITUTIONS THAT ARE THREATENED BY VIOLENCE. IT IS TIME FOR GOOD SENSE AND PRUDENCE. IT IS TIME TO RISE TO THE OCCASION AND SHOW OUR COMMITMENT TO DEMOCRACY.

THIS IS THE TEXT OF PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO'S MESSAGE ON THE MURDER MR. CARLOS PIZARRO LEONGOMEZ.

TST3-MUC4-0097

SAN SALVADOR, 3 MAY 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] GUERRILLA GROUPS HAVE REPORTED 185 SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES CASUALTIES DURING CLASHES WHICH OCCURRED IN THE LAST FEW HOURS IN SIX OF THE COUNTRY'S 14 DEPARTMENTS, BUT THE ARMY CLAIMS THAT IT ONLY SUSTAINED 48 CASUALTIES IN THOSE CLASHES.

ACCORDING TO RADIO FARABUNDO MARTI, A RADIO STATION OF THE GUERRILLA GROUP, THE CASUALTIES WERE SUSTAINED BY THE ARMED FORCES IN CLASHES WHICH OCCURRED ON 1 AND 2 MAY AND EARLY THIS MORNING WHEN SEVERAL AMBUSHES, ATTACKS, AND SABOTAGE AIMED AT THE ECONOMY WERE CARRIED OUT IN SEVERAL PLACES THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY.

RADIO FARABUNDO MARTI HAS REPORTED THAT THE MILITARY ACTIONS, THE LARGEST SINCE THE REBEL OFFENSIVE IN NOVEMBER 1989, WHICH RESULTED IN THOUSANDS OF CASUALTIES, IS PART OF THE "WITH THE WORKERS AND FOR DEMOCRACY" MILITARY CAMPAIGN.

THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN], WHICH DOES NOT GIVE DETAILS ON ITS CASUALTIES, HAS SAID THAT THE ARMED FORCES SUSTAINED 30 CASUALTIES IN ILOBASCO, CABANAS DEPARTMENT, LOCATED APPROXIMATELY 55 KM FROM SAN SALVADOR.

NEVERTHELESS, ACCORDING TO MILITARY REPORTS ISSUED EIGHT HOURS AFTER THE CLASHES IN THAT TOWN, THE ARMED FORCES KILLED 11 GUERRILLA MEMBERS AND SUSTAINED SIX CASUALTIES.

RADIO FARABUNDO MARTI HAS ALSO REPORTED THAT THE GUERRILA FORCES CAUSED 28 ARMY CASUALTIES IN CLASHES ON 2 MAY IN LA LAGUNA, CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT, LOCATED APPROXIMATELY 90 KM NORTH OF SAN SALVADOR.

THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE (COPREFA) ADMITTED THAT THE GOVERNMENT TROOPS SUSTAINED 11 CASUALTIES IN THESE CLASHES, ADDING THAT THEY INFLICTED THREE CASUALTIES ON THE REBELS. COPREFA ALSO REPORTED THAT 26 HOUSES WERE DAMAGED.

COPREFA ALSO REPORTS THAT MILITARY ACTIONS HAVE OCCURRED IN CABANAS, LA LIBERTAD, CHALATENANGO, SANTA ANA, LA LIBERTAD, AND SAN SALVADOR DEPARTMENTS DURING THE PAST TWO DAYS. IN SOME PLACES THE ELECTRICAL SYSTEMS WERE SABOTAGED, CAUSING LONG BLACKOUTS.

THE GUERRILLA FORCES' GENERAL COMMAND ISSUED A COMMUNIQUE IN SAN SALVADOR ON 2 MAY, STATING THAT THE MILITARY ACTIONS ARE IN RESPONSE TO "THE TRIUMPHANT AND ARROGANT ATTITUDE OF THE GOVERNMENT AND THE MILITARY, FOR THE FMLN'S ALLEGED WEAKNESS, WHICH PRECLUDES THE NEGOTIATION PROCESS."

THE COMMUNIQUE REASSERTS THEIR WILLINGNESS TO CONTINUE THE NEGOTIATION PROCESS WITH THE GOVERNMENT TO END A WAR WHICH HAS LASTED MORE THAN A DECADE. THE NEGOTIATION PROCESS IS BEING UNDERTAKEN WITH THE MEDIATION OF UN SECRETARY GENERAL JAVIER PEREZ DE CUELLAR.

PEREZ DE CUELLAR'S SPECIAL ENVOY, ALVARO DE SOTO, ARRIVED IN SAN SALVADOR ON 2 MAY AS PART OF THE NEGOTIATIONS. HE MET WITH PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI AND THE NATIONAL DIALOGUE COMMISSION TODAY, AND LATER HE WILL MEET WITH OTHER LEADERS.

GUILLERMO UNGO, SECRETARY GENERAL OF THE SOCIAL DEMOCRATIC NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT (MNR), TOLD ACAN-EFE THAT OPPOSITION LEADERS COULD "POSSIBLY" MEET WITH FMLN DELEGATES IN MEXICO CITY TO LEARN THEIR VIEWS CONCERNING THE NEGOTIATIONS.

"THE MEETING WILL HAVE AN OPEN AGENDA SO THAT EVERYONE'S POSITION CAN BE HEARD AND SO THAT THE ROLE OF THE POLITICAL PARTIES IN THE NEGOTIATIONS CAN BE DETERMINED," UNGO SAID.

TST3-MUC4-0098

SAN SALVADOR, 7 MAY 90 (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [REPORT] [JULIO ERNESTO RODRIGUEZ] [TEXT] SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI STATED TODAY THAT IT WOULD BE NO PROBLEM FOR THE FOURTH PENAL JUDGE, WHO IS IN CHARGE OF THE CASE OF THE JESUITS MURDERED BY A GROUP OF SOLDIERS, TO ORDER THAT CADETS WHO ARE TAKING COURSES ABROAD RETURN TO THE COUNTRY. IT WAS RECENTLY REPORTED THAT SEVERAL OFFICERS WHO TESTIFIED DURING THESE INVESTIGATIONS ARE NOW ATTENDING TRAINING COURSES ABROAD. IT WAS ALSO REPORTED THAT THE MILITARY SCHOOL'S REGISTRATION BOOK FOR PERSONS ENTERING OR LEAVING THE PREMISES HAD BEEN LOST, INCLUDING THE PAGES THAT CORRESPOND TO NOVEMBER 1989. TODAY, CRISTIANI TALKED ABOUT THIS MATTER AND SAID THE JUDGE SHOULD CONTINUE TO INVESTIGATE AND NOT JUST MAKE STATEMENTS CONCERNING THE PROBLEMS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CRISTIANI] I DO NOT BELIEVE THERE IS ANY PROBLEM IN THE OFFICERS RETURNING TO THE COUNTRY IF A JUDGE ORDERS THAT THEY COME TO TESTIFY. ALL THAT IS REQUIRED IS FOR THE JUDGE TO SUMMON THEM; THEY WOULD BE BROUGHT TO THE COUNTRY TO TESTIFY AND, AFTER THAT, RETURNED TO THEIR TRAINING COURSES. GROUPS OF SOLDIERS ARE FREQUENTLY SENT ABROAD TO TAKE TRAINING COURSES TO MAKE THEM MORE PROFESSIONAL; THIS APPLIES NOT ONLY TO PERSONNEL FROM THE MILITARY SCHOOL, BUT FROM ALL ARMED FORCES UNITS.

CONCERNING THE OTHER MATTER, THE JUDGE HAS TO INVESTIGATE IT. I BELIEVE THAT INSTEAD OF JUST STAYING THERE, THE JUDGE SHOULD CONTINUE TO SEARCH FOR EVIDENCE. TELL ME, WHAT IS THE DIFFERENCE IF THEY ARE BROUGHT BACK FROM SUCHITOTO OR FROM THE UNITED STATES IF THEY MUST TESTIFY BEFORE THE JUDGE? THERE IS NO DIFFERENCE AT ALL. [END RECORDING]

THE PRESIDENT SPOKE TODAY AT THE EL SALVADOR MILITARY AIRPORT BEFORE HE LEFT FOR COSTA RICA TO ATTEND THE INAUGURATION CEREMONY OF PRESIDENT-ELECT RAFAEL CALDERON FOURNIER. HE ALSO SAID THAT THE UNITED STATES CONDITIONING 50 PERCENT OF THE AID GIVEN TO OUR COUNTRY COULD CAUSE THE REBEL FRONT TO INCREASE THEIR ACTIONS. HE ACCUSED THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] OF USING DIALOGUE FOR TACTICAL REASONS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CRISTIANI] WE HAVE STATED THAT AN ACTION OF THIS TYPE WOULD BE VERY UNTIMELY, AS IT COULD MAKE THE MOST RADICAL FMLN MEMBERS DECIDE TO CONTINUE THE WAR AND, THUS, HINDER THE DIALOGUE PROCESS.

[REPORTER] HOWEVER, [WORDS INDISTINCT] PRESSURE GOVERNMENT FOR THEM [WORDS INDISTINCT] WITH FMLN.

[CRISTIANI] I WOULD ASK THE QUESTION: WHO HAS ALWAYS SHOWED GOODWILL AND SINCERELY SOUGHT AN AGREEMENT AND WHO HAS NOT DONE THIS? HISTORY SHOWS THAT IN THE PAST, THE FMLN HAS USED THE PROPOSALS BY [JOSE NAPOLEON] DUARTE'S GOVERNMENT AND MY OWN FOR TACTICAL REASONS. IT HAS NOT BEEN THE GOVERNMENTS. I BELIEVE THAT THE FMLN MUST UNDERSTAND AND BE PRESSURED TO REALLY SEARCH FOR A POLITICAL SOLUTION. [END RECORDING]

ALSO TODAY, THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL AUTHORIZED A SPOKESMAN TO ANNOUNCE THAT TALKS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND FMLN WILL BE RENEWED ON 16 MAY. THE PANORAMA THAT SURROUNDS THIS NEW ENCOUNTER, HOWEVER, PRESENTS AN ENTIRELY DIFFERENT PATTERN FROM MEETINGS IN THE PAST, BECAUSE BOTH SECTORS HAVE MET WITH POLITICAL PARTIES REPRESENTED AT THE [WORD INDISTINCT]. FURTHERMORE, ALTHOUGH THE GOVERNMENT HAS NOT DONE THE SAME WITH THE COUNTRY'S SOCIAL FORCES, THE REBELS WILL TRY TO DO SO THIS WEEK. UNDOUBTEDLY, THE RESULTS THAT COULD BE OBTAINED FROM THE DIALOGUE COULD BE MUCH MORE IMPORTANT THAN THOSE OBTAINED DURING PAST NEGOTIATIONS, BECAUSE ALMOST ALL THE SECTORS THAT HAVE BECOME INVOLVED, DIRECTLY OR INDIRECTLY, IN THE NEGOTIATING DEMAND THAT THE AGREEMENTS ATTAINED BE BASED ON INTERNAL COOPERATION.

TST3-MUC4-0099

SAN SALVADOR, 1 JUN 90 (AFP) -- [TEXT] OFFICIAL SOURCES HAVE REPORTED BLACKOUTS IN MANY PARTS OF THE COUNTRY BECAUSE OF GUERRILLAS SABOTAGING THE ELECTRIC POWER SYSTEM DURING THE NIGHT OF 31 MAY AND THE MORNING OF 1 JUNE.

ACCORDING TO A MILITARY BULLETIN, THE GUERRILLAS DESTROYED 12 ELECTRIC POLES AND 2 POWER PYLONS IN THE CENTRAL AND WESTERN PARTS OF THE COUNTRY IN LESS THAN 12 HOURS.

IN THE EASTERN PART OF THE COUNTRY, THE LEMPA RIVER HYDROELECTRIC EXECUTIVE COMMISSION (CEL) REPORTED THAT ONE OF THE COUNTRY'S MAIN POWER LINES WAS OUT OF SERVICE ON THE MORNING OF 1 JUNE BECAUSE A NUMBER OF PYLONS WERE DESTROYED.

THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE (COPREFA) REPORTED THAT ON THE MORNING OF 1 JUNE GUERRILLAS, USING MORTARS AND RIFLES, ATTACKED A CEL SUB-STATION IN THE NATIVIDAD CANTON IN THE WESTERN DEPARTMENT OF SANTA ANA. THERE WERE NO CASUALTIES, BUT THE GUERRILLAS HAD DAMAGED A TRANSFORMER.

ON THE MORNING OF 1 JUNE, THERE WAS A BLACKOUT THROUGHOUT MOST OF THE CAPITAL CAUSED BY URBAN COMMANDOS OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN).

THE GUERRILLAS HAVE INCREASED THEIR ACTIVITY ON THE FIRST ANNIVERSARY OF PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT. CRISTINAI IS SCHEDULED TO ADDRESS THE NATION ON 1 JUNE TO COMMENT ON HIS FIRST YEAR IN OFFICE.

THE ARMY HAS INCREASED ITS PATROLS AIDED BY HELICOPTERS THAT OVERFLY THE CAPITAL CITY.

COPREFA REPORTED THAT ONE SOLDIER WAS KILLED AND SEVEN WERE WOUNDED ON 1 JUNE DURING AN AMBUSH OF A MILITARY CONVOY NEAR TEXISTEPEQUE, WEST OF SAN SALVADOR.

ACCORDING TO COPREFA, ANOTHER SOLDIER WAS WOUNDED IN A GUERRILLA AMBUSH AGAINST THE ELITE BRACAMONTE BATTALION ON A HIGHWAY IN CENTRAL EL SALVADOR.